Recording in progress.
Good evening and welcome to the June
22nd city council meeting. I will uh I
Mayor Collins is not available tonight
so we'll have to suffer through me. I
apologize in advance. Uh with that could
um could we call roll please?
>> Mr. White
>> present.
>> Mr. Wolf
>> here.
>> Dr. Aldrich present. Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Dr. Emmens
>> present.
>> Mr. Esabel
>> here.
>> Mr. Leborn
>> present.
>> Mr. Moody
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Mr. Cray
>> present.
>> Two members are absent. We do have a
quorum.
>> Thank you very much. Uh, one thing I
forgot is please silence your uh,
devices for us. And with that, can we
say the pledge of allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> With that first item, please.
>> Consent agenda. All agenda items listed
with the designation of CA are
considered to be routine items by the
governing body and will be enacted by
one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
in support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
>> All right. Are there any items that a
council member would like removed from
the consent agenda?
[clears throat]
>> Mr. President.
>> Councilman Lebornne.
Number 19, please.
Uh 19. Is there a
>> concur? Concur.
>> 19 will be removed. Are there any other
items that we would like removed?
With that, uh I would take a motion to
I'm sorry.
>> Move to approve.
>> Second. We have a motion by Dr.
Aldridge, second by Councilman Esabel.
All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. unanimous uh dis um decision on
the consent agenda. Next item, please.
>> Number six, ordinance, third reading,
defining the terms and conditions of
employment for sworn officers of the
Cheyenne Police Department for July 2026
until the end of fiscal year 2027.
>> This item um sets forth the police
department um employment
uh regulations for the year. Um we'll
open it up to discussion online.
Jennifer, is there anybody online that
would like to to discuss this?
There's no one online. We'll close that.
Anyone in the room that would like to
discuss this?
Anyone in the room? Seeing none, could I
have a motion, please? Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on third
and final reading. And I so move.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion by Councilman Esel,
second by uh Councilman Moody.
Discussion from the DAS.
discussion.
>> I have one question. Uh
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Councilman Crave, uh through you. I am
just want to uh confirm that the extra
duty pay um I believe if I read this
correctly is limited to one extra duty.
>> Um who could help us with that?
>> James. Captain James.
>> Captain James.
>> Uh Councilman Crave. Captain David
Jenkins Shine Police Department. Our on
call specialty pay is limited to two per
officer.
>> So that did not change in this.
>> Correct. That did not change.
>> Thank you, sir. Further discussion on
the DS discussion.
>> Hearing none. Could we um take roll
call, please?
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. White.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Mr. Moody.
>> I
>> uh unanimous vote. Uh motion is
approved. Uh next item, please.
>> Number seven, ordinance, third reading,
amending section 1.3.11,
nonconformities 1.4.4, definitions,
1.4.5, interpretation of zoning map
2.2.7, special use approval. 5.1.2
zoning districts established and 5.1.4
use table and creating 5.6 6.10 regional
entertainment re overlay district and
5.7.13
gaming center development standards and
setting an effective date for
compliance.
>> This item came about uh the legislature
changed um who is allowed to decide
where gaming or historic horse racing,
some people call them casinos, uh can be
located. In the past it was uh the
county commissioners that made that
decision. So what we've done is create
an ordinance that discusses where they
can be established by right. Uh
basically that's in your commercial
areas. So that's what we're discussing
tonight and we'll certainly open it up
to the public. Jennifer, is there anyone
online that would like to discuss this?
There's no one online, so we'll close
that. How about in the audience? Anyone
here that would like to to discuss this
uh in front of the council? Yes, ma'am.
Please identify yourself. And
>> thank you. Uh Tracy Lake, general
counsel for Wyoming Downs and 307 horse
racing. Excuse me. Thank you. Just
quickly, um [clears throat] we do
encourage you to support the substitute
that was discussed by the public
services committee. Um that will ensure
that all of the locations
um have time to then apply for the
special use uh in front of you all. and
we do appreciate all the hard work from
the planning commission um and the
public services committee on this issue.
Thank you.
>> Thank you so much. Anyone else?
>> Seeing none. Uh could I have a
>> President Crave? Can I just for the
record um announce that Dr. Renie did
join the meeting at 6:06 p.m.
>> Fabulous. Thank you. Welcome Dr. Renie.
Um could we have a motion please? Doc
Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion by Dr. Aldridge, second
by Dr. Emmans.
>> Mr. President, I move to amend by
substitute dated June 15, 2026.
>> Second.
>> We have a a motion to amend and a
second. Uh uh can you describe the
motion for us? The amendment.
>> Sorry. Uh, President Crave, the
amendment was to clarify the um concern
that had been brought forward with um
where these could be located in um
conjunction with childcare centers and
facilities.
>> Yes, we'll open it up online discussion.
Jennifer, anyone to discuss the
amendment?
No one online. We'll close that. How
about how about in the uh room here?
Anyone that would like to discuss the
proposed amendment? Anyone
seeing none, we'll bring it up to the
dis discussion on the amendment.
Anyone?
All right, we'll take a vote on the
amendment. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> Unanimously approved the amendment.
We're back to the main motion on the
overlay district.
Discussion on the dis. Seeing none,
could we take the vote, please?
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Escoel.
>> I.
>> Mr. Lebornne.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> I.
>> Uh. Unanimous. Unanimously approved the
amended ordinance. Next item, please.
>> Number eight, ordinance, third reading,
amending chapter 15.20, 20 National
Electrical Code Adopted. Appendix K,
International Building Code,
Administrative Provisions Adopted of
Title 15, Buildings and Construction of
the Municipal Code of the City of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, updating the
incorporated national electrical code
provisions as specified.
>> This item is in front of the governing
body. Uh when the National Electrical
Code changes, we're required to uh
update our ordinances to comply with
state statutes. So, that's what we're
doing here tonight. Um, with that,
Jennifer, is there anyone online that
would like to discuss the changes to the
National Electrical Code as adopted?
No one online. How about in the room? Is
there anyone in the room that would like
to discuss this?
Anyone?
Seeing none, we'll close discussion on
that. And Dr. Aldrich, could we have a a
motion, please?
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Second by Councilman Wolf. Discussion on
the DAS.
Discussion.
>> Hearing none. Uh, could we take the the
roll call, please?
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf?
>> Dr. Aldridge?
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Mr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Esel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Labour.
>> This item is unanimously adopted. Next
item, please.
>> Number nine. Ordinance, second reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming. Land located south of Charles
Street, east of Wanandi Avenue and west
of McKinley Avenue.
>> This is a U owner owner requested ordin
um annexation. Uh is there anyone online
that would like to discuss this proposed
annexation?
Uh, no one online. How about in the
audience here? Anyone that would like to
discuss this annexation?
>> Anyone hearing? None. We'll close public
comment and we'll ask for a motion. Dr.
Aldrich.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Motion by Dr. Aldrich, second by Dr.
Emmens. Discussion on councel
discussion.
Seeing none, all in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. The recommendation for uh the
committee next week is to approve uh
unanimously. Next item, please. Number
10, ordinance, second reading, amending
the official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, establishing the zoning
classification of AR agricultural
residential for land annex to the city
of Cheyenne, located south of Charles
Street, east of Wanandi Avenue, and west
of McKinley Avenue.
>> When we move to annex a piece of
property, we try to uh set uh create the
zoning for it as it was in the county.
In this case, it was agricultural. So
that's what this ordinance does is
create an agricultural zone for the uh
item we just just heard. Is there anyone
online that would like to discuss this?
Okay, we do have I'm sorry, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> All right. Um, this is agenda item
number 10.
>> Yes.
>> Um, I'm placing a uh
members of the council, Charles Miller,
for the record. I'm placing a formal
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you, sir.
>> I'm placing a formal constructive notice
of legal invalid invalidity onto the
administrative record regarding agenda
item number 10. [clears throat] This
ordinance attempts to assign an
agricultural residential zoning
classification to the 2.69 69 acre
parcel on Charles Street. Is that is
that correct? 2.69 acres.
>> Mr. Mr. President,
>> council move.
>> Uh point of uh order,
>> would you guys stop my time, please?
>> Um
if you want to. Um
>> u
Mr. President,
>> Mr. Miller, Mr. Miller, we have the
floor.
>> Mr. President, there is no job in the
city job descriptions or anywhere else
that describes a grand overseer of our
planning and zoning undertakings.
Planning and zoning is a sightspecific
issue.
We if unless Mr. Miller actually owns
the land or is within the zone of
interest in which he would be entitled
to receive notice.
His comments, he has no standing to make
these comments.
>> A point of order.
>> President Crave.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh this is a citizen and every citizen
in our community has a right to make a
comment on any item on our agenda.
That's why we have open meeting laws.
>> All right, Mr. Miller. We're we're
talking about zoning for a 2.69 piece
parcel zoning at agriculture which it
currently is in the county. Please hold
your comments to that.
>> Go ahead and start.
>> Is it is there uh is Mr. Wolf able to um
explain a little bit more about uh where
he was coming from. He he is an
attorney. So I'm wondering if there was
actually something of substance that was
going to be uh shared there. Is
>> we can we will ask him but your clock is
running. Mr. Wolf, would you like to
answer his question? Well,
if you look at the cases that have
interpreted who can challenge zoning
decisions, it's limited to the people
who are directly impacted by them,
either the the neighboring residents or
the land owner themselves. Particularly,
we have heard from Mr. Miller when he
has questioned the notice uh provisions
in and a zoning and he has absolutely no
standing to do that. I realize,
councilwoman Aldridge, that this is a
public hearing and we take public
comment and this is a public meeting,
but the when comments are directed to
issues about which Mr. Miller has no
involvement at all, we should not permit
them.
>> President Crave,
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> if we were to follow that logic, no one
in this room tonight that wants to speak
about data center annexation would be
allowed to speak. So, I I think that we
need to stop at this point and allow the
citizens to speak.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Did we answer
your question?
>> Uh, yes. I was just wondering uh uh
through you um uh to Mr. Wolf, I was
wondering uh what gave you the um the
idea that that I have no standing uh in
any particular um input here. I'm just
wondering,
>> Mr.
I I don't have to get an order with Mr.
Miller.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Miller. Go ahead
and finish your comments. You have 40
seconds.
>> Oh. Oh, 40 40 seconds. Okay. Um Okay.
Let me see here.
All right. Sorry about that. Let's see.
Um I'm just I'm going to have to go
ahead and uh just reconcile my my notes
here, but uh I will I'll go ahead and
and move move on to the next.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Miller. Anyone
else online?
No further comments online. We'll close
that. Anyone in the room that would like
to talk about this u zoning of
agriculture for the uh proposed
annexation,
a zoning agricultural designation.
Seeing none, we'll close public comment.
And Dr. Aldridge, could we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading.
>> Is there a second? Second
>> second by Dr. Emmens discussion uh on
the dis discussion
anyone
hearing none all in favor signify by
saying I
>> I
>> opposed
um it passes unanimously. Next item
please.
>> Number 11 ordinance second reading
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming land northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive.
This is a um um proposed annexation to
expand the uh Swan Ranch Business Park.
Um it's proposed by the owner. Um anyone
online, Jennifer, that would like to
discuss this.
>> Go ahead,
>> Mr. Miller. You can go ahead.
>> Go ahead, Mr. Miller. We can hear you,
Mr. Miller.
Uh, can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir.
>> All righty. Um, so this is agenda item
number 11. Is that correct?
>> That's correct, sir.
>> Um, Charles Miller for the record. Um,
this is in regards to Clear Creek
Parkway and Ganet Peak Drive. Is that
correct?
>> That's correct, sir.
>> Okay. So, um, I'm going to try to get
through this one um all the way. Uh, I'm
placing a formal constructive notice of
jurisdictional arbitrage and statutory
evasion onto the permanent
administrative record regarding agenda
item number 11, the annexation of land
northwest of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive. On June 15th, the
developers agent Mark Christensen of AVI
Professional Corporation admitted the
true purpose of this annexation to the
public services committee, stating
verbatim, "This is an owner initiated
application for annexation. Uh this will
be an expansion of the Swan Ranch
business park. So this annexation is
requested to accompany the platting
action and the zoning action for future
industrial type development. Expanding
this business park boundary is a
calculated maneuver to exploit a state
loophole. During the June 1st planning
commission hearing regarding this exact
Swan Ranch expansion, um I had asked the
administration a direct question. Uh, I
said what uh I said, "Does this
designation allow for the project to
bypass the Wyoming Industrial Sighting
Council permitting process?" Your own
planning director, Charles Bloom Bloom,
confessed the regulatory evasion on the
live microphone, stating verbatim
regarding industrial sighting division.
Uh, this is with an existing business
park so it is exempt from the industrial
sighting committee processes. By
approving this annexation, you are
intentionally expanding a geographic
loophole designed to bypass the Wyoming
Industrial Sighting Act. You're actively
shielding industrial developers from
state level scrutiny and illegally
stripping Laramie County of the
statemandated socioeconomic impact fees
required to mitigate the massive
infrastructure strain these developments
create. I demand a no vote. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Anyone else
online? Jennifer,
no one No one else online. We'll close
that. Got anyone in the room that would
like to discuss this proposed uh
annexation of the of the U for the Swan
Ranch Business Park?
Discussion
hearing? None. We'll close public
comment and we're on second reading.
Could we have a motion? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh Mr. President, the recommendation of
the public services committee is to
approve on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Second by Dr. Emmans.
Discussion.
Dis uh Dr.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Um, I just wanted
to point something out for um, Mr.
Miller especially, but for anyone else
who's interested. Today, I called the
Industrial Sighting Commission because I
was unclear on several things about
industrial sighting and I asked
specifically,
do data centers have to go through the
industrial sighting area or act? And
what they told me is that when there is
an expansion of an existing business
park such as this, the industrial
sighting act um going through the whole
council process um is waved. So I just
want to be let uh Charles Miller know
that there wasn't a violation. This was
done appropriately per the industrial
sighting folks. So I just wanted to
share that. Thank you, Dr. Emmens. Uh,
Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. President, through
you. Uh, just to put a finer point on
that, Mr. Miller's comments are are off
base completely. The legislature created
this scheme. So, this is a legislative
action over which we have no authority
to disagree with. we're following
through with the processes and the
powers that are uh delegated to the
council by the legislature. Um so we're
actually following the law contrary to
Mr. Miller's uh objections.
>> Thank you, Councilman Wolf. Further
discussion?
>> Discussion hearing? None. All in favor
of the annexation signify by saying I.
>> I. Opposed?
>> No.
>> Um,
we have approval of the ordinance on
second reading with Councilman Moody
voting no. Next item, please.
>> Number 12, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of LI Light
Industrial for land annex to the city of
Cheyenne located northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive. As we just approved on
second reading the annexation of this
property for Swan Ranch Business Park,
we now need to zone it. This uh
ordinance creates a zone classification
of LI Light Industrial. We'll go online.
Jennifer, anyone want to talk about this
zoning classification?
Go ahead.
Is there anyone there? Jennifer?
>> Yes. I'm sorry, Mr. President. It's user
error tonight. Um, Mr. Miller, you
should be able to unmute yourself,
>> Mr. Miller. Um,
>> I'm sorry. Can I get you to confirm the
agenda item that we're on? Uh,
>> item 12.
light industrial zoning.
>> All right,
here we are.
Okay,
>> your time is running, Mr. Miller. Um,
so I am placing u uh council members
Charles Miller for the record. Um, I am
placing a formal constructive notice of
premeditated regulatory arbitrage onto
the permanent administrative record
regarding agenda item 12. You are
attempting to assign light industrial
zoning to this 26.29 acre parcel. Is
that correct? It's that
>> Yes, that's correct. Um, but this
ordinance is a procedural charade. You
have no intention of leaving this land
as light industrial. On June 15th, your
own planner, Connor White, confessed
exactly how the city uses these assigned
zonings as a mechanical stepping stone
to accommodate data center developers.
He stated verbatim, "It's a backup
zone." Why staff is recommending that be
zoned this way to begin with when we
know that they want to build the data
center. The reason is if council annexes
it and then doesn't zone it to BP, it
has a city zone, it has a backup zone.
Otherwise, we're annexing a parcel, not
giving it it a zone. Well, then what do
we do with no zone district? They
basically have no regulation. So, we
have to have that backup zone. That was
verbatim. Uh the entire purpose of
establishing this temporary backup zone
is to secure municipal jurisdiction so
you can immediately flip the parcel to
business park zoning. and why business
park planning director Charles Bloom
confessed the true motive on June 1st
stating verbatim regarding industrial
sighting division uh citing uh with an
existing business park so it is exempt
from the indust industrial sighting
committee process by voting yes on
agenda item 12. You are knowingly
constructing the administrative bridge
required to grant corporate developers
immunity from the Wyoming Industrial
Sighting Act. You are participating in a
premeditated scheme to defraud Laramie
County of socioeconomic impact fees. I
demand a no vote.
Thank you. Anyone else online?
Anyone online?
Anyone online, Jennifer? Okay, we'll
close the online discussion. Anyone in
the room that would like to talk about
this light industrial zoning?
Anyone? Seeing none, we'll close public
comment and we'll ask for a motion. Dr.
Aldrich.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services the committee is to
approve on second reading and I so move.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Second by Councilman Wolf. Discussion.
Discussion.
Seeing none, all in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> Mr. Moody is a no. The recommendation is
to approve. On second reading. Next
item, please.
>> Number 13, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located north
and south of West Wall Road and west of
Interstate 25 from LI Light Industrial,
CB Community Business, and PUB Planned
Unit development to BP Business Park.
This this ordinance takes several
different zoning classifications and
moves them all into a business park uh
classification. That's the request we've
received. Is there anyone online that
would like to discuss this?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> members of the council, Charles Miller,
for the record. Um, this is item 13. Is
that correct?
>> That's correct.
>> Um, West Wall Road resoning.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Um, okay. I'm I'm placing a formal
constructive notice of egregious
financial conflict of interest and
confessed jurisdictional arbitrage onto
the permanent administrative record
regarding the West Wall Road reszoning
to Business Park. First, this proceeding
is irreparably tainted by a financial
conflict of interest. The official agent
actively lobbying this body for the West
Wall Road resoning is Mark Christensen
of AVI Professional Corporation. Yet,
um the finance committee uh earlier in
the month utilized taxpayer dollars to
award a uh $252,522.90
97 contract directly to AVI to conduct
the Wallik Road extension feasibility
study. You are funneling a quarter of a
million dollars in public funds to the
developers agent to study the exact same
road where they are actively lobbying
you for an industrial resoning. This
violates the public trust and destroys
the impartiality of this tribunal.
Second, this resoning is a confessed act
of bad faith gerrymandering designed to
evade again the Wyoming Industrial
Sighting Act. During the June 1st
planning commission hearing, the
applicant's agent, Mark Christensen,
explicitly admitted they are
artificially manipulating the map to hit
the 320 acre minimum required for this
BP zone, stating verbatim, "We have
strung together some other properties
that have already been platted in that
BP zone." Why did they string these
properties together? Your own planning
director, Charles Bloom, confessed the
motive on the record, stating, "This is
with an existing business park, so it is
exempt from the industrial sighting
committee processes." You're using a
compromised taxpayer-funded lobbying
agent to rubber stamp a gerrymandered
zoning map, specifically to help
corporate developers evade statemandated
socioeconomic impact fees. I demand a no
vote to halt the systemic arbitrage.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Is there any uh
Jennifer? Go ahead.
>> Mr. Christensen, you can go ahead.
>> Uh Councilman Crave, can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir. We can.
>> Uh just for the record, Councilman
Crave, just wanted to point out that the
um Wallick Road resoning that we're
looking at currently is on the west side
of I25 and the extents of the Wallik and
Parsley uh contract are on the east side
of I25. So, just wanted to clear that up
for the council. And then also uh about
stringing properties together. This is a
owner initiated zone change. So an owner
is allowed um no matter how many
different properties they own allowed to
initiate a zone change uh or request a
zone change at behalf of the council. So
just wanted to clear those things up.
Thank you.
>> Mr. Christensen, can you identify the uh
your employer who you're representing
here?
>> Yes, sir. Uh Mark Christensen with AIPC
at 1103 Oldtown Lane.
>> Thank you, sir. I should have done that
at the beginning. I apologize. Apologies
on my part,
>> Jennifer. Anyone else online?
All right, the online is uh closed.
Anyone in the in the room that would
like to talk about this uh zoning issue?
Anyone?
Seeing no one, we'll close public
comment. Uh Dr. Aldrich, could we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading, and I so move.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second. Second by Dr. Emmens. Discussion
from the council. Discussion
hearing none. All in favor on second
reading signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. Uh it's a unanimous
unanimous vote. Uh we'll move on to the
next item. Please.
>> Number 14. Ordinance second reading.
Annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming. land east of South Gley Highway
and south of the Sweetg Grass
subdivision.
>> This is a owner uh initiated um
annexation of about 3500 acres west
correction east of the Bison Business
Park. Um
located off of South Gy Highway north of
Chalkluff Road. Um this is on second
reading. Jennifer will go online first.
Go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you, sir.
>> All right. Give me just a second here.
This is number 14.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Uh, let's see here.
>> Okay. Uh, Charles Miller, for the
record, um, I am placing a formal
constructive notice of arbitrary
governance and fiduciary abandonment
onto the permanent record regarding
agenda item number 14, the 3,460
acre annexation.
>> Is that the amount of acres, Scott?
>> Yes, sir. Close enough.
>> Okay. Um, you cannot legally satisfy
Wyoming statute 15142's
requirement that this annexation is
logical and feasible. Microsoft's own
agent, Rachel Irwing, confessed to the
city, given the early stage of this
effort, Microsoft has not yet advanced
detailed design for this for the campus.
You are granting municipal jurisdiction
to a 3500 acre ghost project. Um, you
are advancing this blank check while
ignoring catastrophic environmental
warnings. As resident Richard Lyall
warned this council regarding low water
supplies, the aquafer under the uh in
the unincorporated area is drying up. I
have a friend who uh has out here he has
a well that goes down 600 feet. He now
has uh he has to now because that's
drying up spend $120,000
to replace it with a well going down 900
ft. Quote, um you are annexing annexing
an unquantifiable utility burden onto a
breaking ecosystem. Why are you rushing
an annex annexation without a design?
Councilman Larry Wolf explicitly warned
the committee, "We don't know and we
shouldn't be arrogant enough to think
that we know what this is going to look
like 10 years from now." He asked you to
delay this until Microsoft signed a $50
million community benefits agreement.
Instead, you're rushing this to
facilitate a massive land sale for the
political elite. As Councilman Wolf
stated verbatim on the record, "What is
the benefit to the city if we annex now?
unless they're going to do some substant
some substantial things for the
residents. Making Senator Cynthia Lumis
a lot richer is not a compelling reason.
Quote, "You are trading our water and
our infrastructure for an elite payout.
I demand a no vote on item 14 until a
binding $50 million community benefits
agreement is secured." Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Anyone else
online?
No one else online. We'll close the
online section and we'll bring it into
the room. Um we'll ask folks to come up.
Uh we'll limit our time to 3 minutes
each. Uh when you come up, please
identify yourself and we'll start with
Mr. White. Sir,
>> uh Mr. President, Michael White. Um,
I've been gone for a while, but I know
that um, AVI is heading this project,
and I appreciate that, but
I think I need to take a lesson from our
Wyoming legislators that um, when we get
as many people as we have in the room,
as I've attended many committee meetings
for the state of Wyoming, when they're
subjects to not knowing all the
information,
the ability for the legislators to make
cognitive decisions.
The legislators appoint a bipartisan
individual group to assess the issue of
annexation with regards to what we know
will be built here. But we don't seem to
do that. We seem to be the experts in
the United States annexation. And I
appreciate Brad being here, but I don't
see the owner of the property here. that
land acquisition has not been finalized
where Microsoft is actually buying the
property. Uh with respect to the Lumis
family, I have seen many times where
this governing body has wanted the
property owner to be at the meeting and
I don't see anybody from the Lumis ranch
or their holding company. So I caution
the council. We seem to be the people
behind the podium, the people. And I'll
take a quote from Governor Gordon where
ride the where he says we need to get
more information and Brad
Edmonds we know is trying to give us all
the information that we need but I think
we need to take a pause in all
annexations right now especially when we
cannot address
what this project is actually for
because we can only talk about
annexation.
And the last point I'd like to make is
that the last time we redid plan
Cheyenne was 2012. That's 14 years that
we have not redone that plan Cheyenne.
So, in my regards, how can we assess
[snorts]
what we're talking about tonight without
redoing all the rules when we should
[clears throat] be specific to those
rules to say exactly what this project
is? So, I say vote no. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, sir. Uh, council
president, council members Brad Emmens,
AVI agent for the applicant and owners
and the and for Microsoft the future
developer. Um, this is a uh owner
initiated annexation uh that we've
brought before you. Uh, we believe it
meets the creditory statutory
requirements for annexation and here to
answer any questions that the council
might have of me.
>> Any questions for the owner's
representative while he's here?
Councilman Leborn.
Thank you, Mr. President. Um I don't
have a map here in front of me. Uh Brad,
um am I correct that uh the uh Oh, I see
this. It uh here's the [clears throat]
Yes. Doesn't quite answer my question.
Does the uh existing uh sweetg grass uh
[clears throat] property and its its
zoning and uh acceptance of uh
annexation
is it abudding uh this uh proposed
annexation?
>> Mr. Evans.
>> Uh Mr. President, for you to Councilman
Labour? as there are portions of the
existing sweet grass uh subdivision that
has already been annexed that join this
on the northwest corner. Um so I would
estimate
20% 25% touch the existing sweetgrass
residential annexation.
>> Thank you.
Any further questions? Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh thank you Mr. President through you.
Um Mr. Mr. Emmens, were you involved in
the sweet grass uh annexation that was
done in 2017 2018?
>> Mr. Emmens,
>> Mr. President, no I was not.
>> Thank you, Mr. President.
>> Any further questions for the owner's
representative?
>> Okay. Thank you very much.
Yes, ma'am.
>> Good evening, council members. My name
is Rachel Irwing. I'm a land development
manager uh with Microsoft. Our address
is one Microsoft Way, Redmond,
Washington. Um, thank you again for your
time and consideration. You've given the
Highlands project over the past several
weeks. I understand why a project of
this scale rages raises questions from
oversight to long-term impacts. And I
want to acknowledge that those are
important conversations to have. At its
core, annexation is about planning. It
is one step in a much longer process
that allows the city to remain actively
involved in how this area is planned,
reviewed, and ultimately developed over
time. One question we've heard
throughout this process is if full full
buildout may occur over many years, why
is annexation being considered now? And
the answer to that question is that
annexation is about planning and not
immediate construction. Projects of this
scale require long-term coordination or
infrastructure. Annexation allows the
city of Cheyenne to participate in that
planning early rather than waiting until
development is imminent. It ensures
future growth can be evaluated and
coordinated under the city's planning
framework, standards, and oversight
processes. It is also important to
recognize that annexation is not the
final approval for development. Future
phases will continue to be subject to
engineering, planning, utility,
environmental, and permitting review as
they advance. Those reviews will occur
at appropriate stages of design and
development. In short, annexation today
is not about accelerating construction.
It's about allowing the city and
Microsoft to plan responsibly and
collaboratively. From our side, we're
trying to be as transparent as possible
about where this project stands today.
We do not yet own the land and we are
still in the early process of planning.
That's exactly why we've been engaging
early through neighborhood and public
meetings, coordination with city staff,
and bringing in subject matter experts
to help answer any questions as they
arise. We also plan to continue that
engagement, including additional
community open houses to hear questions
and concerns as this project evolves.
Ultimately, this is one step in a much
longer process with additional
opportunities for coordination and
review as more information becomes
avail. We appreciate the coordination
the city has to date and we'll continue
working through those as the next phases
of this project advance. Thank you for
your time and our team is here to answer
any questions.
>> Thank you
Mr. Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh Mr. Irving
don't go.
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Thank you Mr. President through you. Um
Mr. Considering I I'm going to make a
motion uh to this council to postpone
this or recommmit it to committee um for
a period that we can decide. I suggested
four months um so that we can um
negotiate an annexation agreement,
community benefits agreement with
Microsoft. What's your view on that?
>> Council President, through you uh Mr.
Wolf. Um, Microsoft is willing to work
with the city in in whatever way is
beneficial for both the city and this
project. So, we're open to discussions.
>> Mr. Councilman Wolf
>> President followup, please. Thank you.
Uh, through you um
if we took four months to do that, does
that create any particular problems for
Microsoft?
Council President through you, uh,
Councilman Wolf. Um, Microsoft would
like to progress the project as soon as
possible in order to begin our
engineering review, our uh, development
plan schedules, and early design and
planning, especially for off-site
infrastructure so we can begin working
with the city as soon as possible.
>> Followup, Mr. Council,
>> thank you. Um,
have you read the Sweetg Grass
annexation agreement?
>> Council President, through you,
Councilman Wolf. Um, I have read a
portion. I have not completely reviewed
the Sweetgrass annexation agreement.
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Um, so you understand that that was
entered into with the same land owners
uh and prior to a decision on
annexation. And that agreement actually
encompassed
uh agreements on annexation and zoning.
>> Council President through you, Mr. Wolf.
Yes, I understand.
>> Okay. And and you also understand that
that uh what my motion actually it's Mr.
Labour's motion and mine. Um is at this
stage just a suggestion to the mayor. We
aren't trying to tell the mayor and his
staff and Mr. bloom, what to do, what
should be in the in the document. Um, we
are just saying for a short period of
time that uh we'd like to give the
parties the opportunity to have that
full discussion. Is that you understand
that part of it?
>> Council President through you to uh
Councilman Wolf. Yes, I understand.
>> Okay. M
>> Mr. President, point of order. I don't
believe we are on the discussion of the
amendment. We should not be, but we have
a proposed developer here, so I wanted
to give council an opportunity to ask
questions.
>> Anything else, Mr. Wolf?
>> Uh, no. Uh, thank you, Mr. President.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Three. Thank
you, Mr. Irving. Just one question.
I understand timelines change. Do you
Does Microsoft have a proposed timeline
for this whole project from start date
to end date?
>> Council President, through you, uh, Mr.
Moody. At this time, we don't have a
start and finish date. However, we would
like to begin working on the feasibility
reviews of this project um once we are
annexed and reszoned and acquire the
property so we can begin coordination
with the city. Um however, we do not
have a construction complete date as we
have not advanced detailed design.
>> That's all I have. Thank you, Mr.
President. Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Um, how unusual
is it or how usual is it typical is it
for you to have a complete timeline at
this point in the de uh development
process?
>> Mr.
>> Council President through you u Miss
Emmens at this point at this stage it is
not very common for a developer to have
a complete detailed design um especially
as we had just we haven't even acquired
the property yet. Um, so there hasn't
been time between approaching the land
owner, working through the acquisition
process, completing a site due diligence
and and review and also completing
detailed design, um, which can take, you
know, depending on the project, months
to to a year.
>> Thank you. Appreciate it. Thank you. Uh,
Director Bloom
and chair, members of council, Charles
Bloom, plan development director. I just
want to provide a little bit of detail
on the annexation agreement since there
has been plenty of discussion about it.
Um, SweetGrass did enter into an
annexation agreement back in 2018. It
was approved in April of 2018. That
agreement has been provided to their
uh to their consultant and also been
forwarded on to them. Um, that agreement
was primarily set up um to number one
identify the payment of park fees and
the timing of park fees. In our unified
development code, it says that when you
plat a property, you are able to um
identify an alternative payment plan and
that was one of the the fundamental
items of this development. Secondly,
there was another element regarding
infrastructure. Essentially, there was a
um a what we would call a subdivision
standard waiver today which sometimes is
dealt with administratively where you
can do alternative roadway patterns and
al alternative roadway construction. So
what they did there is they wanted to
preserve the prairie style development,
keep that name sweetg grass and with
that um development they looked for a
more rural section. So that was
memorialized in that agreement and that
was um a subdivision standards
alternative that they had done.
Secondly, this is a large development
that's phased over many decades. Um,
with that development, they wanted to
identify and the traffic study showed
that over time there was going to be a
need for transportation improvements,
traffic signalization, other items on
the perimeter. So, it identified an
account that that we have and we
continue to maintain um that charges
homes when they are constructed an
infrastructure fee which we hold on to
and we invest to utilize for
infrastructure improvements in the
future like signalization um of major
roadways when it meets warrants. So,
that was the primary impetus for the
development agreement um regarding
sweetgrass. In that development, they
also pledged and it's I understand this
was a pledge of their development that
they would do a planned unit development
and they um which is essentially a build
your own zone district and they
personally committed to items on their
own which talked about uh
sustainability, lower water use, those
types of items um and also um dedication
of parkland in that area which we had
discussion on just recently. Um all of
that was um mostly to satisfy what was
in our unified development code. Since
the annexation agreement was put
together, we have had one major change
in our development regulations regarding
the payment of park impact fees. Um, at
that time they were due a subdivision
and you would have to as a developer pay
a park impact fee before you had even
sold one lot, before you had even
financed um, road construction to get
all that up to snuff. Um, just recently
we amended our unified development code
to to modify the timeline of that fee.
So that fee now occurs that building
permit which is after the development
has been has been developed and that
building permit is ready to be pulled.
>> Thank you, Mr. Welcome.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Good evening, Mr. President, members of
the council, city staff, and the public.
My name is Lucas Downey, and I serve as
a community affairs manager at
Microsoft. I appreciate the opportunity
to be here with you again tonight. It
wouldn't be a Monday this summer if we
weren't all here together spending this
time.
I want to start by briefly grounding us
in something I've shared before,
Microsoft's community first commitments.
These are five commitments we make in
every community where we build and
operate. I know I've stated these in my
previous public comment, but I think
it's important for the public to hear
these and also have these on the public
record so we can hold ourselves
accountable to them. We pay our own way
so our data centers do not increase
electricity costs for our residents. We
work to minimize our water use and
replenish more than we use. We create
jobs for local residents. We contribute
to the local tax base. And we invest in
communities through programs like
workforce development, AI training, and
support for local nonprofits.
These are not just statements. They
guide how we show up and how we operate.
Just as important, we listen. On a
previous project here in Cheyenne, we
heard clearly from the community that
Burlington Trail Road was in rough shape
and needed attention. We took that
feedback, worked with partners, and made
improvements to the road. In addition to
that project, we've added a section of
the greenway in the same area to further
enable and encourage access to the east
for the community. That input mattered,
and it directly shaped the outcome. That
same approach continues today. We are
here, we're listening, and we're taking
notes. Microsoft has been a part of the
Cheyenne community for more than 14
years. We're here tonight as a partner
and we intend to continue showing up in
that way moving forward. Thank you for
your time.
>> Thank you, Mr. Downing. Further
discussion? Yes, sir.
>> Jimmy cheer candidate for Ward One. I
know this has been a hot topic. Uh
through my campaigning door knockocking,
I'd say probably 90% of the residents uh
at least in my area are just concerned.
It's a transparency. I told them they
could go to the meeting that they
recently had over at triplec. They
didn't know about it. So, you've got to
get out. You've got to do your research
on that. I'm not against business. I'm
not against the small business bringing
in uh more tech jobs on that. Uh but
through you, President Craves, Mr. Wolf,
I think that um that would be a good
compromise, a postponement on it.
something of this grand size is going to
impact those residents out there at the
the um Sawrass area and just the whole
city in in general. Uh the envir
environmental impact. I mean, I know
they're going to do their plan study and
whatnot, but I would recommend as a as a
compromise to just do a postponement on
this so that we could go and and try to
ne negotiate some other items with it. I
would be myself, I would be more
inclined to this major project and an
expansion that if they, you know, threw
out on the table that they're going to
buy the YMCA and turn that into the a
rec center, you know, the price has gone
way down or make a huge donation for aa
ballpark, something that will positively
impact the uh the community here, not
just a small donation to the girls and
boys club or a couple of grants that are
specifically set at triple C triple, you
know, LC for just technical uh um you
know um classes of that. Why not the
welding? Why not electrician? Something
else like that? But I would I would
highly recommend this governing body to
do a postponement. Put something else
out on the table that we can negotiate
with them because I mean like it or not,
it's going to happen. I know Miss Lumis
um you know she has a right to go and
ask for the annexation and then for the
zoning change but if we could seriously
consider that to do a a postponement I
appreciate it.
>> Thank you. Yes sir.
>> Can you turn it on for us please?
>> There we go.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah to you city council all that I've
been here more than a couple times. My
question is every time you guys ans size
land seems like you guys are answering a
lot of land all the time from the county
and that's just for me is a little
confusion why why you guys ans size all
this land all the time why couldn't that
3500 acres I'm just ask questioning why
didn't somebody else buy that land
before it becomes to the city you know
somebody that has land that want you
know animals cattle whatever could come
off that 3500 acres I don't
Did you guys ever
>> sir, this is an owner owner request,
>> right? Can you ever consider the people
that live at Sweet Sweet Grass
subdivision that those homes are there?
>> Every time there's a an ant size, you
got these corporate right away want to
put a data center, a software, whatever.
Why couldn't you just make it like a a
subdivision for homes? Why can't you do
that? Because we getting too many data
centers to my Microsoft and China. How
many more do we want in Cheyenne? You
know, there's other things besides that
because, you know, that many data
centers and data centers all across the
United States. You know, there's there's
lot of, you know, we use cell phones,
everything. Everybody uses all over. But
why so many data centers? My question
is, did you ever consider those people
at Sweetwater subdivision that live
there? Would they like to live next to a
a Microsoft business or whatever? You
guys probably live somewhere that you're
not living near places like that. Reason
I'm up here cuz I live around Terry
Ranch Road. They got that data center. I
watch it every day destroying the land.
They're uh tearing down the roads and
everything. I don't know exactly how
close that data center is going to be.
The lights going to be issue. And I know
some I heard stories about some of those
daters make all kinds of noise. We don't
know that yet till it's done. But I'm
just saying they drilled two wells in
that well then my water into the offer.
I spoke this before they said they were
going to go deeper than that. What
happens that whole thing collapsed once
they take the water? You know it's like
a cavity. What if that collapse and it
drops? The whole thing drops in those
things we do not know. mother nature,
the earth, whatever, we don't know
what's going to do. We we plan ahead.
Yes, this is what we want. But every
time I hear an ice, I hear these uh
Microsoft comes in. We want to build
this, we want to build that. Why can't
we build something else beside that in
that area? You know, at one time I
thought there would be a golf course in
that area. You know, that'd be better. I
rather see a golf course so people could
play golf and enjoy. But these data
centers and Microsoft, that's my
opinion. Thank you. Have a good one.
>> Thank you. Miss Vulp,
>> Mr. Chairman, members of council, and
members of the community. My name is
Wendy Vulk. I'm a longtime southeastern
Wyoming resident, a business
professional, and someone whose family
has deep roots in this region. I'm not
here to oppose growth. Wyoming has
always embraced innovation,
entrepreneurship, and opportunity.
economic development matters and our
state has a proud history of powering
the nation through agriculture, mining
and energy production. But as we witness
a growing wave of industrial development
including business parks, data centers,
transmission infrastructure, workforce
housing, quaries, and large-scale energy
projects, I believe we must ask some
harder or some broader questions about
how we grow and who bears the cost. We
experienced them accumulatively. We
experienced increased traffic on shared
roads. We see growing demands on water
systems, emergency services, housing,
and public infrastructure. We
experienced the gradual transformation
of open spaces and the rural character
that has defined southeastern Wyoming
for generations. Growth itself is not
the issue. The issue is whether we have
long a long-term plan and whether growth
is paying for its fair share. Our roads,
bridges, intersections, and public
services were built primarily to serve
existing residents, ranching operations,
and local businesses. They were not
necessarily designed to accommodate the
demands of multiple large industrial
developments occurring simultaneously. I
believe it is reasonable to ask the
companies benefiting from this growth to
become partners in building the
infrastructure they require. I applaud
Microsoft on being a great community
partner. But if industrial traffic
increases wear on roads and bridges,
companies should contribute to their
improvements and long-term maintenance,
if growth requires expanded emergency
services, water infrastructure or
transportation upgrades. These costs
should not fall disproportionately on
local taxpayers. Economic development is
strongest when both the benefits and the
responsibilities are shared fairly. And
as we make these decisions, I hope we
continue to ask a larger question. What
do we want southeastern Wyoming to look
like 20 or 50 years from now? Once open
space is industrialized, it is rarely
returned to its original condition. Once
the character of a community changes, it
can be difficult to restore. I am not
asking for us to stop progress. I am
asking for us to guide it wisely with
transparency, thoughtful planning, and a
commitment to ensuring that growth
strengthens strengthens our communities
rather than placing new burdens upon
them. Wyoming has always prided itself
on thinking long term. I hope we
continue to do so because the choices we
make today will shape the Wyoming our
children and grandchildren inherit. And
thank you all for your time.
>> Thank you. Yes, ma'am.
>> Heather Madre, Harmony Meadows. Um, so I
understand that this is an owner
initiated annexation. However, it was
just revealed that the property owner
was approached. Although this is far
from organic development, um unlike
other record-breaking annexations in the
same area with the same property owner,
Microsoft has not been required to
provide a detailed plan for the
development of this property. The lack
of a plan is not a legitimate reason to
forego any kind of annexation agreement.
In fact, it is quite the opposite. It's
a reason to wait until Microsoft has
some idea of what they're doing here.
Um, the owner has the right to sell
their property to whoever they want and
Microsoft has the right to purchase this
property. Microsoft then has the right
to do whatever they want within their
new asset as long as it falls within
allowed uses which is currently LU in
the county. This allows for agricultural
housing no less than 10 no less than
10.5 acres per home and very limited
home businesses. That is where their
inherent property rights end. Owning
property in this city does not allow
anyone to trample on the rights of
70,000 people. Annexation is not a
right. It is a public process that
requires certain criteria to be met. If
the criteria is not met, the property is
met, excuse me, the property shall be
annexed. At least two of the five have
not been met. The first one being that
annexation must protect the health,
safety, and welfare of the citizens of
Cheyenne. Without a detailed plan, it is
impossible to make that determination.
Even with a detailed plan, how does a
project of this magnitude meet that
criteria? What studies have been done?
How much water will they use? How many
backup generators will be necessary?
Will they bring their own power? Is this
why Tall Grass wants to donate $2.9
million to housing?
The second unmet criterion is that it
must be a logical and feasible addition
to the city. Notably, police, fire, and
EMS services must be reasonably
available. Is this why the city wants to
use six penny dollars to relocate the
fire station on Fox Farm where it
currently serves the many homes,
schools, and families located in South
Cheyenne? Moving services closer to data
centers and farther away from residents
only serves to further the concerning
disproportionate access to services and
resources that already exists on the
south side of Cheyenne. How does that
protect the health, safety, and welfare
of this city? Where will the roads to
this property be? How will police and
other emergency services get there? Once
again, without a detailed plan, it it is
impossible to make that determination.
This property is not ready to be
annexed. Plain and simple. Microsoft
must follow the same rules and laws as
everybody else. The special treatment of
multi-billion dollar corporations should
anger everyone, even if you do support
the unchecked and unregulated data
center buildout. The city is not
accountable to corporate timelines, and
if Microsoft expects the road to be
paved ahead of them at the expense of
the health, safety, and welfare of this
community, then they are in fact not
good neighbors that that they claim to
be. Targeted corporate philanthropy is
not a substitute for proper planning,
and it does not excuse the wealthiest
corporations in this world from
following the law. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Miss Madrid.
Yes, ma'am.
>> K McAdams.
Um, usually now once I get the
information, I have to readjust what I'm
going to say. So, I would like I would
propose a delay because it gives people
time to read and actually check through
chat GPT
the very thing we're building for. So I
take a screenshot of look at the BOPU
statement and it says BPO BOPU also
requires meter installation. Is the
public allowed to have
use or the access of that water usage?
Well, according to chat GPT,
it tells us the BOPU collects the data
but not whether the de the public can
see it. In Wyoming, utility water use
records are often treated differently
depending on who the customer is. If
you're a retail customer, you're metered
and you're checked. Now,
however,
according to this, whether the public
can obtain water use for a specific data
center may depend on Wyoming public
records law and any confident
confidentiality claims made by the
company. I'd like to wait and see how
much
water Microsoft uses. I'd like to see
the metering. Has it ever been public?
Answer the question. Furthermore, this
is just the water usage for cooling, not
water usage for
the energy consumption that tall grass
caruso would use. So the 2% that we're
seeing, how accurate is that? Is that
present
or future use? And it's present use
according to this. So I want to delay on
this. I think it would be a very good
thing. So we could go ahead and get on
our chap GPT and check what is said and
stated and whether or not items are left
out and the truth be told. I don't think
that is too much to ask. These companies
leave out things and I just want to know
what's happening. you you if you want to
use the water, use it below what the
land you've purchased, but don't spread
it out on the data for the data center
all out on our community all through
that aquifer. It's not right if we don't
know how much water is being used. It's
kind of like looking at a stock. You can
look at the present EPS or you can look
at the future earnings of it. And I want
to look at the future
of our water usage. And that's just one
thing. I haven't even addressed
Black Hills Energy and why they want it
so badly. So, please consider delay so
we can chat GBT and look at it and
really get the truth.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Yes. I'm Richard Lyle. live on the north
side of town and I'm not affiliated with
Microsoft or any of those businesses.
But my understanding is if this property
is enexed, it would be subject to
municipal ordinances including the noise
limitation ordinance. If it is not
annexed, it somebody could build either
[clears throat] Microsoft or somebody
they
sell it to and there would be no limit
on how much noise they could have. Um,
and I think it's in the best interest of
the health and welfare and safety of the
residents that the municipal ordinances
including the noise limit apply to this
property.
As far as the aquifer is concerned, if
the property is enexed, it would be
they'd be able to have city water and
city sewer. If it's not enexted, they
would have to go into the aquifer and
that I think is contrary to the welfare
of the residents both in the city and
[snorts] outside the city.
And there's also the financial issue.
There's going to be property tax paid
when something is built. And the only
guess is it's going to be quite a bit of
money. Um
now I went to the uh committee meeting
and I suggested that if the uh you know
there are quite a few potholes and I
offered to give them a list of potholes
that could be filled with this but there
are other other needs too.
As far as city services Microsoft is
going to have their own private police
or you know security people. So, it's
not going to take a whole lot of
Cheyenne Police Department uh uh you
know, the uh Cheyenne Police Department
can back up if there's a situation, but
Microsoft is going to have their own
security. So, that's not going to be a a
net expense to the city. So, those are
my thoughts on this and thank you very
much.
>> Thank you, Mr. Ly.
Anyone else that would like to speak
before we bring it up on the dis?
Anyone else? Yes, ma'am.
>> So, I
>> Please identify yourself.
>> Okay. My name's Donna Frostto.
>> Thank you.
>> From Wyoming. Um,
>> can you bring the microphone up, please?
There you go. Thank you.
>> Can you hear me?
>> There we go.
>> Okay. I I'm all in favor for it being
postponed, too, as far as like the water
consumption. Um, seeing that Amazon even
put out a report that 2.5 billion
gallons of water were just used in 225
is kind of a big deal. I don't know why
waiting is not allowed, but or why it's
such a rush, but just to ease the
residents and our health and benefits
around it. Um, it's just a big deal. So,
I value our water and in a drought, it's
kind of rough right now. So, I hope that
is considered with everything else.
>> Thank you, Donna.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi.
>> Hi, I'm Penny Hollandbach. I am not
associated with Microsoft. I'm just a
resident here in Laramie County. Um, a
couple weeks ago, I went to the meeting
that they had at the civic center. Um,
and we were talking about the gallons of
water that Microsoft will use. Um, it
was brought to our attention that we
used 93 million gallons of water last
year, but yet we can handle 2.6 billion
gallons a year,
but we're on water restrictions. So, how
like why are we forced to be on water
restrictions, but yet we're giving
thousand billions of gallons to
Microsoft to build
their infrastructures. Um,
[clears throat]
I think Oh, and also I couldn't help but
notice that in the newspaper I saw an
article that stated that sewer and water
prices were going up for Cheyenne
residents. How is that
contingent with saying that the
residents don't have to pay for
increases for the water in the sewers?
That's my question. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Penny.
Any other
comments in the room?
Any other comments?
>> Seeing none, we'll bring it up on the
dis and I'll ask for a motion, please.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Dr. Aldrich, seconded by Dr.
Emmens. Discussion on the dis.
>> Yes, sir. Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh, President Crave, I just I wanted to
uh respond to some of the things that
have been said tonight. I know that
there was a recommendation or a
suggestion that perhaps u Microsoft
could uh purchase the old YMCA
um because the price on that has dropped
and I know that it's being up actually
put up for auction. Um there are a lot
of challenges I think with that and in
light of a new recreation center being
built by the Mory Brown Foundation. I I
don't know that that would be the best
investment um because it is landlocked
and it has a lot of ADA issues as well
as a boiler issue with its pool. Um I
did want to point out that um
Microsoft's donation I thought I think 1
point it's 1 point something million 1.3
million to uh girls and boys club or
boys and girls club is fairly
substantial. I don't think that's in non
um a non-starter. They also um I don't
know that people are really aware of
this but donated um
uh quite a bit of money for what we call
um gutter bins. uh through the Frog
Creek partners in order to be able to
make sure that uh water that's going to
Crow Creek is not uh that we're being
able to strain a lot of the silts and
the trash out of that before it gets to
Crow Creek. Um because their commitment
is to a um returning more water than
what they're using um that's usable and
that's they've been doing that since uh
long before this discussion ever came
up. So I think sometimes the things that
they've done have have gone uh unnoticed
and in the background.
Um
I would it wanted to also um point out
the Lumus family does have a right to
sell their land to whoever they would
like to. Um which is part of the what
the land which is the land we're
discussing in annexation tonight. Um
they've done a subdivision. It was
suggested that maybe they should do
housing. Well they have. It's called
sweetg grass. Uh they also donated the
land that LC sits on back in the 70s,
but probably a lot of people in this
audience are too young to remember that
or to know that.
Um and if any of you um are homeowners
or own property, you would want to be
able to sell your property to the
highest bidder as well. Um you would not
want to um be told by neighbors that you
couldn't sell your property to whoever
you wanted to sell your property to. We
value personal property rights in the
state of Wyoming.
Um we do have lights and noise
ordinances in the city. Um we are able
to monitor and meter water when it's uh
used. City water is being used which I
believe is much safer than taking it
from the aquifer uh through a well
system or having to worry about a septic
system with leech fields. Um and I agree
that the benefits and the
responsibilities need to be shared. Uh
there was a question about why we have
water restrictions if we're not using
our full amount of water. uh we have
water restrictions so that we can
continue to preserve water and so that
we um recognize that it is a valuable
resource and asset that we have um and I
think Mr. Strong could definitely
explain or anyone from BOPU um could
explain that we had an increase in water
and sewer and that was not um because of
data centers. Um that's something that
is that is reviewed and um looked at um
each year and that was based on the
infrastructure that we need to support
currently um with the uh uh reduced
amount of water that we're selling. So,
um I just I think that uh there's a lot
of misinformation out there. I think
there's a lot of uh things that are
happening in other cities and other
states that um don't necessarily apply
here in Cheyenne or in Wyoming, uh due
to some guardrails that have been put in
place by our state legislature and by
our community. And so, um I would
encourage you to continue to do your
research and do your homework. But for
that reason, I will be a yes vote on
this tonight.
Councilman Escoel.
>> Mr. President, I'm sorry to interrupt,
but can I just um let the record show
that Mayor Patrick Collins joined the
meeting at 7-Eleven.
>> Thank you. Welcome, Mayor Collins.
Councilman Escoel,
>> what's he doing?
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Through you,
uh especially for the people that live
in Sweetgrass, this annexation is going
to have the largest conservation
easement that we have in Larmy County.
Uh
well definitely the city of Cheyenne. Uh
and by having a conservation easement up
there on that bluff between Sweetgrass
subdivision and where the closest
development Microsoft would do, uh means
that there can't be any development
there. And if I was to live in that type
of uh development, uh having a
conservation easement uh outside of of
where I live would probably be one of
the greatest things I could hope for.
But, uh, going forward, uh, if if this
was sold to a developer and they were
going to put another
thousand homes in that annexation, they
would use probably 100 times more water
than what if they
use that whole land for data centers.
So, uh that that's one of the things I
think that is
spread out there as far as
misinformation is about the water usage.
So, uh there are a lot of other things
that go could go in there that would use
a lot of water, but I won't really get
into that. So,
I'll support it. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilman Escobel. Uh
Councilman Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Through you,
uh Mr. President, just some guidance
from you would be helpful. Um, I'd like
to make a sort of overarching statement
about what we're doing, how significant
this is, how this is the largest
annexation we've ever done and probably
ever will do. That's the first request
I'd have of you. Second request is I
have some questions I want to ask of Mr.
Bloom to understand the parameters of uh
the way he and the planning and zoning
deal with annexation. Um so that's
request number two. Question number
three is I have a motion to ask us to
postpone
uh this matter for a period of what I've
suggested to be four months to allow the
mayor and his staff time to negotiate
with Microsoft uh an annexation
agreement. It's not directive. It's not
mandatory. They could come back to the
council and say we were unable to do
that, but we tried. But it would give us
an opportunity to deal with the
magnitude of this undertaking and all of
the fine people that we have seen and
heard from. Remember we listened to 70
people on Mr. Moody's motion for a
moratorum and um so I'd like to honor
some of that. So that's number three. So
how would you like to proceed,
>> Mr. Wolf? If number three is approved,
the delay, there's probably not a need
tonight for number one and two.
>> Exactly. I agree.
>> So, should we go ahead and and address
your uh amendment to postpone? And if it
fails, then we'll come back to number
one and two.
>> Um,
>> does that work?
>> Mr. President, I that's perfect. I I
would be delighted to do that. Um
because I think setting up the
discussion for the motion to postpone uh
will in fact lay some of the groundwork.
If it's defeated, then we can go forward
with the other two issues.
>> All right, Mr. Wolf, would you like to
make a motion to amend?
>> Um yes, your honor. Um
your honor. [laughter]
>> Sounds good.
>> 46 years of habits die really hard.
[laughter]
I would one time, just to bother you
with a little story, um I was uh at a at
a ceremony. I was wearing a long duster
and they said, "Okay, Mr. Wolf, would
you make some remarks?" And I stood up
and what did I do? The first thing I do,
I buttoned the coat on the duster
as I would do in a suit in the
courtroom. Um thank you. Um, for members
of the audience, uh, I have some extra
copies of this motion if you'd like to
see it. Uh, I've provided it already,
uh, Mr. President, to the members of the
council and, um, to I think the clerk
has a copy of it. Um, but if, um, people
want to come up and get it or we want to
distribute it, they're all right here.
Um this motion uh
yeah anybody uh who would like a copy?
I've got there about 15 or so there.
Thank you. Um
Mr. President, um this motion is very
simple. Um it it looks a little
complicated because it has two and a
half pages on it, but the motion itself
is a very simple one. It just says that
we would move to postpone or recommmit
um to committee which is what we've done
if you recall in two recent cases. One
involving the urban farmer, one
involving um the uh proposed Cox Ranch
annexation. Um and um I suggested
November 26 uh the the first meeting in
November, which is November 9th,
and for the purpose of allowing the
mayor and the staff to negotiate uh a
comprehensive what I've called
annexation
mutually beneficial partnership
agreement between the city and
Microsoft. So Mr. President, that's the
motion. I can talk about the suggested
contents if you wish. You have them all
in front of you. But again, these are
all just a suggestion from that that
that I've drafted after thinking about
this, talking to to some some folks
about it. Um, and obviously none of it
is is directly binding on what the mayor
and his staff would do.
Okay, we have a motion by Councilman
Wolf.
>> Point of parlatory procedure. What What
exactly is the motion?
>> I'm I'm going to address that. His
motion, as I understand it, and correct
me, Mr.
Uh, your motion is to postpone or
recommit to committee until the first
council meeting in November of 2026,
which happens to be November 9th, which
allows the mayor and staff time to
negotiate a comprehensive annexation
beneficial partnership agreement. Is
that correct?
>> That's correct, Mr. President.
>> And do we have a second?
>> Second.
>> We have a motion by Councilman Wolf, a
second by Councilman Lebornne. When we
have a motion to amend, we go back out
and for discussion before we bring it
back up on the dis. So, I will start
online. Do we have anyone online that
wants to discuss the motion to amend?
That's what we're here to discuss
tonight. Now, the motion to amend. Looks
like we do have someone uh Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller,
can
>> you hear me?
Mr. Miller.
>> Yes. Can you hear me?
>> We can now. Go ahead.
>> All righty. Um,
okay.
This, uh, my name is Charles Miller. Uh,
mayor, members of the council, um, I'm
placing a formal constructive notice of
fiduciary illusion and bad faith
negotiation onto the permanent
administrative record regarding the
motion to postpone this annexation for
four months. Councilman Wolf has just
proposed a delay to negotiate the $50
million community benefits agreement um
that was demanded, but the live
transcript proves this motion is a
political charade designed to pacify
this room without securing a single
dollar for the taxpayers. Councilman
Wolf explicitly confessed to the
Microsoft representative that this delay
is toothless, stating verbatim at this
stage, just a suggestion to the mayor,
"We aren't trying to tell the mayor and
his staff and Mr. Bloom what to do." He
further admitted the premeditated
loophole to this governing body, stating
verbatim, "It's not directive. It's not
mandatory. They would come back to the
council and say, "We were unable to do
that, but we tried." A suggestion is not
a statute. We tried is not a fiduciary
standard. Microsoft's agent responded
only that they are open to discussion.
Discussions behind closed doors are
unacceptable when 18% of this city's
land mass and the entirety of our
aquifer are at stake. You cannot legally
pause a quasi judicial proceeding simply
to exhaust public opposition. I demand
that this motion be amended right now.
The four-month postponement must
explicitly mandate that a binding $50
million escrow and community benefits
agreement is a strict legal pre
prerequisite to the third reading of
this annexation. If you refuse to make
it mandatory, this delay is a documented
fraud. I yield my time.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Anyone else
online? Jennifer.
>> Okay, no one else online. We'll close
that and we'll come to the room. Yes,
ma'am.
Good evening, city council. My name is
Marian Callas, candidate for Ward One. I
would like to um support the proposed um
postponement of the annexation of 3,500
acres of land. Um so that way Shine and
Microsoft can come to a better deal so
they can be in a mutually prosperous
partnership. Um, with land acquisition
of this scale and for the purposes of a
data center, um, I think the city should
be negotiating for more in exchange for
our land, resources, and workforce
rather than have community benefits like
housing, um, be something that we hope
will be donated to us. Um, or uh,
something that sweetens the deal in an
effort to assuage public disapproval. I
think we should be negotiating um
community benefits into our long-term
prosperity partnership with Microsoft
from the start and that means at
annexation.
Um this is not your average annexation.
This is exceptional and it should be
treated as such. The unimaginable wealth
of Microsoft renders it immune to
extortion or bribery. To argue that
annexation in exchange for mutual
prosperity is a slippery slope is also a
fallacy. Just because we ask more from a
trillion dollar tech giant in exchange
for a massive quantity of land and
infrastructure does not will ask the
same of a request.
Um, Governor Gordon in his executive
order um stated that partnership with
municipalities is one way that data
center developers can demonstrate their
comm
um I think that with so much public
scrutiny and distrust of data centers
and elected officials. Um it would be in
the best interest of both Microsoft and
city council to negotiate a con a
contractual partnership agreement rather
than a handshake or a pledge. There are
a number of wealth management minds in
this community who could offer their
suggestions to the governing body for
how Cheyenne can continuously prosper um
from more than just taxes and jobs that
the data center boom in China is
currently which is why this postponement
might be a good idea. Um, Cheyenne's
land, resources, infrastructure, and
work workforce are precious not only to
us, but also to this new hyperscale
model of data center that seeks large
swats of land and access to a stable
power grid. This gives Cheyenne a lot
more leverage than we've ever had in the
past dealing trying to bring in data
centers. Um, so there's no need to rush
um because Microsoft is committed to
Cheyenne and this is this is the time
for negotiation is that annexation.
There's a huge pot of money on the
table. We have a really good hand and
we're playing too small. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, sir. Uh, Miss Madrid.
>> Heather Madrid, Harmony Meadows. I,
no shock, support this postponement. I
do understand where Mr. Miller is coming
from on one hand, but but at the same
time, I think that first of all, I
didn't hear anybody demand that we need
to have this $50 million agreement
before this is postponed. And I think if
that was a demand, then we probably
wouldn't get one more extra day. Um,
there needs to be time to negotiate um
instead of making demands right up
front. I agree with everything that was
just said. Um, we need to be asking for
more. I I really truly believe that
these data center companies need us more
than we need them. And we ha I mean, I'm
not I'm not opposed to data centers. I'm
not opposed to development. I am opposed
to having our rights kind of
systematically picked off one by one by
constantly updating the UDC and the land
use map and all of these, you know,
that's it's just seems really convenient
to me to have those things happening and
then to come, you know, to the podium
day of annexation and say, "Well, we're
following the UDC. We're following the
land use map." But it's like, of course
you are after you spent the last however
many years amending it to fit this
agenda. Um I I I don't think that
postponing this annexation harms a
single person and that includes
Microsoft and it would be very helpful
for public trust which has at this point
eroded almost in my opinion beyond
repair and this would do a lot for that.
So I appreciate this um this motion.
Thank you.
>> Thank you Mr. Rush.
>> Good evening, council members. My name
is Dante Rushton, director of real
estate and property management. Cheyenne
Leads. I reject the postponement. Uh,
Shy Leads. have the benefit of
partnering with the city and the county
to represent both on economic
development fronts and we work with
Microsoft to plan and build out
infrastructure and they do pay their way
on every bit of every piece they require
and so delaying does not help anything
with this annexation request. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Further discussion uh in the room
further discussion.
All right.
Uh, we'll start over here. Ma'am.
>> Okay. McAdams. Um, thank you again. I'm
kind of looking this and thinking the
reversal.
You keep talking about owner initiated.
Owner initiated. That's your right.
Well, I'd like to put a reversal on
this. If every if these items are owner
initiated, what about people who don't
want to come into the city? their rights
have been kind of abused by this
council. Just saying. So owner initiated
is out of the question for me. So I
really would like to delay this so
people can really think about these
items, the city, the county
commissioners, those people who might be
elected. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, sir.
>> Hello, council. Uh my name is Gregory
Barl and I am for postponing this uh
until some more research is done on it.
this whole data center thing going
across the country seems like there's no
restrictions, there's no rules, it's
it's I mean besides the you know city
county uh state laws that might exist
might exist uh we could do a lot more
research on this and really to ensure
that it is the best deal for the
residents and for the company. I'm not
against development. Um, but I think
that there's there's other things to
consider that we just don't know yet.
And I spoke at one of the other meetings
about this that, you know, it seems like
we're just rushing into this and and and
not really knowing uh what these huge
data centers. This isn't just a little
data center either. This thing is
massive uh thing. So, it's going to
change lives. it's going to change
Cheyenne. But, um, something I haven't
heard brought up tonight, besides these
these, uh, temperature variations and
the heat that comes off of these things,
uh, the the the stacks that have fire
constantly coming out of them. Um, but I
know there is a water shortage and
whether we have the billion gallons or
whatever that I'm still not convinced
that we have enough water to uh for all
the residents and the other things that
we need to do and for the data centers,
the huge data centers. So, one of the
things I wanted to propose was I think
the residents might feel a little bit
better, especially the ones that are
within five miles of this thing is um
it's like a shared ownership, like a
partnership in it somehow. I don't know
how that would look. Um, but if people
have a stake in it, uh, it it may be
accepted more and, uh, embraced more
from a resident standpoint. Just wanted
to throw that out there, but uh, I'm I'm
for delaying this and and studying it
some more. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi, I'm Elizabeth Marvin. Um, Willow
Pond neighborhood.
I'm not the most eloquent speaker, so
bear with me. Um,
I'm for the postponement. I appreciate
him putting the motion out. Um,
the whole thing just kind of feels like
if you give a mouse a cookie,
that's what it feels like. If we don't
postpone, we're giving the mouse the
cookie. We're giving the mouse that can
afford the cookie the cookie
because we don't have as much of a say
as they do.
I'm just a mom. I can't afford to put
$1.3 billion dollars into the community
at once. That's not something I can do.
And I think a lot of people feel that
way. A lot of people who live here in
Cheyenne feel that because they have
deeper pockets, they have a bigger
voice. And I think that's where the
erosion of trust is coming from
really and truly. not with your
decision-making skills, not with your
leadership skills, but with the fact
that their voice seems louder. Because
every time I come to one of these
discussions,
it's not people who are not getting a
paycheck from Microscop that are for
Microsoft.
Every single person that talks on behalf
of a multi-billion dollar corporation is
somehow connected to the corporation.
And it feels like
the ma the mouse now wants a glass of
milk and the mouse now wants a napkin
and then he's going to need to go to the
bathroom make sure he doesn't have a
milk mustache like this is just it's
just one of those things
we we don't
it's not equal and it's not fair and as
many committees as we have the majority
of the people speaking are for Microsoft
because of course they are they have a
vested interest in making more money.
That's all I have to say about it. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Penny Hollandbach again. Um, I agree
wholeheartedly with the young lady who
just spoke before me. Um,
I also am for postponing this. Um, I
agree. I feel like
the more we try to give, the more
they're going to take. Um I just feel
like this is all
I agree. It's just the deep pockets. Um
whoever has the most money gets the most
say. Um there was a comment about we are
not um that we have water restrictions
because we're preserving water. Well,
we're not because we're giving all of
our water to the data centers to be able
to build. So to me, that's not
preserving water. Um I think a lot of it
too we think we're just focusing on the
water aspect of these data centers. My
concern is um what about our native
wildlife and our native flowers and
where are these guys going to go? We
outlive out by archer and we've already
had probably five or six mountain lion
sightings within the last month because
they're being forced out of wherever
they're roaming at. They're coming into
town into the county to seek out shelter
and food. And in that being said, some
of them are being relocated, but a lot
of them may be just shot. So now we're
putting our wildlife at risk as well.
Also, I think we need to consider um
what about the foreign matter that's
going into the earth, the concrete, the
steel, the wires, the pipes, all of
that. How far down is that all going to
go? that stuff is never ever ever going
to break down in our earth and it's
stuck there in Wyoming which means our
lands never have a chance to regenerate.
Um we're just kind of stuck with that.
Also, is there a possibility of um water
contamination? If any of these things go
wrong, is there a possibility of water
contamination?
Um
is that always I'm sure it's always a
possibility, but what are the odds of
that happening?
Um,
and I think that might be also all I
have to say.
>> Thank you, Penny. Yes, sir.
>> Jim Cheryl, ward one candidate. Again, I
strongly encourage the governing body to
do a postponement. Uh, President Crave,
through you to Dr. Eldridge with the
amount of money that they are putting
into this project and what they could
donate to the community, they could tear
down the YMCA. They put in a lot of
money into that pool just before it went
belly up. And why didn't they go and
donate $1.2 million to the YMCA that's
been here 70 years instead of Boys and
Girls Club? Not to get off subject of
that. There's other things that we can
do to sweeten the deal. I appreciate
that they're doing a very wide
conservation area, but for the sake of
the residents to do a postponement on
this to to the the luses are going to
sell no matter what. They're trying to
get what they can out of it. I don't
blame that for I know this is their last
term. Should probably move from from
Wyoming. If I had $50 million, I'd
probably live in Hawaii. But the fact of
the matter is is that we need to do a
postponement, sweeten the deal, get some
more things that are out there and more
transparency to the to the community,
more environmental studies to the
community. This way they'll feel more
comfortable about it. So that's that's
what I'd really encourage you guys to do
a postponement, take this amendment.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Miss Madrid. Before we take
your round two, let's take first time.
Yes, sir.
Thank you very much. Uh for those of you
who don't know me, Jonathan Noble with
Microsoft. Uh Microsoft remains
committed to the community and for
paying our fair share for all the
improvements that are required by this
project. We have a long history of doing
so. The we are not asking for any
special processing or exemption from the
process. Uh no special treatment around
zoning, none of that. Uh we do recognize
that the process and the appropriate
process before us is to annex the
property, conduct the studies in
conjunction with staff to really
fine-tune and hone what are those
improvements uh from a traffic
perspective, from a water perspective,
etc. Um, staff has a long history of
being very effective around those
conversations and making sure that the
development that happens in this city
works for the members of this community
uh, first and foremost. And we abide by
that and we support that. We are hopeful
tonight to have this annexation proceed
so that we can continue with the
millions of dollars worth of studies,
the extensive work that's required with
staff, etc. to create a project that
really works for the community, not
simply tomorrow, but for a long time. As
we've talked about, this is a long-term
investment. We are eager to start the
process
towards that investment. uh but we are
uh once again committed to paying our
fair share and really feel that the
appropriate mechanism for that is
through development agreements uh like
we've done before culminating in over
$68 million worth of infrastructure
improvements for this city today.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Mr. Mr. President,
>> Councilman Wolf,
>> thank you. Uh few questions for Mr.
Noble uh through you.
>> We're on we're on your motion to amend.
I understand that. Um, thank you. Um,
Mr. Noble, you're one of the top
Microsoft decision makers involved in
this project, aren't you?
>> I am one of several. Okay. But you
occupy a position of significant
responsibility that's going to be
responsible for uh the the development
of the Highlands project and and the
other projects that you have.
>> Correct. Is that right? Um
so tell me specifically what
would be impaired by a decision to
postpone this for four months?
Like I mentioned, we we're really eager
to start those studies that are required
to inform this decision. Um right now we
don't know whether we're moving forward
under county or city. Um you know, we're
clearly in a position to move forward
under county. We actually don't think
that's the right path. We don't think
it's the right path for Microsoft. We
don't necessarily think it's the right
path for the position. So we are eager
to have clarity around the rules of the
road moving forward and really feel that
annexation sets those rules. City has a
strong record and tradition of managing
uh data center development in particular
but all types of development in the city
really effectively and we look forward
to working with the city on that
process.
>> Mr. followup please Mr. President.
Councilman,
>> Mr. Noville, the state of the record
today and from all of these hearings we
have is this. Microsoft has consistently
told us that this project is 10 to 20
years in the future. That has been your
entire testimony. Now you have said,
well, we want to do this, we want to do
that study, we want to try and make some
inroads here. But your overall testimony
is this is a long ways off. And so I
come back to this question about uh that
I asked uh Miss Irving, which is what's
your position on negotiating an
annexation agreement now with the city?
>> Mr. Noble, this has very little to do
with postponement, but uh if you could
if you could give us an answer.
>> Absolutely. So, getting back to what I
just stated, um we feel that
one, getting back to the timeline piece,
while we fully anticipate this
development to take 10 to 20 years to
build out in full, we don't plan on
waiting 10 to 20 years to start the
construction. That's the reason why
we're eager to really lay the
groundwork, establish the rules, work
with city staff, make sure that we are
all clear on the investment that it's
going to require. That's investment by
Microsoft working in conjunction uh with
city uh various other folks to build out
sewer, water, um power etc to make sure
that we are shouldering that costs
completely. um that takes time to one
design, it also takes time to build. But
our hope is to start building well
before that 10-year mark. You know,
while we don't know the design, follow
what Mr. Irving said, we don't know the
parameters yet. So, we're not in a
position to commit to a specific
timeline. Our hope is that we will be in
a position by going through this process
to start construction on those early
phases well below before that 10-year
horizon.
We can't commit to that. We don't know
that as Rachel commented at this stage
of development. Very few people can
commit to a specific timeline because
that's how early we are. That being
said, we know the process from here and
it, you know, the established process
within the Cheyenne is annexation
studies, make sure you enter into the
development agreement to make sure all
your costs are covered. Uh, and that we
are absorbing our fair share and you
know, as was highlighted before, we view
our fair share as all the costs being
driven by our project. Um, and then be
in a strong position to move forward.
The sooner we get started, I think the
more the benefits to city systems, uh,
city revenue, etc. begin to acrue.
>> Thank you, Mr. Noble.
Uh, Miss
Councilman Leborn,
>> I have a
question.
So during this period of time
when we know that [snorts]
um Colgrass is coming in with that
massive power project,
we know that there is great concern
in other places about this uh
uh question of these developments.
Was there any con consideration on
Microsoft's part to look at something
similar to what happened at the
Sweetgraphs annexation agreement?
Did you ever consider I'm just curious?
We have a precedent. It certainly is has
is different but it's in the same area
and has spells out a lot more detail
that is certainly helpful to uh me in
terms of making a logical decision about
this.
Was there consideration on Microsoft's
part or the property owner's part to
take a look at an annexation agreement
uh as you began to analyze this?
>> Mr. Noble, please.
>> So, as we uh looked at this, had
conversations with staff, we recognized
the fact that we weren't asking for any
special consideration.
um we weren't looking for exemptions to
how parks were being paid, other
infrastructure was being paid or any of
those things. So, it was pretty clear
that the existing processes and
structures worked well for the city and
worked well for us. So, we did not look
for an exemption to the um development
processes that the city has in place.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Appreciate it, sir.
Um,
have you have you spoken, sir?
>> Okay, let's have the first time folks
first. Thank you.
>> Okay. The name's Don Taylor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> I'm going to read something to you.
Opposition to US data center
construction surged in early 26 with
communities blocking or delaying 75
projects worth about 130 billion. In the
first quarter, the number of active
opposition groups more than doubled to
833 across 49 states, matching nearly
all of 2025's total disruption in the
three months. Data center watch said the
resistance was driven by concerns over
energy consumption, environmental
impacts linked to AI infrastructure.
More than 300 state bills were
introduced in early 26, including
moratorium proposals in 14 states
reflecting growing regular regulatory
scrutiny of data center expansion. I
don't get what the bums rush is. I know
that we're fighting us. We're fighting
leads who have Cynthia Lumis' daughter
as a part of leads.
We've got
basically developers
who hell yes, they're going to make
profit off this thing. That's kind of
like the chicken killing dog guarding
the hen house. They're innocent as hell,
but they're sure a lot of feathers
around their mouth. You guys are like a
bunch of little oligarchs up here.
You're competing with flipping the
commissioners, leads,
Microsoft, Meta.
I mean, we're just little peeons. one of
your folks here who's not here, he wants
to spoon feed the facts to us.
Instead of giving us real data from, you
know, to the media, he's going to spoon
feed us. That came from a open mic
in uh January. That ain't cool.
We have every right to have the facts
not spoonfed to us because we sure as
hell don't need them.
>> Sir, we watch your language, please.
>> Okay, that's fine. I'm done.
>> Have you spoken yet, ma'am?
>> No, I have.
>> Okay, let's let's have your testimony.
>> My name is Janet Tolman. I'm from Indian
Hills Community. I just have concern
because of the rush and so I'd like to
see it postponed. First of all, because
the data center will consume about one
of Cheyenne.
That's not a small portion of Cheyenne.
um and the number of people that it may
impact, those that are going to be
nextdoor neighbors to the the data
center and their concerns. Um
um and I would like just to see more
environmental studies to find out,
you know, what type of nature is living
on this property,
you know,
do these animals need to be moved
somewhere? Do the plants that might
become extinct, do they need to be
planted somewhere else?
Those are some of the concerns. Also, my
concern is I guess kind of with the data
centers, it just makes me think back to
the 1930s when the 1920s were roaring.
People expanded and did all kinds of
things
only to lose almost everything.
And I just just have a hesitation about
rushing and pushing forward um with
this. and I would like to see um it
postponed.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Good evening, council. Uh my name is Rob
Tur. I'm a business agent with Local 192
in Cheyenne, Wyoming. We're plumbers,
pipe fitters, HVAC service technicians.
We've been in the community since 1907.
We built the power plants in the 70s,
built the trolling mines, we built this
state, built the country, unions did,
but that's besides the point. Um,
I know we're here to talk about the
postponing the amendment. Uh, I just
want to say that the sooner we can get
our local workers out to work on these
projects,
um, the sooner the middle class gets
back to normal here in Cheyenne, the
middle class has been, it's been hurting
for a long time here in Cheyenne. Um,
it's been in decline. It It really has.
I mean, the middle class is stronger
here in Cheyenne than it has been since
since I've been here the last 32, 33
years. Um, it's evident. It's evident
here. Uh, I'm a local business owner
here in town. I I can see the
difference. I go downtown four nights a
week, do business downtown. I can see
the difference. There's people down
there all the time spending their money.
I'm against this this amendment because
the sooner we can get our folks to work,
local local guys here in town, we get
paid great benefits, um, health care,
retirement benefits, all this stuff
benefits the community because we're
putting back into the community this
money we're earning. the sooner we can
get our guys to work on these projects.
Local guys, I I I tell you, 360 of us
there are um like I said, since 1907
we've been here and the sooner we can
get our guys out there on the job to do
the job safely, uh the sooner this
community is going to benefit from that.
And the the guys, our local guys, we
have several here, the sooner these guys
will benefit. I just want to say one
thing real quick. The the amount of
misinformation is staggering. It it's
mindn numbing. I mean, I I just it's it
keeps swirling around. I mean, I get it.
We need to do all this responsibly, but
it's it's staggering.
It blows my mind. And one more point. I
mean, why would we want to pigeon hole
Microsoft at 50 million over this
fourmonth?
That's just then then they might just be
like, well, okay, here's here's your 50
million. Why why wouldn't we just keep
pushing it? I mean, we can we can get
more, you know, why why stop at 50
million, right? Right. Right. You know,
this is America. If Lumis wants to sell
her land, God bless her. God bless
America. Let's get this sucker going.
And thank you for your time.
>> Thank you, sir.
Anyone else? First time.
Yes, ma'am.
>> Hello. I'm Jana, a homeowner in
Cheyenne. I already wrote to all of you
recently about the noise level and this
is a huge problem throughout the
country. This is not theoretical. You
live here too. I don't think Microsoft
is going to give you millions of dollars
to move to Marta's Vineyard or some
other place like that where they don't
have data centers.
>> We're talking about postponement.
>> Yeah. At the very least, of course. And
Yes. Yes. Um, and the people that, you
know, support this, I don't think they
even understand like what they going to
be dealing with. People with the
construction, yeah, there is noise with
construction, but you go home and
hopefully you can get a good night's
sleep. But this is constant. And there
were I send you videos where you can
hear the sounds, this low um frequency
humming that people hear all the time,
247. And any noise that is 247 is
torture. if if it's something that's
irritating and this is a facts there is
one video where from Newsmax and this
investigator woman she looked into this
problem in detail and um she's saying
that this loan she calls it tonal noise
and
>> ma'am we're we're discussing whether to
postpone or not.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's what I'm saying
because we have to find out more about
this.
>> Okay. So you're in favor?
>> Yeah.
That's important because
they need to show us. First of all, they
don't have a plan. My understanding is a
detailed plan. How many buildings, what
kind, what type of noise is going to be,
how far is going to be heard, what kind
of power are they going to have, what
kind of power they going to, how many
megawatts they going to start at, what
is their plan to scale up to, how fast.
I haven't heard any of those details.
And my understanding is when you had
annexations like this for like housing
development there was a detailed plan
and I don't know that there is a I
haven't seen anything a detailed plan
from Microsoft and they say they don't
ask for any special treatment but they
are you told when I came here the first
time on May 26 you said that this
processes take a long time five to five
to six years well last time I was here
one woman who representing Microsoft
said that they are planning to buy this
land in the next few weeks. So all of a
sudden five to six years of planning is
turning into a few weeks because I don't
think they're going to buy this land and
this they have pretty serious guarantees
that they can do what they want on it.
So it's just
everything sounds wrong and I don't
think we're going to be safe. You live
here too. I hope you think about your
well-being and we need more studies.
They need to show us a building. They
have many data centers around the
country. Show us a building. Tell us
this is how much noise it's going to
make. this is how much power it's going
to be. This is how much chemical slash
we're going to discharge for each
building and we have this many
buildings. Where is that plan? Cuz I
haven't heard about it and I really
looked. So that's the problem that we
need. We don't know enough about what's
going to happen here. And anyway,
>> thank you very much. Appreciate it.
Anyone else for the first time?
Okay, Miss Madrid,
>> Heather Madrid, Harmony Meadows. I
apologize. I try to avoid double
dipping. Um, there's just a few things
that I would like to address that have
been said with regards to this um
postponement. First of all, I would like
to say to thank you guys because despite
what is out there on social media and
what happens in these rooms, I have had
conversations with almost every single
one of you and there been actionable
steps taken to address concerns and I
appreciate that very much and I think
it's important that that everybody
understands that that's that that is
happening. Um so um somebody had earlier
asked about failure in these closed loop
systems and and yes of course like
that's a that happens with everything.
Um the the problem is that when we
cluster data centers or anything else
it's creating a statistical certainty
that something will go wrong and it's
not if it's when. Um and I actually ran
the numbers and I can send that to you
because I can't remember it all off the
top of my head. Um but um with regards
to the need to annex in order to plan, I
well I do understand that the problem
with this city's process is that it
isn't just annex and then time to plan.
It's annex, update the map, reszone and
it's over. There is no time to plan or
do these studies
um between annexing and reszoning and
and and then the public process is over.
Um, I would say I agree. It probably is
not typical to
have these long-term plans developed on
these massive properties, but is it is
an annexation of this size typical? Of
course, it's not typical that there
would be plans. This is the most
atypical annexation that we've ever seen
in the city. Um,
I remain unimpressed that Microsoft is
paying their fair share. That's the bare
minimum that we all pay our fair share.
We that's we all do that. That's kind of
an expectation. That's not like a gift
to the community that you're paying for
your own infrastructure.
Um
and I could be I could be wrong about
the local workers. Um I think they're
working. I don't know if there's some
that are still not working considering
all the projects that are h already
happening. So, I think our local
workers, if they want to be working, I
think they are. I don't know. I don't
have any evidence to support that one
way or the other, but that would be my
guess. And um if they're [snorts] not
working, it just the the need for a man
camp doesn't support the idea that local
workers don't have jobs. Um okay, I
think that's all. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Further discussion on the
postponement.
I uh want you guys
>> can you turn on your microphone please
and identify yourself?
>> I just want you guys to postpone it. You
know you guys there's so much anizing so
much Microsoft going on. First of all
that guys was talking about Microsoft he
needs to know figure out what everything
else that Microsoft that we have already
around this area they should have
figured out by now what's going on
instead of saying that we need to have
time and see what's going on. They
should know already because that
Microsoft that when we have is up and
running. That's my first one. Second
one, uh, nothing's [clears throat] back
to normal for us, for me where I live.
If you were living next to where they're
building these Microsoft, it's it's
annoying. It's heartbreaking watching
these equipment going across, right? I
could see it right there working at
where my where I live and drilling
wells. too. Well, they did the first
well, second well, they're drilling and
you guys, some of you guys that uh for
it don't understand. Corpus don't
understand. We be people that live near
or residents, family, my neighbors.
If you were living out where we were,
you probably consider thinking about it.
What we go through, what we see, we
don't know what's coming to that area. I
know it's going to be big. And then you
know it's it's like I said if you were
living if it's you and that Microsoft
next to your house near your
neighborhood you'd be considered too.
Second of all my wife was talking this
is going to be a little off. Uh my wife
was talking to one of her friends. Her
friend was talking to somebody that's a
big honcho of Microsoft. She asked him
the question. What about the wells you
guys are drilling so forth? How about if
you contaminate the water? He turned
around and told her, he says, "Who
cares? You know, we're going to own
Cheyenne pretty soon." This is from one
of these Microsoft big executives.
>> Microsoft doesn't have any wells.
>> Data center.
>> They don't. They're not using wells.
They're using
>> Yes, they are with me where they are.
They drilling two wells. I am on the
wellwater.
>> That's not a Microsoft.
>> No, I'm not Tom Mox like data center.
You guys science data center wants it
too. Same thing. may be different, but
I'm saying this guy said he's gonna own
Cheyenne. That's what that's what quote
I just something you guys got to think
about. Who's going to control this city?
Are you guys or they going to control
it? That's all I said to say. Thank you,
sir, for allowing me to speak. But yeah,
nothing's back to normal where I live.
So, there's no normal on that people
that live near it.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, sir.
I'm back. Uh this is Gregory Barrow. I'm
Cheyenne resident and uh I just wanted
to bring up something that in support of
holding off on this for right now until
November 9th. Um because I think the the
data centers have overtaken this country
so quickly, not just Wyoming, but all
over. And uh there's regula or there's
going to be laws coming out that are
going to change things. There's there's
going to be requirements that as the one
lady spoke about noise complaints and
the noise these things put out. Um
there's a lot of that kind of stuff I
don't think we fully understand yet and
and that's what may change in 10 years
from now. the long range estimate I
heard uh how many of you council members
are even going to be here in 10 15 years
from now. So that all changes. So my
suggestion to you is for possibly
uh getting together a coalition of
citizens because there is such a um you
know um concern about this whole matter
and at last I checked Cheyenne's about
65,000 70,000 people. I understand the
workers that are, you know, needing the
work. That's fine. But there's a lot
more residents that got to deal with
this, especially the ones that are
living around it. So, this coalition
that you could kind of draft up would
be, I don't know, 15, 20 people that can
monitor, that can stay in touch with it
because city council, you know, they
they need to have some bite this
coalition. They need to have the mayor's
ear so that they could alert the city to
when things do go ary if they go ary
right seven 10 years down the road. Uh,
I don't know if this exists anywhere
else in the country, but we could be the
first and we should be cuz citizens are
very concerned about this. And I think
something like that would help keep the
playing field honest and so that the
people would have a voice because
ultimately the people are the ones that,
you know, decide and they're they've got
the majority. uh it's not you know it's
not the other business owners and all
that the people come together and I
think you've seen that demonstration
tonight where we've come together with
these concerns and so that's a proposal
that there I mean there's quite a few
that are pretty smart on all this data
center stuff and they could work with
Microsoft but they could also have the
mayor's ear the city council ear so when
if this gets approved later and problems
do arise
um they would have a voice in it and
that's where the delay or the moratorum
or whatever you want to call it for four
months it might give that time to where
it can actually form that
>> thank you
>> anyone else last chance yes ma'am
>> Donna Frostto again so I'm for the
postponement as well um just research it
does never hurt anybody. Um, having
homes here, we always had to abide by
laws when we purchase homes, whether
it's billion dollars or not, we have to
worry about our neighbors as well. And
as you guys being the committee that
protects its citizens, I think it's your
due diligence to not just look at the
money, but look at the health and
research of what we have going on behind
it. It just kind of feels like, you
know, why if it's all for the growth,
then why didn't Budweiser come in years
ago when they wanted to come in? because
the resources, the water, all that
stuff, they were rejected, but now the
data centers are rushing in. So, I'm
just saying what is the what is the
difference on holding back for a little
bit just to protect the citizens a
little bit more and give us an ease of
mind of what's going to happen to our
city.
>> Thank you.
>> Anyone else?
>> [clears throat]
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Sorry. Penny Hollandbach again. Just a
final word. Um I'm so for postponing
this. Um the bottom line is I think a
lot of us here just don't want the DC
centers here in our community. Um it's
not about the money. It's not about what
they can bring to the community. It's
about us not wanting them on our land.
It's about us not wanting to live across
the street from them, behind them, next
to them. We don't want to look out our
windows and see what we used to have
these beautiful rolling hills. Now we
have this big ugly data center that just
looks horrible and it's not it's not in
Wyoming. I've been in Wyoming for 40
plus years. I don't want to have to look
at ugly, nasty data centers. And I know
Microsoft was saying that they will
basically reconstruct
um the land that they dig up to kind of
mimic our natural habitat of what was
there before. It's not the same. It took
years and years and years for the rocks
and the bushes and all that to grow.
You're not going to replace that. Um so
that was my final word. I think you all
just need to look at what the actual
residents want, not about the money. Um,
it's about what we want. We've been
here. We love our land. We want to keep
our land the same way that it's always
been. I'm up for change, don't get me
wrong. But do we have to destroy our
land in order to do that? Um,
and I just think you all really need to
postpone this and think and listen to
the residents about what we want. And
from what I'm hearing, we don't want
this. It's just not Wyoming. It's not
the Wyoming way. Thank you.
>> Thank you. All right. Um, not seeing
anyone else. We'll close public comment
and we'll bring the motion to amend back
up on the dis. Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
I was always told you don't share your
dirty laundry of your family.
But I got to say that this whole
situation
is so disturbing to me. We have two
people who have come up with a
an amendment to take us right back to
where we were at the beginning of the
spring when uh one of our fellow
councilmen had the idea for a moratorum.
We went through the whole process. We
went through all of the readings. We
took all of the comment. We heard every
single bit of it. We listened. We
listened to both sides.
This council took a vote to to um deny
the moratorum
and to move forward. So here we are
again doing the very same thing which I
find incredibly disingenuous
and I am certain that my esteemed
colleagues have they're trying to do the
right thing.
But to me, this is just this is like a
workaround. I didn't get what I wanted,
and you can give me that face.
I didn't get what I wanted, so I'm going
to take another run at it. And that's
not okay. It's not okay for these people
to say, "Okay, we told you no once, but
maybe try it again, and we'll give you
another false hope that we're going to
do that."
We we made a decision before not to do
it and there were the reasons for doing
it.
We have conflated these issues
incredibly right now. This is about
annexation.
It's not about all these other things
we've talked about. It's about whether
or not a land owner who has requested
annexation of their land that they want
to sell whether or not they can annex
it. But we've conflated it all out of
bounds
and that's not okay.
We need to follow the process we have
and we need to do it honestly and with
transparency
which is what we keep hearing even
though we've listened to hundreds of
hours I think of comments and emails
about this.
So, I would encourage
um my fellow council members to vote
against this ordinance. We made a
decision before to move forward. Let's
move forward. This this last speaker put
it better than anybody else. She said,
"We don't want them here. It's not going
to be
I want them here in five months. It
doesn't matter what we do." And that's
okay that some people are not going to
want it. I'm sorry that they're not
gonna get everything they want, but
if we postpone this for four months, in
four months we'll be in the very same
situation and we'll just keep doing it
over and over. And that's not okay for
the community who we're supposed to be
entrusted to re represent and to build.
And it's not okay for people who have
put in so much hard work on this issue
and we keep dangling this carrot in
front of them. So I would encourage my
fellow council members to vote no on
this amendment.
>> Um Dr. Aldrich
>> President Crave through you. Um I
actually am going to be a no vote on
this postponement tonight and the reason
for that is because of exactly what my
colleague from W 2 just said. Um, and I
made a note when uh, Miss Hollandback
spoke. Um, she said basically, we don't
want it here. Um, I don't think this
post I'm not gonna argue with you, but
evidently this postponement is not going
to give you what you're hoping to get
from it. It's not going to
>> give you answers to the environmental
pieces. We've got uh information from um
our attorney, our city attorney that
talks about that um annexation decisions
or legislative decisions based on
statutory criteria and public policy
considerations.
Um and that there is are some real
concerns with trying to tie this to a
financial dollar amount. Um for that
reason, I'm going to be a no vote. I I
don't think that this is putting this
off is going to be beneficial. uh to
anyone that's involved in the process.
>> Uh Councilman White.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Through you,
um
I'm not in favor of this amendment for
uh really a very simple reason.
Suppose a ranch owner would like to sell
their land to a manufacturer
or a warehouse distribution center.
housing development.
I doubt we'd be having these
discussions.
the fact that, you know, I'm all for
responsible growth and environmental
stewardship.
Um, but boy, I believe private property
rights are affected whenever government
gets in the way
of a property owner who's a willing
seller
and a business that is a willing buyer.
that that really
um
that really concerns me and I think we'd
be setting a very bad precedent. So,
does that mean that
a business wants to come into town, goes
through the process, and then
maybe a a council, a future council
says, "You know what? I think we're
going to hold out and before we annex
anything, we're gonna we're going to say
we want 10 million.
I just think it it really
concerns me that we're treating
businesses
inconsistently.
Does Microsoft have deep pockets? You
bet.
But just because they they're a
multi-billion dollar corporation
doesn't really mean we should be
treating them differently.
The owner of the property wants to
engage in a lawful business transaction
with a willing buyer.
And based on everything I've seen, the
annexation request satisfies statutory
requirements and all of our ordinances.
And so if we're to deny a reasonable
business transaction, even though all
the legal requirements have been met,
and then by the way, hang a $50 million
tab on it as well.
I I I just nope. I can't I can't support
it.
>> Councilman Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. President, through you.
Uh I guess I would repeat what I said
one of the previous meetings because not
all of you were here for that. But if
you really want to stop data centers,
the building you need to go to is the
one at the Golden Dome about seven and a
half blocks that way. The reason the
data centers come here is because of tax
laws. the tax structure in Wyoming
that's set at the state legislative
level. Uh, of course, the climate is
suitable for data centers here in
Wyoming. That's another reason they come
here or not coming here because the
Cheyenne City Council's given them their
golden ticket. We actually have the
strictest regulations for data centers
of any city in the country. That's why
they want to build in the city uh
as opposed to the county. Uh
on another note since I guess I got
called into the guard and been told I'm
on the take for from data centers and
I've told my colleagues this I worked
for the railroad for 44 years and talk
about noise.
I'm surprised they can still hear,
but uh I follow in the railroad
retirement system. It's since I was
elected after I retired, I go into a
system called last employer of record,
which is the city of Cheyenne, according
to them. So, they take 50 cents of every
dollar I make being a councilman. We
make $2,000. That's our compensation for
being up here. So, there's a th00and
that. then they'll take half of the
annuity. So, your spousees will also
fall in the railroad retirement system.
My wife, who has nothing to do with any
of this, loses $500 of her annuity
because I'm a councilman. Then they take
social security out of my check. We'll
never see that. We're not in the social
security system. So,
I my pay was $3942 a month for serving
on the council.
So, never taken one dollar of corporate
money, not even in my 10 years of being
in the legislature. So, thank you,
whoever said that, for giving me the
opportunity to put this on public
record.
>> Thank you, Councilman Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. President, through you.
Thank you for your service, Mr. ESel.
[laughter]
Um, where do you start on this? Um,
this is the largest annexation the city
of Cheyenne has ever done.
It's probably the largest one we will
ever do because if you look at the maps,
all of these big blocks of land are
being
divided, bought up, built on.
and we first started this and let's
review a little history to address
Councilman
Emmens uh concerns about why we're doing
this.
This is not 2025.
This is 2026
in which the entire country's opinions
about data centers has fundamentally
changed and we as the leaders of the
city for better or for worse need to
recognize that. [snorts]
Now what did we do with the moratorum?
moratorum. I voted against the moratorum
as did nine other as did nine people on
the council. I didn't think it was the
right thing to do. I thought it would
not be responsible. It would create
chaos uh in the business community. So,
I voted against that.
This is different.
Madame counselor woman, this is
different.
Microsoft, this first of all, this comes
to us with every single issue you can
imagine in an annexation proceeding.
Absolutely everyone. And we got another
one this evening from the city attorney.
So when this first arose and goes starts
our complicated process,
I said
we should treat this differently.
We should treat this with the enormity
and respect
that it deserves.
We didn't do that. We treated it with
the same respect that we treat a 2.7
acre annexation, which is one of the
items that we just dealt with.
This is the largest one of the largest
corporations in the world who is already
here has a number of data centers in
operation
under construction and they have plans
for many more so we're told.
So my first reaction was okay we should
create a separate process of this. Did
that happen? No.
That was in my judgment a failure of
leadership.
We should have done that. So once we're
into this process, what do we do? Now it
feels like we've all been listening to
data centers for months now. I have been
to
probably not hundreds of hours, but a
whole bunch of time along with everybody
else.
But for this project,
this is the first full council meeting
that we actually are addressing this.
This went to the committee. The
committee heard some testimony. First,
well, I take it back. First, we had a
public hearing
and we had some testimony there and then
we had a committee meeting and now we're
here on second reading.
If this postponement is not approved and
you can count the votes yourselves,
we're going to have another committee
hearing and then we're going to have
another full council discussion of this.
So, if you want to save some time,
council members, you should vote to
postpone.
But I don't think that's the way it's
going to turn out. Now, there are a host
of issues that we should address with
this and I've been trying to do that.
But the biggest issue is that
what is proposed in here is trying to
balance up the benefits with the
detriments, the burdens that come from
all of these projects.
And a notion which is actually very well
supported that cities ought to be who
are in this decision-making process
ought to be in partnerships with the
data center developers.
And that's all I've suggested.
Spend some time talking about what a
partnership looks like. And guess what?
We have a perfect model from 2018.
And I have it right here. And what does
it do? And it's the one with the same
land owners.
And it is
a very remarkable document because it
starts from the premise of we're doing
an annexation and zoning which in and of
itself
visiates your whole argument which I've
heard time and time again that we're
only talking about annexation. So they
do a document that says we're going to
talk about annexation. We're going to
talk talk about zoning. We're going to
talk about traffic. We're going to talk
about dedication of land for parks.
We're going to talk about, you know, the
the planned development of this
community. And that's all I'm suggesting
that we get the mayor and his staff to
do.
But for some reason,
my colleagues apparently don't want to
do that. They don't want to lead on this
issue. They don't want to appear to be
actually in a position of saying,
Microsoft, what are you going to do for
us? Yes, a million here, a million there
is fine, and you're going to pay for all
of your improvements. Well, I agree with
Miss Madrid on this. Of course, they're
going to pay for those. They benefit
from them. Why wouldn't they? So, we
shouldn't pay for them. you don't want
to pay for them out here.
Uh I keep hearing this notion of private
property and I'm just mystified by it.
Councilman White, Councilman Aldridge,
we're not interfering with anybody's
private property rights.
You have no right as a property owner to
be annexed. Mr. Brody's memo to us this
evening tells us exactly that and the
Kate law which I have read is abundantly
clear on that subject.
So if somebody comes to us and says,"I
own this piece of property and I want
you to annex it." And by God, you have
to do that.
We can tell them
maybe, we can tell them no.
And that's clearly within our
legislative powers. And if we tell them
no, we haven't deprived them of any
private property rights. That's a
ridiculous notion.
When you own private property, you have
in the law a bundle of sticks. None of
those sticks represents the right to be
annexed.
There, the property owner's rights in
this case are completely unaffected if
we to deny this outright.
Now if we if they the property owner has
made the requisite showing under the
facts and that the procedures have been
followed then the statute says you shall
issue
the annexation order. But that's a
factbased determination and we have yet
to make that determination on this
council.
So,
I could go on and on. Um, and we may
because in fact, if we deny this
postponement, I got a whole bunch of
questions for the planning department.
Um,
but so, let me just summarize.
It's in all of our interests, members of
the council, to postpone this. It's in
all of our interests to buck up the
mayor and the chief of staff and the
staff and say go negotiate a strong
agreement that deals with all of these
issues. And I've outlined them in this
motion and there are probably more and
get those things addressed. And I'm not
commanding you to do that, but it's in
the city's interest to do it. And we
just heard Mr. Noble really say, "Oh, we
want to do some planning and we want to
do a thing." That's just corporate speak
for we don't know what the heck we're
going to do in the next four months, but
it's unlikely to be very substantial.
And then you heard him close his
argument by saying, "Yes, we may be 10
to 20 years out, which brings me to my
one other final point, which Mr.
uh Brody's memo brings out clearly which
is if this is so far away,
why are we doing it? Why don't we deny
this annexation
and then let the council that's in place
5 years from now, 10 years from now deal
with all of these issues?
That notion hasn't gotten any traction,
but I may bring it up again. Thank you,
Mr. President, I appreciate how well
you've conducted this hearing and um and
for allowing me to make that
presentation.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> thank you, Mr. [clears throat] Chair.
Three thanks. One, I apologize.
>> No apology.
>> No, no, it's I need to
>> I know you feel strongly about this,
Councilwoman Emmens,
>> and I didn't have dinner, so my blood
sugar is probably all screwed up, but I
do want to apologize because that was
not okay.
Second of all, um oh man, I forgot my
second again.
Um
oh, I know the document that um we were
given with the um amendment on it
to numbers two through the end of the
road. I have no issues with. I just feel
like many of those things are
contractual in nature and those are
things that can still happen but it
doesn't ha we don't have to postpone in
order for those things to happen. We're
going to have those studies. They have
to provide the studies through EPA
through the county through the city.
They have to do those things in order to
go forward anyway. So I don't think it's
an eitheror. I think we I feel strongly
we can proceed with this and still make
sure that everything is done
appropriately is done to protect the
environment to pro protect the community
and to protect the people in Cheyenne.
>> Mr. Sharon, just one comment.
>> Your your thought is exactly right. But
going to a point that I made in a
interrogation I had with Mr. Bloom is
that
once we annex, zone, change the map, all
of which we are going to be asked to do
tonight and then at the final council
meeting on third reading. The public's
involvement in that process is done.
all of you disappear from that process
because it's all done behind at that
point the closed doors of hopefully the
renovated town city hall. Uh so while
yes, you're right that some of that work
may be done, the reason you want to put
it in an annexation agreement and the
reason they did it in Sweetgrass is that
they're locked into it by contract.
And that's why we need to do it now. And
we and if we miss this opportunity, if
we miss the opportunity to get an
annexation agreement now and define
these issues and define their
obligations because remember they want
these things not in place now in 10
years from now. And we better be awfully
careful and awfully thoughtful because
in 10 years from now who knows what the
environmental constraints are going to
be. And if we don't say we want you to
use best available technology,
then we may never get it because it
might not be in Microsoft's interest 10
years from now to actually build that
way.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Thanks, Mr. President. Through you, just
real quick, my colleague from W once
said is on point. Just again, this is
not the same as the moratorum. It's just
slowing it down. That's what people
wanted. That's why I proposed it. So, I
ask everybody vote I on this. Thank you.
>> All right. Anyone else? Mr. Labour.
Um, so we don't have any comments online
from the council people and the mayor.
>> Mr. President, I don't see any hands
raised.
>> Thank you. Uh, well, [clears throat] Mr.
President, I hope you'll allow some
latitude here. We're on the
postponement.
I'm trying I'm just trying to push the
meeting along. Mr. Labour, we're going
to have another opport opportunity after
this discussion. Well, but I I have one
question in particular that I'd like
answered before I make my statement
here. And that question is, is the uh
Microsoft property here that uh looks
like it's going to be annexed
going to be turned over to the leads
organization for a business park or is
Microsoft going to run that business
park?
Um, I don't know who to ask that to. Um,
>> I think Dante's here.
>> We'll ask Mr. Russian if he has any
information on that.
Welcome again, sir.
>> Thank you, Councilman. To answer your
question, it has not been agreed to yet.
We currently do manage Bison Business
Park Proper as it currently sits. It'd
be a discussion to be had.
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
>> That's an important point, Mr.
President, that and I think it's um very
relevant to our discussion of the
postponement
because the postpone the entire idea of
the postponement is to gather
information,
bring it into a more uh cohesive form
and work with uh those people and
entities that are interested. I
particularly want to note that uh in our
agenda tonight, we are approving uh that
agreement with leads for $100,000 a
year. it's on the consent agenda, but I
consider that to be a tremendous bargain
and something that is relevant to this
discussion because of lead's management
of existing business parks and Microsoft
data centers in those facilities.
So I think that it's important to note
that Microsoft has been a good good
partner I guess you could call it in uh
those data center projects that are do
exist in those business parks.
And I also want to point out that one of
the things that we're talking about here
is the amount of money that some of us
believe is reasonable to ask from
Microsoft Corporation when they annex
into the city and become part of the
city. And that is something that has
been mentioned here earlier, Mr.
president
regarding the question of the industrial
sighting commission and how those
projects uh
become law and are built. So, I'd like
to point out that
people might not agree with this, but
the facts of the matter are
that the industrial sighting commission
and that process, which was begun many
years ago by
Governor Hler and his whole point was
growth on our terms.
Has changed now that uh the legislature
saw fit to do that.
So, it's not extortion
any more than it's extortion to uh get
the payments that were now being made,
as I understand, from the treasurer
today from the gold mine folks up out in
the county. It's about paying for
participation in the city. And the
reason I asked for this postponement,
and I think it's spilled out in a number
of places,
is the fact that we have tremendous
needs in this city. And they're not to
fix the YMCA.
They're not for
wishes,
they're for needs.
And we could certainly use this revenue
in very effective ways on our drainage
program. that is woefully behind the
times and needs a lot of help or the
other items in our [snorts]
many many million dollars of delayed
uh maintenance on other issues. So I
just want to be sure what try to
understand why I have my opinion about
this and it is that uh this delay this
postponement is reasonable
because of the process.
This is not
[snorts]
anything more than those of us who
take this responsibility
and look at the issues
choose to act on in an absolute good
faith method.
When I look at the conditions of
annexation
that we are to review
and we do review as we did tonight on
smaller projects and this obviously is
uh
inconceivable in the past
but the question is logical and feasible
in my mind.
So when I look at logical and feasible
in South Cheyenne,
which with what's going on right out
there right now, when I look at logical
and feasible when
um tall grass
energy is coming off that Cheyenne hub
with massive power to one of the largest
power plants,
certainly bigger than anything in the
region. I don't know nationally.
Is that logical? Well, that's my opinion
of whether that's logical or not. And
that's all the decisions that we all
have to make. Is this logical?
Is it legitimate
to follow through with the process that
is in existence in the state of Wyoming
to ask massive
industrial developments
to contribute to the needs of the
community? Well, it obviously is. If
this is the particular method of doing
it, uh so be it. But we're not being
uh obstructionists.
We're not being uh
attempting to
go back on a decision that's been made.
This decision is being made tonight. And
we have a process here that we brought
forward for legitimate discussion in a
good faith effort to talk about
unprecedented
issues. We don't deal with these kind of
issues. Um we haven't we we've dealt
with some really good projects out in
our business parks. I applaud Leads for
everything they've done.
But this is way different
and it's way more controversial.
So asking for the process
to follow our existing template of the
immediately adjacent property
might be considered by some to be
wrong.
We don't believe it's wrong. We believe
it's a legitimate attempt, good faith
attempt
to look at something
that's never happened here before
and probably will never happen again and
to try to make sure that right from the
initiation of that annexation,
we have these conditions and these
conditions are serious.
So, I'm sorry that some individuals seem
to believe that uh those of us that
support this are obstructionists or uh
unrealistic or trying to I I can't
imagine what our motivation could be. My
motivation is to look at these facts. My
motivation is to look at South Cheyenne
and in the county
where the massive power plant is being
is under construction
and that power is going to go somewhere
and it's not going to go far and it's
going to go a lot of it. And so I hope
it's understood
that we're not trying to stand in the
way of progress. We're not trying to uh
harm Microsoft.
Uh they they've I'm certainly aware of
all that they've done and and certainly
there are they're not the only uh data
center people. I mean there are other
data center folks doing it. So I hope
everyone understands we're looking at
this set of facts
and at this very important decision that
is unlike any I've ever the magnitude of
this and the amount of money involved is
uh incredibly different than my many
many years on the council. It's just
unprecedented. So this is our effort to
look at this difficult unprecedented
situation within
the law within our motion tonight and
say we have an opinion about this and
this opinion is
that we need to really understand better
the details as has been spelled out in
other annexation agreements.
So, I don't think it's wrong and I and I
hope we all recognize that uh there's
differences of opinion and there's
differences of interpretation,
but as I interpret
this annexation action,
particularly in light of the governor's
recent uh uh statement, [clears throat]
and it's it's on it's on us. And if
we're looking at it a little
differently, so be it. If we're looking
at it within the process that we're
following tonight, so be it.
That's that's the way this works or it
should work. And if we don't succeed
with this uh motion tonight, certainly I
I expect I'm going to be on the council
for another two and a half years. I
expect to be involved in these
decisions. I expect to try to try to uh
use my best judgment to look at South
Cheyenne and what's happening there and
all of the considerations that come into
that area which are
city county um lot of lot of issues and
I look forward to doing that. I expect
that uh we'll be able to do it. But
above all else, I want to note uh my
colleague here's point.
The public, this is the public's
opportunity and I and I applaud
the meeting tonight. everybody had a
chance to to speak, but we're going to
move into a different process
and it's going to be very expensive and
it's not going to be of the scale we've
seen previously in my opinion. So, uh I
hope we all keep it in mind that uh
we're in this together. We have
differences of opinion. We look at this
process a little differently. Um, I
certainly do. I've attended these
meetings. I think uh we're going to be
getting later in this meeting into the
uh planning commission's questions.
Uh I think there are a lot of questions.
This is our attempt to get the answers.
If it doesn't uh succeed tonight, we
understand,
but it is not anything more than
attempting to do the job we were elected
to do. Thank you.
>> We have a motion in front of us to amend
and postpone until November 9th. Any
further discussion?
>> Seeing none, all in favor of the motion
to amend signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> No vote.
>> Online, do we have
Councilman Renie? We have Councilman
Renie and Mayor Patrick Collins
>> and their votes.
>> No.
>> Okay. The uh hands of those in favor is
Councilman Wolf, Councilman Moody,
Councilman Lebornne. The motion to amend
fails. We're back on the main mo main
ordinance.
Further discussion from the council.
Dr. Aldridge. Uh, President Crave, I
have a question for city treasurer. I'm
just wondering if she might be able to
tell us uh what, and I recognize that
this is not necessarily Microsoft's um
or the proposed land, but if she can
tell us what the revenue was um from
property taxes that were paid from um
data centers this last year.
>> Madame
Director, do you have any way of knowing
that?
>> Um Mr. president through you. I do not
have that way.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you. Um I'm going to be a yes vote
for this annexation tonight. I believe
that um it's in the city's best interest
to be able to provide city water um and
have it metered versus having um the
opportunity for someone to uh drill into
our aquifers uh through wells. I also
believe that uh the discharge, my
understanding, will be put into tanks
and that way it'll be able to be tested
before it's released into our public
water system, which I believe is u a
health and safety standard and is more
beneficial for our community. Um I also
believe that the property tax that we
will um have generated from this um even
if this takes 10 years to build out.
>> Point of order. We're talking about
>> I'm voting why about talking about why
I'm going to vote for this.
>> I know, Madame Councilwoman. But you've
also argued uh that this is just about
annexation, not about data centers.
>> Well, thank you, Councilman Wolf. Um, go
ahead and and let's let's hear the rest
of your
>> And the my last reason for voting for
this annexation is um because I believe
that through this annexation process,
which will then uh be addressed on the
next item of zoning, that we will also
be collecting the sales tax for however
long on electricity, which quite
honestly is probably the bigger benefit
of order.
>> I will be voting yes. You have no idea
whether that's true or not for the
Highlands project.
>> Councilman Wolf is her opinion, please.
>> Yes.
>> Further.
>> Thank you.
>> Further discussion on the ordinance in
front of us.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. President. Through
you. Thank you everybody for public
comment. I will be a no. This is too
large. A lot of unanswered questions.
Jobs are not going to be impacted for
construction. They're still constructing
data centers.
you know, we're still going to collect
the tax revenue from the data center is
already there and the electricity sales
tax that are already there. So, it's
just to increase the revenue. However,
we have to look at more than just are we
going to get that revenue 10 20 years
from now. So again, it's not going to
impact the ones that are currently there
or anybody's jobs that they currently
have. But I will be a no to any
unanswered questions. Thank you,
>> Dr. Emmens. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I'm
going to be a yes on this. And the
reason is because I feel like when I was
elected to this position, it was to be a
steward for the city and the city's
resources and the services to the uh
residents of the community. And this is
the right thing to do to impact all of
those uh city resources by annexing the
property. Thank you, Councilman Wolf.
>> Mr. President, through you um
to my third issue that I was going to
bring up which was is a set of questions
about annexation for Mr. Bloom.
Is he still with us?
And
Direct your questions to the to the
chairman. Mr. Wolf, what's your
question?
>> Mr. President, I actually have a series
of questions.
>> Let's take them one at a time.
>> Um,
Mr. Bloom, let me give you this.
That's for the public.
This is for
the council.
>> Thank you.
>> Go ahead, Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Uh, Mr.
Chairman, through you, Mr. Bloom. Um
what I'm trying to do is understand the
parameters of annexation in in your
thinking in the thinking the planning
and zoning department
and I've constructed a set of
hypotheticals
uh which are uh before you in shorthand
form. I've also reproduced the statutes
that pertain to annexation.
Um and um I want to start with a base
case scenario which is land to be
annexed about 3,500 acres. It's
undeveloped used exclusively for cattle
ranching operation. It's close to the
city but not right next door to
developed city or residences east and
south of Laramie County uh community
college south of uh Sweetwater
Sweetgrass residential area and
commercial development.
If the property is annexed to the city
then the city's obligated to apply sewer
and water. Uh the land is within the
sewer and water boundary.
uh base zoning is agriculture.
Okay. So the first question is
um
this is just cattle ranch that's all it
is and
that's all
maybe they think about it. So so they
come to you land owner comes to you and
says we want this annexed.
So, what do you ask him?
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> Sarah, three to members of council.
First of all, Councilman Wolf, I really
appreciate all the work you put into
this. I I don't know what your goal here
is to evaluate this. If we do have
someone come forward with an annexation
request, yeah, it's their right to
request annexation. We make a
recommendation on how it meets required
findings, which are very loose, very
open interpretation. And ultimately our
recommendation is presented to you the
governing body for you to consider if it
meets those criteria. And in this
specific case we feel it meets the
criteria for annexation.
>> Okay. So if somebody just has a ranch
and vacant land then you say okay I'll
take your petition for annexation and uh
move forward with it.
>> Okay. So so so on that question you
would answer
>> yes annex. So, let's go to question
number two. They come to you and say,
"We want you to annex this, but we're
going to put a conservation easement
across the entire property that's going
to say that this has to be in
agriculture forever.
Does the city think it's prudent to
annex uh agriculture land for
perpetuity?"
director,
>> chair, members of the city council. Um,
I would defer that question to you.
Ultimately, is your decision to make as
the representatives of the city, the
city governing body determine if that's
the best interest regarding conservation
easements in general um where they are
put in place in areas that would be
potentially urban urbanized and for
urban development. Those are problematic
because they hinder growth and
development. Now, in this specific case
of the Highlands annexation, uh our
comprehensive plan does talk about a
natural and sensitive heritage area
which is paralleling the it's along the
ridge line and it's the bluff. Um that
is something that was included in the
2014 plan document. It was actually
included in the 2006 plan document as
well. So, um, looking at the community,
uh, sensitivity to that natural feature,
I would think that if there's a
preservation easement of some source or
some type of easement that guaranteed
that that uh, further complied with the
plan, which is voluntary, it's not
regulatory, it's a voluntary um, action,
then that'd be fine.
>> Okay. So, annex that under that with a
conservation easement. Okay. So, they
come to you now, the ranch owner, and
say,
um, we want you to annex this, and we
want to put a, um,
feed lot on this, and we want to put a
meat processing plant on this land, and
we want you, the city, to supply us with
water. and we have a the
state-of-the-art
plant that's going to use as little
water as possible and we have a way to
handle the manure. What would you do
then?
>> The mayor, I mean, sorry, chair, members
of council, um, in that specific case,
this zoning that we have proposed right
now could allow that type of use. So, we
treat it just the same. We don't
evaluate annexations or zonings based on
proposed uses. Um but when an applicant
or a land owner does disclose what they
are proposing at that time we will
mention that but there is no guarantee.
In the um years of being in planning and
development there are many times where a
development has been proposed and that
development is not what ends up. Um it's
very common uh for developments to
change. In fact, we built a fire station
on the site of a proposed
uh trampoline park at one time.
Development plans change and that was
presented to you in front of the
governing body that was going to be a
trampoline park at one time.
>> Okay. So, you would take the position
that yes, from your position, you'd
recommend that it be annexed.
Director,
>> chair, members of the council, yes, we
would we would find it to meet the re
the review criteria.
>> Okay. Uh Mr. Chairman, again, so we're
on number five, uh or number four, I'm
sorry. Um so they come to you and say,
"We want you to annex this ranch land."
And you say, "Well, what are you going
to use it for because we need to
establish zoning?" And they tell you,
"It's none of your business."
I don't have to tell you that. This is
my private property, right? which we've
heard sort of tonight. Um so what do you
say to that? Do you annex under those
conditions?
>> Director, chair, members of the council,
we don't have the right to require that
they disclose what they're proposing the
use for. There are times in the
development process like the site plan
where we can look at a detailed um use
analysis. Those are accompanied with
traffic studies, drainage studies, um a
lot more technical studies on how it
would affect the environment. But if
it's annexation and they choose not to
disclose what they are intending to
build there, we're strictly looking at
it for we're looking at it um amongst
this review criteria for annexation.
>> Okay. So annex under that circumstance
in hypo number five. So,
number four. So, in hypothetical number
five, they come to you and they say, "We
want you to annex this property." And,
"Oh, by the way,
if you annex it, once you annex it, we
get paid a lot more money.
And so, we need you to help us
facilitate that land transaction by
approving this annexation.
Is that a discussion you ever have and
does that affect your annexation
decision?
>> Chair, chair, members of the council,
I've never had a discussion like that
regarding a developer with any type of
land development deal. The ultimate goal
is for someone to make a profit, the
person selling the land, the person
developing the land, the person
providing a service. Um, that's a given.
We're not ever put in a situation that
you had described there.
>> Okay.
And I I I applaud you for that because
that's probably not something that is
actually something through you, Mr.
Chairman, uh that you want to get
involved in. All right. Now, let's turn
to
Microsoft um and the annexation for a
data center. So, they come to you and
they say, "We want you, we want you to
annex this and we want to put a data
center on that." I assume that you'd
process that in the normal course of
annexation business.
>> Director, chair, members of council. Um,
yes, we would process that the normal
way of business. If you look at our
social media pages, discussion points,
even if we have a car wash, a bank, a
coffee shop, man, do I hear the public
say, "We have too many of those." Do I
say, "Time out. We're done. Add data
center to that list." No, we don't.
>> Okay. And and I've heard that argument
before, but this is so far from a car
wash and a liquor store. I mean, we're
talking about
hundreds of thousands of feet under roof
uh for these data centers, some of them,
uh and maybe more than one building. So,
it's not a very apt comparison, but I
gather your decision would be to annex.
So,
>> Cherry, it may may be
>> it may be appropriate to compare the
water usage from a data center to a car
wash, though.
>> That might be a fair argument.
>> That's true, but probably not the energy
use.
>> Fair.
>> Um, so hypothetical number seven, they
come to you and say, "We want you to
annex, but we're going to build on this
property for 10 years."
>> Should we should the city annex that?
director,
>> chair, members of council,
I' I've owned my the present house for
eight years.
I'm finally completing my backyard.
So, I can't set a timeline on when a
project is complete. It is a free
market. Anyone can buy a piece of land.
They can buy land. Whether it's for
strategic positioning in the industry,
whether it's because they just want to
have it now because the price is right,
because there's no cheaper time to buy
land than right now compared to
tomorrow.
I I can't prejudge a development based
on when they intend to develop it.
>> So annex go forward with the annexation.
>> Director, chair, members of council.
Yes, that's correct.
>> Thank you. Uh final one uh
on these hypotheticals. Um,
so they come to you and they say, "Okay,
we want you to annex and
we want to put a data center here and
also we may want to put our own power
plant on this site and we want you to be
you the city to be able to supply us
with
water for that."
What would you say about that
annexation?
>> Director
and chair, members of council. Um,
that's a really good question. Right
now, we have not had a development
proposal that has moved forward where
someone has said through an application
that they are installing a data center
with a power plant that is um attached
to it. Um, I do know that there's
technologies out there for power plants
that could be natural gas that do have
systems that use water and ones that are
air cooled that don't. Um, typically
those discussions occur with our board
of public utilities. Um, and I'm not
aware how those work with the inner
workings because we do have, you know,
some water concerns that do exist and
they try to be prudent with um,
promising and pledging our water um,
beyond our capacity. Um, regarding the
specific data center developments right
now, I do know that there have been some
um, discussions of alternative power
that could occur. um that hasn't been
necessarily disclosed to us or at least
not me um that there is a power
generation facility that is being uh
constructed on a data center site. Um we
are I I'll take that back. We are
working with one uh data center
developer who is looking at a u hydrogen
style facility, but we're trying to get
some more information on what that
exactly is. Um, but that's that's really
the only one that actually has something
in the in the pipeline that I'm aware
of.
>> U, thank you. Just Mr. Chairman, just
one more question. Um, if I might uh
through you. Um, Mr. Bloom, I appreciate
your uh analysis on these. Um, does does
a land owner have an absolute right to
have their land annexed?
Director,
>> chair, members of council, um, under
state statute,
the required findings pretty much say if
you you meet these, you're you satisfy
the conditions for annexation.
Ultimately, it's the um governing body
who makes that decision. We do have some
tools in place um in the planning realm
where we can look at um where we want a
city to grow, how we want that land use
to to look and those are the processes
that we're going through with the land
use plan amendment and the corresponding
change the urban growth boundary. Um in
Wyoming what's been very common when it
comes to our growth policies especially
for municipalities is to annex. There
are other communities that uh don't
annex and they stay within their
confines. Um and that can lead to
challenges as well. Look at Boulder,
Colorado for example. Um that community
has very limited growth potential
because of how it's been set up. Um how
they hand out water and the result there
is unattainable, unaffordable housing
that they're rapidly trying to address.
>> That's great. Is that is that who you're
speaking to or something? chair, member
of council, uh, Councilman Wolf, I'm
talking about Boulder, Colorado. They
started with a Danish plan back in back
in the day in the believe it was the 70s
which had some very strict growth
controls.
>> Thank you very much, Mr. Bloom. Thank
you, Mr. President. Mr. Chairman,
>> further discussion.
Further discussion. Councilman Labour.
[clears throat]
>> Thank you, Mr. President. in the uh on
the back side of this handout that just
went out uh that deals with statute
15142,
you get to subsection C
and the annexing municipality shall
prepare a proposed annexation report as
specified in this subsection.
this report shall at a minimum
contain
and it goes on in great detail of what
that report shall contain.
Uh I haven't seen any such report. Is
there one that specifically follows the
state statute here uh about what that
minimum I won't read it all but um cost
of infrastructural improvements basic
services
um
cost of infrastructure improvements
required within the existing boundaries
um have we prepared a document of this
nature Mr. Bloom. Director Bloom.
>> Mayor, members of council, that's a
great observation that was in here. Um,
we've discussed that a couple of times
with some previous annexations,
specifically the county pocket
annexations. Now, a lot of uh folks get
this confused with a financial impact
analysis and then also carrying out the
statutory requirements. What we're
required to do, and we send our
certified mail notice to people within
the annexation area, is we have a bullet
point list that follows the state
statute that says as a result of this
annexation, what you're proposing and
what you need to connect to utilities at
this time is going to cost A, B, C, and
D. And typically that is zero dollars.
And what that is in regard to is what is
the city the municipality going to
charge or to demand for infrastructure
improvements. Back in the day when we
annex Sunnyside edition which is the
area located to the east of Ridge Road
um out by College and further east out
that direction with that at the time of
annexation there's a requirement that
people were um expected to construct
roadways. So in that specific scenario,
we would have had to provide a cost
estimate for what those construction
costs would have been.
>> Maybe maybe I'm not being clear on Mr.
President completed that.
>> I asked about this annexation that's
before us right now.
>> Do we have any such report?
>> Chair, members of council, Councilman
Lelay, yes, we do have that report and
we can send that directly to you all.
>> Well, I look forward to receiving it. I
think we should have received it uh
prior to tonight because it has many
interesting aspects and I think that uh
certainly the other annexations are
[clears throat] somewhat comparable but
uh I think this statute is clear and uh
I think that it isn't sending it out to
uh those other people is for our
evaluation
to see if the four conditions of
annexation are met
>> as a point of information.
>> Um
>> Dr. Chairman Crave, as a point of
information, if you look at that um
15-1-42
letter E and the very last uh sentence
there is the estimate shall be provided
to the landowner and affected public
utility prior to the hearing, not to the
city council.
>> I see. Well, uh Mr. President, I think
what we have here is a real defect.
a real defect in our process.
>> What kind of a process do we have here
where that information is available to
perhaps the adjacent land owner but not
to the people that make the decision?
>> It's the legislature. I don't know.
>> Um I [laughter]
I don't think it's the legislature. I
think it's us.
>> And I think we should have that
information, Mr. Chairman. And I and
furthermore, let me say this in regard
to the action the vote we're going to
take here soon. There's been a lot of
dodging and diving on this thing. It's
pretty clear this is a very serious,
very major action
that's on our part that's on our
shoulders.
And I believe that this information is
very relevant. And I believe that
there's an extra effort that needs to be
made in regard to these as we proceed as
we get into a little later in this
meeting. The uh reports that we got from
the uh we're going to have to overrule
the planning commission.
There's a lot of factors here and if
they're all on the table, we make a
better decision. Thank you.
>> Further discussion.
Discussion
hearing. None. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Yes. And those opposed?
>> No.
>> Hands of the nose. Councilman Wolf,
Councilman Moody, Councilman Lebornne.
The action is approved. Next item,
please.
>> Number 15. Ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AG agricultural
for land annex to the city of Cheyenne,
located east of South Gley Highway and
south of the Sweetg Grass subdivision.
>> Okay. As uh Mayor Collins frequently
says, once we move to annex a piece of
property, we have to give it a zone. Uh
our our motion is to give it a similar
zone as to what it was in the county.
The reason for doing that is
maybe not in this case but at times the
final zone is not known and so it we
need to be able to uh operate the
property uh within the city. So this is
asking us to zone the land we just
discussed as agriculture
and Jennifer do you waving at me. What
is it?
Oh, I'm just trying to get your that we
have people online with their hands
raised.
>> Okay. Okay.
Okay. We're ready to So, that's what
we're going to discuss now is zoning
this property as agriculture.
Let's start online. Um, who's our first
person?
>> Mr. uh Don Stam, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Uh, can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Okay. Thank you for uh your time
tonight. Um I'm sorry I was trying to
get on earlier for the last discussion.
Um I'm was opposed to uh or I was for
the the holding off for the four months
to get more information. I'm sorry this
is backtracking just a little bit. Um
everybody's been talking about
disinformation.
Um and it's you know I own a house out
in Sweetgrass. Uh we bought out here
because of the country living, the lack
of sound, lack of noise, lack of massive
light systems, uh to impede on our
quality of Wyoming life. Uh which is
very important to us is why we bought
out here. People out in the development
paid more money to be on the outside
edges so they didn't have these big
places obscuring their view and
everything.
Um, and so we talk about being notified
um about these meetings that are going
on because I don't live in a 300 foot
radius of the where it's going in. Um, I
was not notified. If you're putting in a
single house that you're annexing, 300
feet is realistic. If you're putting in
a massive data center that's taking up,
you know, square mile or whatever, uh,
that
distance for the notification has to be
scaled to that envelopment because it's
going to affect you much more and if
make more effects farther on. Um, when I
sit out on my deck at night, I like to
be able to look up at the stars. Um, if
we've got this massive data center over
there with all their lights and
everything,
there goes our view. Um, that's why we
moved out of town. That's why we move
next to ranch land. Um, and so that's a
big impedment on our property rights, on
our own rights. Same thing goes with
sound. Uh, there's going to be more
noise out there. Uh, that's what we
moved out to the edges for was to get
away from the noise. Um, we moved out
here, you know, and nothing was set in
stone, but we were told, okay, there's
going to be parks out there. There's
going to be a golf course out there.
That's fine. That's that's landscape.
That's, you know, green. But to hear
that this large data center can come in
and one of the things they asked for
special treatment, which Mr. Noble said
earlier they didn't ask for any special
treatment was that the landscaping
requirements were diminished for them.
>> Sir, we're talking about agriculture
zoning here.
>> Well, you're you're talking about zoning
on it, right? But I said I'm sorry I got
in right a little bit too about five
minutes too late to be heard on the last
time. Um, and it's just that we need to
be able to have a Wyoming quality of
life. Um, and that's what I'm saying.
Uh, we don't know how this will affect
our our property values. We don't know
how this is going to affect our quality
of life which we have paid for. Um, and
and that's why, you know, we're against
rushing through this process.
um you know this information is we need
to be mo notified with everybody within
a square mile of this development
because that's what it's going to affect
people as and we just don't feel that
the everybody has made the attempt the
reasonable attempt to get the
information out there and be able to
hear other people's views.
Um, not once have I heard a single conti
constituent say, "I am for this data
center who hasn't had their hand in the
proverbial pot." Um, and I understand
that's how people make their livingings,
but this is also our quality of life.
Um, and that's, you know, we appreciate
you guys listening to this. We
appreciate your your your time and
consideration, but I think at the scale
of this, there needs to be more
information out there to people
available without having to track it
down through all the back links. Um, and
and I appreciate the time and appreciate
you guys listening to me.
>> Thank you.
Next, next person, Jennifer.
Um, before I go to the next person, I'd
like to let the record show that Mayor
Patrick Collins left the meeting at 9:18
p.m. Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead
and unmute yourself.
>> Hello, Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> hello.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you now, sir. We're
discussing zoning for agriculture
>> um for data center future use or
>> agriculture. We're zoning the property
for agriculture.
>> Oh. Oh, okay. And then uh the next is it
the next one where you're going to be
immediately reszoning it to business
park. Is that correct?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Oh, okay. Okay. But you're splitting
those two things up.
>> Yes, sir.
>> So, they kept Okay. Okay. I get it. All
right. Um excuse [clears throat] me. Uh,
sorry about that. Just one moment. Um,
uh, council members, uh, Charles Miller
for the record.
Uh, for the permanent administrative
record, um, Charles Miller, my testimony
is strictly gerine to item to agenda
item number 15, establish establishing
the agricultural zoning classification
for the 3,460
acres east of South Gley Highway. Is
that correct?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay. I'm issuing a formal constructive
notice um that approving this ordinance
is an intentional bad faith
misrepresentation of the municipal
zoning map and a fatal violation of the
Tanga doctrine. You are attempting to
launder a trillion dollar hypers scale
industrial complex through a fake
farming classification. You are
assigning AG agricultural zoning to 8
18% of this city's land mass future land
massly fully knowing the applicant
intends to build a massive data center
on it. However, we don't actually know
what they're intending to build on it
because there's no no plans. So, um
however, your your own planner Connor
White confessed this exact scheme on the
live microphone. He stated verbatim why
why staff is recommending that uh be
zoned AG to begin with when we know that
they want to build the data center. The
reason is if council annexes it zones it
and then doesn't zone atone BP it has a
city zone it has a backup zone otherwise
we're annexing another a parcel not
giving it a zone. Um
let the record reflect that the city
planner openly admits you are applying a
false classification simply to establish
a backup zone. planning director Charles
Bloom attempted to excuse this um
manipulation.
Uh actually I believe was the mayor the
Mr. Mayor had already had also said this
annexation doesn't do anything but
change the color of the map. Um
I'm sorry one moment here. Um
>> Mr. Miller. Yeah. Um, I'm sorry. One
moment. Uh, sir, you have no detailed
design. You have no baseline data. And
you
>> Your three minutes are up, sir. Thank
you.
>> Anyone else online? Jennifer.
Okay, we're going to close the online
discussion. We'll bring it into the
room. Is there anyone in the room that
would like to discuss zoning this
property as agriculture? Mr. Emmens.
>> Uh, Mr. President, council members Brad
Brett Emmens, AVI agent for the
applicant. Um, in this case, um, the
Lumus Arenham
uh, people are keeping a portion of
this. So, not all of the zone change is
going to transfer to BP. The portion
that the Lumus family is keeping is
staying AR. So, I just wanted to kind of
point out that the two of them are a
little bit different. In fact, it um
those areas that the Lumis family are
not going to transfer or proposed to
transfer are going to stay AR at this
time.
>> AG
>> AG.
>> Sorry, President T. Whatever the sign
zoning is is what they're keeping it
>> agriculture. Okay. Thank you very much.
I appreciate you clarifying that for us.
>> Anyone else else in the room that would
like to discuss this um zoning action?
Hearing none, we'll close discussion and
we'll bring it up on the dis for a
motion. Please, Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion by Dr. Aldrich, a
second by Dr. Emmens. Discussion on
zoning for agriculture
discussion
hearing none. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> Hands of the nose, please. Uh,
Councilman Moody, Councilman Labor, the
action is approved.
Uh, I've been asked uh that we take a
short break. It is uh 9:24. Why don't we
reconvene at 9:35
and we'll keep pushing ahead here. We've
got quite a bit of an agenda to go.
Thank you.
>> Oh, it feels good to stand up.
>> Hello. appreciate you. Thank you.
Okay, we're ready to reconvene.
Okay.
All right. We have everyone back. Uh
Jennifer, are you set to go?
Yes.
Jennifer, are you are you ready to go?
Okay. With that, uh let's go to the next
item, which I believe is item number 16.
>> Number 16. An ordinance second reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located east of
South Gley Highway and south of the
Sweetgrass subdivision from AG
agricultural and PUD planned unit
development to BP business park.
>> Okay. So, what we're doing here is we're
still talking about the same 3,500
acres. A portion of that, roughly
[clears throat] 3,000 acres is being
requested to be um considered as a
business park. As Mr. Mr. Rman said
earlier, the remainder um will stay
agriculture.
So that's what we're going to discuss
now. Uh we'll open it up to public
comment and we'll start online.
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can unmute yourself.
>> Hear me?
>> Mr. Miller?
>> Yes. Can you hear me?
>> We can go ahead.
>> Okay. Um, for the permanent
administrative record, Charles Miller,
my testimony is strictly gerine to
agenda item number 16, the ordinance
reszoning this land to business park. I
am issuing a formal constructive notice
that approving this resoning is an act
of premeditated regulatory arbitrage and
a fatal violation of the Tonganga
doctrine. You are attempting to justify
this massive reasonzoning by claiming it
is for a Microsoft campus. But maybe
it's a data center, maybe it's not. We
don't know because there is no plan.
This is a Schroingers data center.
You're being asked to vote on a
corporate hallucination. Microsoft's own
agent, Rachel Irwing, explicitly
confessed on the record, "Given the
early stage of this effort, Microsoft
has not yet advanced detailed design for
the for the campus." Jonathan Noble
admitted, "We do not have a campus of
this size to pull from because you have
no plan. You have no evidence. Under the
Tanga Doctrine, a zoning board cannot
bridge the analytical gap with a blank
check." As resident Heather Madrid
warned, without having a plan, it is
impossible to prove that this annexation
is protecting the health, safety, and
welfare of the community. So why are you
rushing to assign a permanent industrial
entitlement to a ghost project? The true
motive is documented on your own
microphones. Councilwoman Emmens
confessed that by applying this business
park zoning, the industrial sighting act
going through the whole council process
is waved. Councilman Wolf defended the
statutory evasion, stating verbatim,
"The legislature created this scheme."
So this is a legislative action over
which we have no authority to disagree
with. You are actively jerry
gerrymandering the municipal map to
execute a legislative scheme that
deprivives Laramie County of
statemandated socioeconomic impact fees.
You're allowing developers to manipulate
the map by stringing properties together
no matter how many different properties
they own as confessed by AVI's Mark
Christensen. Furthermore, you are doing
this based on a temporal fraud.
Councilman Lelayourne exposed the
developer timeline, stating verbatim,
"icrosoft has consistently told us that
this project is 10 to 20 years in the
future. That has been your entire
testimony. You are rushing an emergency
zoning waiver for a project two decades
away while simultaneously ignoring the
fact the developer um
I'm sorry that the developer is already
out there drilling wells on the site
before this council has even voted. This
tribunal is a predetermined sham. The
evidence is void. The scheme is
confessed. As requested by the public,
please do not trade our community's
long-term public voice for corporate
handouts with zero guarantees. I demand
a no vote.
>> Thank you. Anyone else? Jennifer
>> Maj, you can go ahead and unmute
yourself.
>> N Chadek, I'm a county person, not a
city person, but I've been both. I'm a
polymath and I look at things through a
lot of different lenses and this
annexation for me has so many questions
especially because the property owner is
a politician which means they deal with
lobbyists and things that happen that
we're not privy to. It was already
stated earlier this evening that the
property
had somebody come to them about it,
which means that's like poaching, right?
And within all of this, it's interesting
that they want to keep their own little
parcel agricultural while selling out
everything surrounding it in a way that
the community is obviously
[clears throat] against. So, in my
opinion, this is very corrupt. Um, and
you have to look at it from a lot of
different angles, and I'm not re relying
on our local news to report on things
like this. I'm going to places like
dataenters.com,
which gives a lot of up-to-date data
center information. And one of the key
things in an article that was printed
June 16th of this year dealing with the
expansion of data centers and Microsoft
here in Cheyenne.
Land is becoming a strategic asset
and that emerging markets are attracting
greater attention. Infrastructure
development is becoming more
geographically diverse. Campus scale
planning is replacing smaller deployment
models. We don't want it. It's growth.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. Another one.
>> Bailey Evans, you can go ahead.
>> Good evening, everyone. Thank you for
>> Hello.
Hello.
Miss Was it Evans? Miss Evans.
Miss Evans.
>> J.
>> I I I show that she's unmuted. I do have
another person. So, if we want to maybe
go to them and then we can come back.
>> Okay. If she's still there, we'll come
back.
>> Okay. So, uh, Steven Low, you can go
ahead.
Sorry. Love. Steven Love.
>> Mr. Love.
>> Hi, my name is Steven Love, Ward One.
Can you hear me? Okay.
>> Yes, we can. Go ahead.
>> Uh, I'm a longtime listener, first time
caller. Um, I'd just like to remind
everyone that the way Wyoming was
founded was with strong property rights,
and that continues to define us as a
people.
Let these people do what they want with
their land. If you're worried about data
centers, call for the lowering of the
noise ordinance or impose water taxes on
data centers, but don't tell people what
they can and can't do with their land.
Wyoming is losing a youth at a
staggering rate, and it's because of a
stagnant economy. We have to permit
industry to improve our economy. Support
homeowner initiated annexation. Oppose
forced annexation. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Love.
Jennifer, do we have Miss Evans back?
>> Nope. It looks like she dropped off.
>> All right. Anyone else?
All right, we'll close the uh online.
Anyone in the room that would like to
discuss this
um zoning
ordinance?
Mr. Emmens.
Uh, President, council members, Brad
Evans, AVI agent for the applicant and
just wanted to follow up a little bit
more to um, state that the existing
developer, they kept the diagonal AG
area so they can save continue to save
the ridge. They are still developing the
sweet grass subdivision and they have
located this area in an area where they
think it will not affect their
development. they would not have sold
land if they thought it would or
proposed to sell land to an area. So to
say that they're not paying attention to
that is is not true. They've they've
saved the AG area and they've located
this in an area that they feel would not
uh have uh bad intentions on their
residential development. Um, the other
thing I wanted to say about the uh
annexation and zone changes, we did also
have a adjacent neighbor meeting and we
invited everybody in the Grass Hill
subdivision which is to the southeast of
this. Uh, it's a county subdivision that
is actually has the closest houses uh to
this property. Um, we had that the end
of
May. Um, and um, we did have three of
the neighbors come to that meeting. Uh,
we answered probably 15 20 of their
questions. uh most of their stuff was
about a noise u and we talked about how
we were going to mitigate that. So just
wanted to let uh this council know we
did have a neighborhood meeting for
adjacent in the grass hill subdivision.
So um happy to answer any questions the
council has.
>> Thank you sir. Appreciate it.
>> Yes ma'am.
>> Please turn that on until it you see the
green light and then speak right into it
so everyone can hear.
>> Hello. My name is Amanda Augusta. I live
in Cheyenne and I work for Microsoft
overseeing all physical security
operations in Cheyenne. I am a member of
the community and I understand not
everyone sees data center growth the
same way, but I'd like to share what
I've personally witnessed over the past
four and a half years since I've been
here. When we talk about data centers,
it's easy to picture buildings and
servers. What I see every day are people
in our buildings.
Just last week alone, we had 516 vendors
visit all of our campuses to support
ongoing operations and maintenance.
Today, Microsoft employs 267 full-time
employees alongside approximately 245
dedicated support staff specifically
that are security and critical
environments across our three campuses.
That's over a thousand people per week
that are showing up to our data centers.
And this doesn't include the people who
work to help our data centers but don't
need to physically show up but live in
Cheyenne.
These are good paying careers with
opportunities for growth. I've
personally witnessed vendors gain
experience and build skills to move into
Microsoft roles. Others have started
with Microsoft with no technical
experience or skills and have progressed
to managers within a few years. I've
also had the opportunity to participate
in programs such as Empower Her and the
Trades Exploration Day at Archer. The
enthusiasm from students and even
teachers is remarkable. They want to
know what the careers are and what's
available to them and how they can be a
part of the future. As the Cowboy State
Daily stated yesterday in the news,
Wyoming loses roughly 70% of its
residents by the time they reach 30.
This can be an amazing way to keep youth
in Cheyenne. Whether it's working for
Microsoft or being a part of the trades
that help run our data centers every
day.
The reality is data centers power much
of our modern-day life from businesses,
schools, healthcare systems, public
services, and the technology we use
every day. The infrastructure located
here in Cheyenne plays a key role to
keeping those systems running. As our
community considers future growth, I
encourage us to look beyond the
buildings themselves and consider the
opportunities they create, jobs,
technical education, partnerships with
local schools, and long-term investment
in Cheyenne. I'm proud to I'm proud of
the work we do. I'm proud of the people
that make this happen every day. And I'm
proud that Cheyenne continues to be a
place where innovation and opportunity
to can grow. And I'm proud to be a
member of this community. So, thank you.
>> Thank you very much.
Yes, sir.
And please, there you go. Okay. If you
can speak right into that microphone for
us.
>> Yes. Good evening. My name is Kevin
Banish. I've lived in the Cheyenne area
since 2004 and a lifelong Wyoming
resident and have worked at Microsoft
Cheyenne data center since 2013. I'm
here tonight in support of adding this
land for future data center development.
Uh when I was young and interested in
technology, I didn't think there would
be a career for me in Wyoming. Today,
there's hundreds of people building
technology careers right here in
Cheyenne. Over the last 13 years, I've
watched Microsoft's presence in our
community grow from a few facilities
into a major contributor to our local
economy. I've seen local contractors and
many other businesses benefit from data
center development. These facilities are
not just buildings. They represent
long-term investment in our community,
creating both construction and permanent
jobs throughout the local economy.
Microsoft reports that it is now the
number one taxpayer in the city of
Cheyenne and the number two taxpayer in
Larmy County, contributing significant
property tax revenue that helps support
local services and infrastructure.
Today's students in Wyoming can look at
careers in technology, engineering,
construction, operations, networking,
and skilled trades and know those
careers exist right here at home. They
no longer have to assume that
opportunity only exists somewhere else.
Data centers are also critical
infrastructure for a modern economy. The
cloud services, communication systems,
healthcare technologies, and business
services that people rely on every day
all depend on facilities like the ones
we have here. Shine has become a
recognized leader in this industry.
Approving this land addition would
continue that momentum and position our
community for future investment, future
jobs, and future opportunities. As a
lifetime Wyoming resident and as someone
who's worked in this industry locally
since 2013, I believe this is a positive
step in Cheyenne's future. Thank you for
your time.
Thank you very much. Yes, sir. Welcome.
>> Good evening, city council members and
all the supporters of Cheyenne. My name
is Brian Church. I'm the Metro
[clears throat] Build program manager
for Microsoft data centers in Cheyenne
here. In 1987,
I came to Cheyenne as an Air Force
airman. Had no idea where I'd be 39
years later.
Then I met and married my wife in
Cheyenne. Our three children were born
in Cheyenne.
When I retired out of California in
2006,
we came back to Cheyenne.
[snorts] We bought, sold homes, been
active in our church, played sports,
purchased groceries, and all of our
vehicles right here in Cheyenne. Our
children took classes in LC.
One served in the Navy, came back,
bought a house in Cheyenne, now works at
the Microsoft data center. Another works
in town in Cheyenne, bought his house in
Cheyenne, and he serves the Wyoming Air
Guard. Yet another went to Eastern
Wyoming College and now works at the
Microsoft Data Center. What does all
this mean? [snorts] Over the years,
since I was an airman, I heard many
times that Wyoming wants the veterans to
stay here. They want them to raise
families here. They want them to stake
their roots here, spend their money
here. And we did that. A huge factor in
deciding where to live for veterans is
employment. We have defense positions
here. others defense jobs, but if you
want to do something different and get a
little bit of good pay, for years,
Cheyenne did not compete
until Microsoft changed that. In 2013, I
was recruited at the Microsoft data
center and hired as the first hourly
critical environment employee, and I
have since held many positions out at
Microsoft data center. I never thought
I'd have the income I do now, and my
wife spends it really, really well here
in Cheyenne.
Actually, both of us do. Um, but anyway,
a key for veterans is transferable
skills. Veterans have them. Microsoft
wants them. If there's a veteran out
there that wants to know about a good
career with Microsoft to stay here, look
me up. Thank you Cheyenne City Council
for your time and thank you veterans for
your service.
>> Thank you, Mr. Church.
Welcome, sir.
>> Good. Good evening, everyone. My
[clears throat] name is Casey Mullikin.
I'm a resident of Cheyenne. I have lived
here my whole life. I am a graduate of
Cheyenne East High School and joined the
Wyoming joint apprentichip training
program for electricians after high
school. I am a master electrician by
trade and a current contracted employee
for Microsoft. I would like to discuss
how Microsoft has provided stability in
my life for my family and I. I worked
for a local shop here in Cheyenne for
many years as a journeyman electrician.
And during [snorts] that stent, it had
its ups and downs. Some years were busy
with work and other years were slower. I
chose to leave the local shop I was at
and go work as electrical foreman on one
of the data data centers being built.
This was one of the best decisions I
made. Not only was I home every night
with my family, but I also made more
money to provide for them as well. Being
a single father and living off one
income can be stressful and these data
centers provided higher wages and
stability for years at a time. I took my
experience as an electrical foreman and
applied for Microsoft position. I
started working for Microsoft last
January and my life has changed even
more. The work life balance for
Microsoft is amazing. Not only do I have
a lucrative career, but I also have more
more time with my family. This change
has come because of Microsoft bringing
the data centers here to Cheyenne,
allowing trades to grow and hiring
knowledgeable people to expand their
careers even more as full-time Microsoft
employees. Cheyenne needs more companies
like Microsoft here. The culture that
Microsoft brings as well as the
stability is second to none and I am
very thankful to be a part of this.
These data centers will provide
thousands of jobs for the trades and
hundreds of full-time Microsoft jobs
after they are built. I strongly believe
in Microsoft in the future it brings.
Thank you for your time.
>> Thank you, Casey. Yes, sir. Welcome.
>> Good morning. Good evening. [laughter]
>> It might be morning.
I am a lifetime Wyoming resident and for
the last eight years I have lived in
Cheyenne. I started my career in the oil
and gas industry. Unfortunately, most of
my oil and gas industry was spent in
other states. With the downturns and
upturns, I chased the work.
Coming back to Cheyenne after we had our
daughter, Microsoft has given me the
opportunity to be home more, raise my
family, and some of the points that come
with that is I now get to get my kids
off the bus. I get to take my wife to
dinner on Friday evening and not tell
her that I will be working this weekend.
uh [clears throat] I get the opportunity
to use my mind instead of my hands and
my body which I believe is something
that is very rare in my generation.
Another thing that is also noticed being
on the construction side of Microsoft is
the safety.
Everywhere preaches safety. Microsoft
practices safety. I've never been told
to do anything unsafe. And anytime I
mentioned something unsafe, I was told
that I could do exactly what it was done
to make myself safe.
Right now, fun fact, Bison campus has
2.3 million man hours worked with no
reportable incidents.
I challenge any other industry to
complete compete with that. It is
unheard of to work that many hours and
not have one guy go home because he hurt
his hand, smash his feet, everyone goes
home to their families the way they went
to work that day. And that's an
impressive thing for me.
In closing, I believe that the data
centers are a positive addition to our
community, adding jobs for local people
directly and indirectly.
And if they are willing to learn and
train for the jobs that Microsoft has
the positions available for them,
the culture that microsoft brings to
Wyoming
to Cheyenne matches that of Wyoming's.
They are respectful. They don't ask you
to do anything they wouldn't do
themselves. And that is why I believe we
should continue forward with this.
>> Thank you. Thank you very much. Further
uh comments in the room? Anyone else?
We're talking about zoning here for a
business park.
All right, we'll close the uh discussion
and we'll bring it up on the dis and
I'll ask for a motion, please.
[snorts]
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Dr. Aldridge, second by Dr.
Rimmons. Discussion
discussion
hearing none. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
>> Hands on the nose, please. Uh,
Councilman Wolf, Moody, and Lebornne.
The motion is approved. Next item,
please.
>> Number number 17, ordinance, second
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne.
Classification for land located between
I80 and College Drive east of Southwest
Drive from MUB mixeduse business
emphasis to LI Light Industrial.
This was a proposed zoning change which
I understand has been uh withdrawn, but
I will open it for discussion so we can
get a motion up here. Anyone want to
talk about this?
Anyone online? We do have someone
online.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller.
Hello, Mr. Miller. [snorts]
Mr. [clears throat] Miller.
Mr. Miller.
>> Yes. Can you hear me,
>> Mr. Miller? I I just want to make sure
you know this has been withdrawn.
>> Okay. Um, I will go ahead and yield my
time.
>> All right. Thank you. All right. We'll
close the uh public discussion. Dr.
Aldrich.
>> Mr. President, the motion to approve on
second reading died due to lack of a
second.
>> There is no motion. Um,
let's see.
Do I have to take a vote on a
>> something? There's no There's no second.
There's no
>> Nobody makes a second.
>> No discussion. Anyone want to discuss
it? There's no second.
>> All right. I believe we're done with
this item.
>> I think I [snorts] did that right. This
is a little unusual. Uh, number 18.
Ordinance second reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
I80 east of College Drive from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park.
>> This is a uh separate um roughly, I
believe, 400 acre parcel
um that is asking to be reszoned to a
business park. We'll open it up to
discussion online.
Um Jennifer, anyone?
Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Uh, yes. Can you hear me?
>> We can go ahead.
>> Yeah.
>> All righty. Here. So, this is um uh item
number 18. It's a future land use map
amendment. Is that correct?
>> It's a zoning map, a zoning change.
>> Uh, okay. Hold on. Let's see here.
>> From AG to BP.
Okay,
>> just give me one moment here. Sorry,
>> your clock is running. Mr. Miller,
>> I apologize. Uh, just give me one moment
here.
I'm sorry, I'm having some technical
difficulties here. I'll have to yield my
time. Thank you.
>> All right. Anyone else online? Jennifer,
we'll close the online portion and we'll
open up to uh comments within the room.
Mr. Emmens, welcome again. Thank you,
Council President. Brad MNZ, AVI agent
uh for the owner. Uh on this one, it's
Reed Land Company. Uh before you is a
zone change from AG to BP. Um just
wanted to point out a couple things um
about this project. Uh it was originally
zoned AG as it was a holding zone uh to
uh get the sweetgrass original
Sweetgrass area annexed. the Reed family
agreed to annex this parcel and so they
did give it a holding zone of AG um with
the intent to uh reszone it in the
future when they had a development
project. Um this is a again being
considered for a a Microsoft data center
and so uh the BP zone is being
requested. Um the there is the future
land use map that goes along with this
does have mixeduse employment as a
portion of this area and therefore it's
really just expanding that mixeduse
employment area to a greater area within
the the acreage. Um um this parcel has
been looked at by uh residential
developers in the past. Um and both
times has not gone forward because of uh
high groundwater
um in the area and actually being too
flat, which is very unusual to find a
piece of property that's too flat. Um it
makes it harder to uh have storm water
pipes uh uh basements for the biggest
thing for residential for the high water
line. So both residential developers uh
were not interested if they couldn't put
basements under the homes. Um so happy
to answer any questions of the council.
>> Any questions for the uh owner's rep?
Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh President Crave, I just wanted to u
ask Mr. Emmens. I believe the testimony
we heard during committee was that the
this family has been trying to sell this
piece of property for 30 over 30 years.
Is that correct,
>> Mr. Mr. Council President, that is what
the owner did and the owner is here,
too, in case there's some questions if
the council has.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. All right. Thank you, Mr.
Rimmonson.
>> Yes, ma'am. Welcome back.
>> Thank you. Uh good evening, council
members. My name is Rachel Irwing, uh
land development manager for Microsoft
for the record. Uh thank you again for
your continued time and in consideration
on the Reed property. Uh, similar to
Highlands, the actions before you
tonight, the resoning to business park
and the future land use amendment is one
step within a broader ongoing planning
and entitlement process. It is not the
final approval for development. Unlike
Highlands, this property is already
within city limits. Uh, that means the
process moving forward will occur within
established review frameworks for the
city uh with additional oversight as
more detailed design work progresses. As
we've shared, we are still early in the
process. Our focus has been on being
transparent about what we know today
while continuing to engage with city
staff and the community as additional
details are developed. That approach
will continue and future phases will
include more detailed technical review
and refinement of the project. Our goal
is to work in partnership with the city
to ensure development occurs in a
coordinated and responsible way. We
appreciate your consideration and our
team is happy to answer any questions.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, sir. Welcome back.
Good to be back. Um, good evening, Mr.
President and members of the council.
Um, Lucas Downey here and I serve as
community affairs manager with Microsoft
and I appreciate the opportunity to
speak to you all again tonight. I want
to briefly restate our community first
commitments because we believe it is
important to be transparent and to hold
ourselves accountable to them. We pay
our way so our operations do not
increase electricity costs for the
residents. We work to minimize our water
use and replenish more than we use. We
create jobs for local residents. We
contribute to the local tax base. And we
invest in the community through
workforce development, AI training, and
support for local nonprofits.
These commitments are the standard we
hold ourselves to in Cheyenne. And we
believe it is important to put them
clearly on the record. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Yes, sir. Welcome.
Uh, good evening, Mr. President and
council members. I'm gonna have to read
from this because I'm getting old and
now I can't remember what I have to say.
Closer to me, or I can use teacher
voice. Your choice. All right. Uh, my
name is Troy Aik. I am a 20-year
resident of Cheyenne. Moved here in 2006
with my family. Uh, a resident of W 3.
I'm also the director of the IT pathway
at LC. Um in my role I work with
Microsoft and its employees closely. Um
I am here though to speak on my own cogn
cognizance and not that of LC the
school. Uh so I want to make that clear.
Um I cannot speak in support or
opposition of the development within my
role of LC. What I would like to speak
though is my experience as an
instructor, mentor and industry
professional. Microsoft and its Cheyenne
data centers have had an enormous
positive impact for our residents and
our students in what they've developed
for us and what they've assisted with us
in creating learning environments that
truly change lives. When meeting
potential new students, the number one
question I get is, "What do I have to do
to work at Microsoft?"
That should say a lot in and of itself.
Even with other global players in our
market either currently or coming I
don't get how do I work for Meta how do
I work for Google how do I work for a
AWS I get how do I work from Microsoft
the people know that these are great
jobs that this is a lot of opportunity
for them and these are not people who
are begging to get out of Cheyenne they
want to stay here they want to live here
and these aren't all 18-year-old
students the majority of my students are
career changers
They are trying to change their lives
and this gives them that opportunity.
Since 2018, Microsoft has donated nearly
half a million dollars to my program.
When I started with LC in January 2019,
I was told, "Fix it or kill it." It had
32 students.
Now we have over 300.
They have provided over $100,000 in
direct training equipment. They have
provided over a4 million in
scholarships,
money to pay people to change their
lives.
They've paid for $50,000 to build a new
telecom lab. They paid $50,000 to
enhance our cyber security training.
Hundreds of students over the last eight
years can trace their career starts to
scholarships, training equipment, or lab
environments sponsored by Microsoft.
These are career changers and
traditional students seeking better
long-term jobs. I'm going to skip
forward here because my time Cheyenne
has an opportunity to build a future for
our current workforce beyond low wage,
low skill roles and to lay the
foundations for our children's futures
to be better than ours. We have a
responsibility to do so.
>> I had a question. Mr. President,
>> Councilman Escoil has a question for
you, sir. Do you have any 65-year-old
retired railroad engineers in there?
[laughter]
>> I would be happy to to tour you around.
And yes, we have people of all ages that
that pursue degrees with us.
>> Hey,
thank you for being here. Appreciate it.
>> Welcome, sir. Please turn on the
microphone for us and identify yourself.
>> My name is Dan Reid. I'm spokesperson
for the uh Reed family. Um, the
[clears throat] property in question
here has been in the Reed family for
three generations now, ownership of
which was transferred to my generation a
few years after the untimely death of my
father in an aviation accident.
While portions of the property are
designated for residential use in the
comprehensive pro plan, after decades of
marketing this property, the Reed family
has learned that the property is not
feasible for residential development.
Multiple developers have determined that
topography and other characteristics
make residential development
impractical.
Dating back to the 1990s, residential
developers have inquired about the
property, but ultimately never been able
to determine residential development is
feasible. We were told by local real
estate agents that annexation in 2016
would open the door to residential
development, but that still didn't help.
In the early 2020s, the property was
under contract two times with different
residential developers. both of [snorts]
whom eventually backed out of the
contracts during due diligence for the
reasons that Mr. Emmens described.
All contacts and interest in recent
history have been uh industrial in
nature, wanting to develop the property
as an industrial uh uh development. Uh
we now understand that high upfront
costs due to uh topography
uh make the land unsuitable for
residential development. Over a period
of nearly five decades now the Reed
family has made a solid goodfaith effort
if feudal uh to sell the property for
residential development. Let me also
interject that um uh portions of this
family group uh developed a section of
property east of Cheyenne known as Bison
Run which are residential ranchets. Uh
this group also uh provided the property
uh to the developers and worked with the
city of Cheyenne to develop uh what is
now the Nioera Industrial Park. Uh so we
have some expertise in this area. The
simple fact is that no matter how much
the city needs housing, this property is
proven unfeasible
uh for residential development.
Finally, let me observe that among
the negotiations
for the sale of part or all of the Reed
family land, those with the Microsoft
people have been the most professional,
the least adversarial, and in most
regards the easiest of all, suggesting
to me that they will be conscientious
and civily committed members of the
Cheyenne business community.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Reid.
Further discussion uh in the room?
Further discussion?
Seeing none, we'll close public comment
and we'll bring it up here and ask for a
motion.
>> Uh Mr. President, the recommendation of
the public services committee is to
approve on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Second by Councilman Wolf. Discussion.
discussion.
Seeing none, all in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> Mr. Moody is a no.
This motion is approved. Next item,
please. Number 19, ordinance author uh
sorry, resolution authorizing submission
of an application to the Wyoming State
Loan and Investment [clears throat]
Board for a loan from the Wyoming
Drinking Water State Revolving Fund for
an amount not to exceed $20 million for
the lead service line investigation and
replacement project and authorizing the
mayor, city clerk, and director of the
board of public utilities to execute the
application and all related documents.
Uh several years ago, I believe it was
in Flint, Michigan, um there were some
lead pipe issues which uh
caused the federal government to mandate
that federal or correction that lead
lines be removed throughout the country.
Uh this is a grant request to the state
Wyoming state loan and investment board
for $20 million to begin that process.
We'll open it up to the um
online audience. Do we have anyone?
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> me.
>> Hello. Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you, sir.
>> All right. Um, for the permanent
administrative record, Charles Miller, I
am issuing a formal constructive notice
of gross fiduciary negligence and public
gaslighting, specifically addressing the
fiscal statements made by Councilwoman
Aldrich and Councilwoman Emmens
regarding the lead pipe crisis. Uh, Dr.
Aldrich, you have attempted to equate
the pedestrian safety and aesthetic
development of the multi-million dollar
Reed Avenue corridor with the toxic lead
pipe crisis poisoning the city's
drinking water. When I audited your
$77.3 million in hidden reserves, you
scoffed. You stated verbatim on the
public record. First and foremost, we
use reserves for large projects. We are
waiting for some regulations at the
federal level. We're looking at some
grant monies that are available to help
with that toxic service line. I'm not
sure how we're going to make Mr. Miller
happy. You make the taxpayers happy by
not prioritizing pedestrian walkways
over neurotoxins. You willingly extract
millions from reserves to fund the
primary pedestrian entrance off of the
Reed rail corridor. But when it comes to
toxic lead in the water of workingclass
homes, you suddenly close the checkbook
and tell us to wait for federal
handouts. Dr. Mr. Emmens, you and this
administration have actively attempted
to minimize the scale of this threat,
acting as if the lead simply isn't
there. This governing body stated
verbatim on the record, "I don't believe
we've truly establish the size of that
issue or the cost of that issue." The
cost is established. Your own board of
public utilities engineer, Bryce Biller,
testified to your own finance committee
that you face upwards around 100 million
to complete this overall project to
remove the lead lines. You cannot claim
the lead isn't there while Boo begs for
a $20 million state loan to dig it out
of the ground. By deploying our
municipal wealth to fund Reed Avenue
sizzle reels and rail cars while
simultaneously demanding taxpayers go
into debt to clean their own water, you
are acting with deliberate indifference
to public health. Socializing toxic debt
to fund aesthetic pet projects is a
breach of your fiduciary duty. I demand
you reappropriate those reserves to the
water system immediately. Thank you.
Further discussion online.
Okay, we'll close that. We'll open it up
to the audience here. Mr. Strong, did
you want to say something?
>> Be careful. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Uh, unfortunately, Bryce Door
could not be here today, so you guys are
stuck with me. Just to clarify, uh,
Councilman through you, it is a, uh, $20
million loan with hopefully will qualify
for 25% principal forgiveness.
>> Thank you.
Thank you. Further uh comments. We'll
bring it up here in a minute. Mr.
Labbourne. Further comments uh from the
audience.
Comments. Okay. We'll close public
comment and bring it up on the dis.
Let's get a motion from Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Second by Councilman White. Discussion.
Mr. Lebornne.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh Mr. Strong. So
if this grant is approved, um
what identification has happened thus
far and remediation, is this going to
really uh [snorts] do more to identify
and begin dealing with the problem or
how do you expect to uh uh phase it over
time,
Mr. Stro?
>> Yes, through you, sir. Um, so this will
really kick off our investigation
process where we'll actually have to
pothole every uh curb stop that we
suspect could be lead to confirm the
material on both sides so that we can
develop a capital improvement project to
replace all the lead services here in
Cheyenne.
>> Thank you.
>> Further discussion,
>> Mr. Mayor, I miss Mr. C. Grave.
>> Yes, sir. Council Lor.
>> Well, there's been a lot of discussion
about this and there was some earlier
here tonight, but of course the
magnitude of the problem is
pretty
vast and not totally identified. So, I
just want to make the point that this is
a an excellent grant application so that
we can begin to really understand and
begin to deal with the problem. And so
it really shows that the Board of Public
Utilities and the City of Cheyenne is
not hiding from this or passing the
buck. We've got uh quite a bit of time
here ahead of us to take care of it and
so I speak very much in favor of this
grant application. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Council Leborn. Further
discussion?
Further discussion? Seeing none, all in
favor signify by saying I.
>> I. Those opposed. The recommendation is
to approve. Next item, please.
>> Next item is number 21 on page four.
Resolution authorizing the acceptance of
a donation from Tallgrass ILS Holdings
LLC for affordable housing purposes and
authorizing the mayor to execute a
donation agreement. Uh this is a uh $2.9
million donation from Tallgrass ILS
Holdings LLC
uh to be used for affordable housing. Um
this is similar to the uh prior uh grant
that we' received from related
companies. Uh this is going to allow us
to more than double um the original
amount of u income based housing. Uh,
let's open this up to the public. Uh, is
there anyone online that would like to
discuss this? Jennifer. Okay,
>> Mr. Miller can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Okay. Sorry, I'm just trying to find my
notes on this one. Okay. Um,
here we go.
Um, for the permanent administrative
record, Charles Miller, my testimony is
strictly gerine to the resolution
authorizing the acceptance of a $2.9
million donation from Tall Grass ILS
Holdings for affordable housing. I am
placing a formal constructive notice of
egregious municipal hypocrisy and
systemic conflict of interest onto the
record. The administration is framing
this $2.9 million check as an act of
corporate philanthropy. It is not. It is
corporate camouflage. You are accepting
a multi-million dollar bailout from an
energy conglomerate to cover up your own
administrative failures. As Councilman
Caggrave published in his official city
update this week, you were forced to
accept this money because the state loan
and investment board denied Cheyenne's
request earlier this year.
because you uh failed to secure standard
state housing grants, you are relying on
charity from a corporation executing a
massive infrastructure footprint in our
c county.
Councilman Leborn verified Tall Grass's
true motive on the record, stating
verbatim, "Grass energy is coming off
that Cheyenne hub with massive power to
one of the largest power plants,
certainly bigger than anything in the
region." Resident Heather Madrid saw
right through this charade. She formerly
warned this council on the permanent
transcript. Is this why Tall Grass wants
to donate 2.9 million to housing? Yes,
it is. But the ultimate betrayal is that
this donation is a band-aid on a bullet
wound you inflicted. As I have formally
entered into the record, it is the
height of a municipal hypocrisy to pass
a hat around for affordable housing
donations while this exact same council
is preparing to eradicate hundreds of
acres of master planned residential
land. Tonight, your own planner Connor
White confessed that your data center
resonings will remove areas from
anticipated residential development at
the time when the city needs residential
development. You intentionally destroy
the city's residential master plan to
accommodate tech monopolies. You failed
to secure state funding and then you beg
a massive energy corporation for a $2.9
million bailout just to build 440 units.
This is not city planning. This is the
definition of a corporate oligarchy. I
demand you reject this compromised
capital. Thank you,
>> Jennifer. Anyone else?
>> Mr. Lee Filer, you can unmute yourself.
>> Welcome, Representative.
>> Thanks there, Mr. President and City
Council. Can you guys hear me? Okay,
>> we can, sir.
>> Okay. Yes. On on this uh you know, Mr.
President through you and council
members, I just want to express my
support of this. Tall Grass being one of
those people in our community or one of
those companies in our community that
actually wants to actually help our
community sees the needs that we have.
We've seen this from Related Digital and
now we're seeing this from Tall Grass
because they both have seen an absolute
need for housing within our community.
And as regulate regulators and elected
officials, these are the types of
partnerships I think we all need to look
at. And when you have companies that are
willing to do this, I just think this is
a wonderful idea and I'm in support of
this. Thanks, Mr. President.
>> Thank you so much. We appreciate you
being here. Jennifer
>> Jennifer
>> Casey and Abby Palma, would you like to
speak?
Um, sure. I just I just wanted to speak
up this evening, um, Mr. President,
because I I actually was responding to
to Mr. Miller's comments.
Uh, it's I think I think this is a great
um offer by Tall Grass, you know, to
support uh what what needs to happen in
this community um somewhat based on the
the development that's happening. But in
large part, I I sort of wanted to send a
message to Mr. Miller that, you know, if
he if he logs in every time to dispute
things as if it's a game, you know,
there's real business going on here and
if there's things that he feels strongly
about, um, I I think we all really
appreciate his comments and sometimes he
has some really good things to say, but
uh, if he's weighing in on everything
just to be a disruptor and and just to
make a point, uh, it's it's really not
constructive to the process and and
nobody really wants to hear what he has
to today. So, um I apologize for him
meaning just to send that message, but I
I I think uh he he could be well advised
to to sort of weigh in when it it's very
important to him and when it means
something to him as a constituent as
opposed to just being disruptive to the
process. So, um that that's all I have
to say tonight. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much, Jennifer. Anyone
else online? All right, we'll close the
online comments. We'll bring it back in
house. Anyone here that would like to
talk about this item, the donation from
tall grass? Anyone?
Okay, we'll close public comment and uh
we'll take a motion, please.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Councilman Esabel, second by
Councilman White. Discussion on the DAS.
>> Uh Councilman Esel.
>> Uh just to
address the last person's comments. Uh,
one of the things they told us in the
legislature is don't speak on every item
because after the while people quit
hearing you, best way, if I wanted to
make a demand, it would be for Mr.
Miller to come down here and see us in
person. Come up to the microphone in
person like these other hundreds of
people do every other week.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldrich.
No.
>> Okay. Any other any other comments on
this item? Discussion. Discussion.
Hearing none. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
>> No.
>> Councilman Moody is a no. Recommendation
is to approve. Next item, please.
>> Number 23. A resolution overruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
plan Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from agricultural, rural,
and urban residential to mixeduse
employment and amending the urban
service boundary for property generally
located east of South Gley Highway and
south of the Sweetgrass subdivision.
>> This is a um resolution to overrule the
planning commission. Um we'll open it up
for public comment, but I understand we
are going to try to postpone it. uh
shortly. So just I just wanted you to
understand that upfront. Um anyone
online that would like to discuss this?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Um can you hear me?
>> We can sir.
>> Yeah. Uh I was just thinking uh you said
that hundreds somebody said hundreds of
people come there. There's been times
where I'm at a meeting and and there's
nobody there at all. Uh but anyhow uh
for the permanent administrative record,
Charles Miller,
uh my testimony is strictly gerine to
agendum item number 23, the resolution
overruling the planning commission's
disapproval of the future land use map
amendment.
I am placing a formal constructive
notice on the record that adopting this
resolution is an indefensible violation
of the Tanga Doctrine and the Wyoming
Administrative Procedure Act.
You are [snorts] formally overruling the
planning experts of this county to
codify an act of corporate supremacy.
Your own planners refused to rubber
stamp this expansion. As city planner
Connor White confirmed on the record,
the planning commission didn't have the
yes votes. It basically came to the
recommendation of denial or failed to
approve. Why did it fail? because your
own staff documented that this map
amendment would remove areas from
anticipated residential development at
the time when the city needs residential
development. Those were in your
documents. Uh you are systematically
erasing our residential future to build
an industrial business park and you are
doing it using a broken outdated
framework. As resident Michael White
correctly warned this council, the last
time uh red they redid this plan was in
2012. That's 14 years that we have not
redone that plan Cheyenne. So in my
regards, how can we assess what we are
talking about tonight without redoing
all the rules? He said, "Under
established juristp prudence, you cannot
bridge the analytical gap to overrule an
expert denial unless you present new
substantial engineering evidence to
justify the override. You have no new
evidence. Microsoft's own agent, Rachel
Irwing, explicitly confessed to this
body, Microsoft has not yet advanced
detailed design for the campus. You are
passing a formal resolution to overrule
your own planning commission using a
14-year-old map to erase needed
residential housing for a corporate
ghost project. As Councilman Wolf
questioned regarding this massive
undefined timeline, if this is so far
away, why are we doing it? Why don't we
deny this annexation and then let the
council that's in place 5 years from
now, 10 years from now deal with all of
these issues? You cannot legally
overrule a planning denial without a
site plan. Passing this resolution
codifies an arbitrary and capricious
abuse of discretion into the permanent
record. I demand a no vote. Thank you,
>> Jennifer. Anyone else online?
>> All right, we'll close the online
comments. We'll open it up to discussion
in the in the uh room. Anyone here would
like to comment on this item?
Mr. Evans,
President, council members, Brad Evans,
AVI, agent for the applicant. Uh, I'll
be real brief because I know this is two
weeks looking to be postponed, but this
area was never in the residential area.
So, just wanted to make that clear that
this is not a change from residential to
a commercial area. it was agricultural
rule as the existing on the existing
map. So um and then it did um this one
did pass on a three it got three votes.
There were five planning commission
members there and it got three votes but
by state statute it has to have a
majority of the planning commission
members which is since it's a seven
person board uh it failed to meet the
majority of a full board that was there.
So, just wanted to clear up a couple
items on that.
>> Thank you, Mr. Emmens. Appreciate that.
Any other comments? Any other
testimony? Hearing none, we'll close
public comment and we'll bring it up for
a motion.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt
and I so move.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Mr. President, I move to postpone until
the July 13, 2026 meeting of the
governing body. Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Second uh by Dr. Hmons to postpone.
Discussion on the postponement.
>> Discussion.
Uh Councilman Labour.
>> Could [clears throat] we have an
explanation of uh the move to postpone?
>> My my understanding it's a timing issue.
Uh but u Mr. White might be able to help
us.
>> Mr. president and members of uh council.
So the reason for postponement is
basically to keep the um all the
projects basically on the same time
frame. Uh this is a resolution meaning
tonight could have been its final
consideration but can't do anything when
it comes to future land use maps when
the area is not annexed into uh the
city. Um otherwise it would have had to
go to county commissioners for
concurrence as well. Did not go to them
for concurrence. it went to them for
comment only. They had no comments. Um
so that's why it does need to be
postponed, but we wanted to have
everything on the agenda so it could all
be discussed at once at public service
committee and move forward together in
the same discussion. Uh but to keep
everything in the same timeline, uh this
does need to have the twoe postponement
so it lines up on third reading with the
annexation
um of the land.
>> Thank you. Further discussion on the
postponement discussion hearing none.
All in favor of the twoe postponement
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Councilman Lebornne is a no. Uh the
postponement is approved. Next item
please.
>> Number 24. Resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne,
changing the land use designation from
agricultural, rural, and urban
residential to mixeduse employment and
amending the urban service boundary for
property generally located east of South
Gley Highway and south of the Sweetgrass
subdivision.
>> Okay, this is another um
um land use uh planning commission uh
override.
Um, again, this item will be postponed,
but we'll open it up to public comment.
Is there anyone online that would like
to discuss this?
>> A point of information. This was not a
rule.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. Um,
okay. I'm sorry. This is changing the
land use designation from agricultural
rural to urban residential. I apologize.
um and mix to mixeduse employment
and amending the urban service boundary.
Anyone online that would like to talk
about this?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller
>> and you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> All right. Um
this is uh number 24. Is that correct?
Yes.
>> Uh, for the permanent administrative
record, Charles Miller, my testimony is
strictly gerine to agenda item number
24, the resolution amending the future
land use map and expanding the urban
service boundary.
I am placing a formal constructive
notice on the record that this amendment
constitutes illegal spot zoning and a
gross violation of administrative due
process. You are right rewriting the
constitutional master plan of Cheyenne
to execute a corporate land grab. Your
own planners refused to endorse this.
The record reflects that the planning
commission failed to approve this map
amendment. Why? Because your own city
planner, Connor White, testified that
this specific MA map alteration would
remove areas from anticipated
residential development at the time when
the city needs residential development.
You are systematically erasing our
master planned residential future to
build an industrial business park. And
you are doing it using a broken,
outdated framework.
Um this is the this is practically the
uh you you are expanding the urban
service boundary forcing the taxpayers
to absorb the utility liability of and
I'm sorry can you can you verify it's
3,460 acres is that what this is in
regards to
>> uh that
um I believe it is south of south of uh
east of South Korea. to the highway
south of Sweetgrass. Yes, sir.
>> Um, and so, uh, but so you guys are
forcing the taxpayers to absorb the
utility liability of all those acres for
a Phantom project. Microsoft's own
agent, Rachel Irwing, explicitly
confessed regarding this exact exact map
amendment. Microsoft does not yet own
this property. The site is currently
going through our acquisition process
and these applications are part of early
stage planning. Redrawing the
comprehensive future land use map of the
city, erasing needed housing and
expanding our utility bound boundaries
to accommodate a developer that does not
even own the land and has no detailed
design is a facial violation of the Taka
Tanga doctrine. This is not sound urban
planning. This is the cotification of
corporate capture. I demand a no vote.
>> Anyone else online? Jennifer.
All right, we'll close the online
comment. Uh, anyone in the room that
would like to make a comment on this
discussion
hearing? None. We'll close comment and
bring it up uh for a motion.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt an
I so move.
>> Second.
>> Second by Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. President, I move to postpone until
the July 13th, 2026 meeting of the
governing body.
>> Second. Seconded by Dr. Emmens.
Discussion on the motion to postpone.
Discussion hearing. None. All those in
favor of the postponement signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> No.
>> Uh, Councilman Moody and Lebornne are a
no. The motion is approved. Next item,
please.
>> Number 25. Resolution overruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
plan Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from mixeduse residential to
mixeduse employment for property
generally located between I80 and
College Drive, east of Southwest Drive.
>> Okay. Uh this is a motion to overrule
the planning commission's disapproval,
but I want to remind u the audience that
this item has been withdrawn.
Uh so we do have to introduce it. So, is
there any comment online?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Um, okay. Uh, I was just wondering uh
for for the record, Charles Miller, I'm
just wondering if if you might be able
to explain a little bit about uh what
the withdrawal of this item, you know.
>> Yes. This this
>> what was it for? What was it for? How
what was the backstory there? I guess
>> this this property um had been requested
to be uh reszoned. It's already I
believe it's already in the city so it
was a reszoning issue. Um they the
applicant uh wanted more time to work
with the local residents and so they
they have withdrawn this and uh uh may
or may not at some future time apply for
reszoning. And um just uh really quick
uh are there any other uh agenda items
that are going to be upcoming here that
are also part of that removal?
>> The next item number 26.
Um and I believe and we already did one.
So I believe that's I believe that's it.
Number 25 and 26.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Okay. Anyone else online? Jennifer.
Okay. We'll close the online. Anyone in
the room? Discussion
hearing none. We'll close public comment
and ask for a motion.
>> Mr. President, the motion to approve on
second reading died due to lack of a
second.
>> There is
>> point of order, Mr. President.
>> Uh, Dr. Reinnie.
>> Thank you. Um, historically when
something didn't get a second in
committee, the chairman of the committee
has always said for the sake of
discussion, I will move to to approve or
adopt. Um, and then if everybody's on
board, then there wouldn't be a second
now, but there may be somebody that was
not somebody from the other the
committee that may want to actually
discuss the item that wasn't present at
the committee where it didn't get a
second. So, I really do believe that we
should stick with how we've historically
handled these.
>> So, you're saying we should make a
motion?
>> I think the motion be should be made,
but then since it's been withdrawn, the
rest of us should just again not second
it.
>> Dr. Aldrich, are you interested in
making a motion? Well, just as a point
of information, um I I believe that we
have the option whether to um add the
however for the sake of discussion, I
move to approve on second reading, but
if it makes Dr. Renie feel more
comfortable, I will then, however, for
the sake of discussion, I move to
approve on second reading.
>> Is there a second?
There being no second, this motion dies.
Next item, please.
>> Thank you, Mr. chairman that we've done
it that way for decades now and I thank
you for um humoring me.
>> Next item please.
>> Number 26 resolution amending the future
land use map of plan Cheyenne changing
the land use designation from mixeduse
residential to mixeduse employment for
property generally located between I80
and College Drive east of Southwest
Drive.
>> Okay, this is another uh motion to amend
the future land use map. It is. This is
part of that same project that has been
withdrawn. Uh we do need to introduce
it. So we'll open it up to public
comment online. Uh anyone, Jennifer?
Okay, online is closed. Anyone in the
room that would like to discuss this
discussion? Seeing none, can we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. President, the motion to approve on
second reading died due to lack of a
second. However, for the sake of
discussion, I move to approve on second
reading.
>> Anyone want to second this hearing?
None. Motion dies for lack of a second.
Next item, please.
>> Next item is number 28 on page five.
Resolution amending [snorts] the future
land use map of plan Cheyenne, changing
the land use designation from urban
residential, mixeduse residential,
mixeduse commercial, and community
business to mixeduse employment and
removing the extension of East Allison
Road from the master transportation plan
map for property generally located south
of I80 east of College Drive.
>> Okay. We are amending the future land
use map. Is there anyone online that
would like to to address this?
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We can, sir.
>> All righty. [clears throat]
What happened to number 27? I'm
wondering.
>> That was on the consent agenda.
>> Oh, I see. Um, wow. That seems like kind
of a really important one to be having
on the consent agenda. But let me go on
item 28.
Um,
okay. This is the
uh future land use map uh removing the
East Allison Road extension. Is that
correct?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay. For the permanent administrative
record, Charles Miller. My testimony is
strictly gerine to agenda item 28, the
resolution amending the future land use
map and removing the East Allison Road
extension. I'm placing a formal
constructive notice on the record that
this map amendment constitutes illegal
spot zoning in a gross violation of
administrative due process. You are
rewriting the master plan of Cheyenne
and severing our transportation grid to
execute a speculative corporate land
grab. Your own planning experts refused
[snorts] to endorse this. They voted to
deny it because your city planner,
Connor White, testified that this
specific map alteration would remove
areas from anticipated residential
development at the time when the city
needs residential development. You are
systematically erasing our master
planned residential future. And worse,
this resolution officially executes an
act of street sabotage. The record
reflects that this amendment changes the
major street plan by removing the um the
ex uh the extension of East Allison
Road. You justify the amputation of this
road by pointing to traffic models run
by the developer.
Let that part sink in. Uh that is an
evidentiary fabrication. Microsoft's own
agent, Rachel Irwing, explicitly
confessed regarding this exact parcel.
We also have have not yet acquired this
property. These applications are part of
early stage planning. As I have formally
entered into this record previously, it
is mathematically and legally impossible
to run an accurate traffic mitigation
model to delete a major public street
for a ghost project that the developer
confesses does not exist on paper.
redrawing the comprehensive future land
use map of this city, erasing needed
housing, and physically deleting a
public road to accommodate a developer
that does not even own the land and has
no detailed design is a facial violation
of the top tonga doctrine. This is the
codification of corporate supremacy. I
demand a no vote.
>> Thank you. Uh, anyone else online,
Jennifer?
All right, we'll close the online
discussion. Anyone in the room uh want
to address this item?
Anyone hearing? None. We'll close public
comment and we'll ask for a motion.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt an
ISO move.
>> Is there second?
>> Second by Councilman White. Discussion.
>> Mr. Brody. Uh Mr. Chairman.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Question for Mr. Brody. Mr. Brody, what
is the Tupanga doctrine? We've heard
this several times tonight. I'm just
curious.
Mr. President,
>> councelor, Councilman White, John Brody,
city attorney, the Tango Doctrine is
juristp prudence out of the state of
California, the California Supreme Court
in the 1970s. It applies to
administrative law in the state of
California. It does not apply to the
state of Wyoming. Um,
in a basic premise, it just says that
there has to be sort of uh factual
findings when a city council, for
example, is operating in a quasi
judicial capacity. That is not the way
the city council operates when it makes
zoning uh decisions, when it makes
annexation decisions, when it makes land
use uh map plan amendments. Um those are
all legislative in nature. Um so it
doesn't apply.
>> Thank you.
>> Further discussion?
Discussion.
>> Hearing none. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed?
>> No.
>> Councilman Moody is a no.
>> Motion is approved. Next item, please.
Next item is number 33A on page seven.
Contract modification number one to
contract number 8286 between the city of
Cheyenne and Matson Brandon LLC for
public defender services.
>> Um
this is
a contract modification uh for public
defender. That's about all I know.
Jennifer, uh is there any online
comment?
No comments, we'll close online. Anyone
in the room wants to discuss this?
Seeing no one, we'll close public
comment and we'll ask for a motion.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve the
amount not to exceed 36,000. And I so
move
>> second.
>> Second by Councilman White. Discussion
on the DAS. Discussion. Counciloman.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. President. For you.
It was a no vote on finance committee,
but I received documentation. I'm
satisfied, so I understand the need, so
I'll be an I vote. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Anyone else? Uh, Councilman
Labour.
>> Mr. President, I believe uh item 32A was
pulled off the consent agenda, wasn't
it?
>> No.
>> No, it wasn't.
>> Further discussion on 33A.
Discussion hearing none. All in favor
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
Motion is approved. Next item, please.
>> Number 34A. Consideration to purchase
between the city of Cheyenne and
America's Freedom Tribute for the
purchase of a Vietnam War Memorial Wall
for the Community Recreation and Events
Department.
>> Uh this is for uh the Freedom Park at at
at Lions Park. This is the World War II
and and other u
war uh exhibits. Um it's in process and
this is the final consideration for it.
So we'll open this up to public comment.
Anyone online?
Anyone? No one online. We'll close that.
Is there anyone in the building that
would like to discuss it? Director,
welcome.
>> Good evening. Jason Sanchez community
reckoning events. Uh just wanted to make
a quick statement that before you and
for your consideration is a contract
with the America's free freedom tribute
uh for the purchase of a Vietnam
memorial wall for Freedom Point. Uh this
is a single source purchase. Therefore,
no bids were requested. America's
Freedom Tribute is a sole provider of
the Vietnam Memorial Wall. This is an
80% replica of the original Vietnam
Memorial Wall. Originally, our um uh our
friends, our um
sorry, I just had this. The Veterans
Remembrance Group um was looking to
purchase a used wall, one that had been
traveling, but we found that some of the
panels had been damaged and were in need
of replacement. So, this is for a full
brand new wall uh for our park. Uh the
funding mechanism, the total purchase
amount of this would be $275,000.
We would be using uh 150,000 of one-time
funds and 125,000 out of park
enhancement funds.
Um the in conversations with the mayor,
the governor has committed to raising
100,000 toward this purchase. Um we have
other sponsors that uh we just received
another 10,000 from Southerntherland and
uh the Veterans Remembrance Group will
continue to fund raise to backfill any
of the funds we use out of enhancement.
and I will stand by for questions.
>> Questions for Director Sanchez?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Uh Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh
President Crave through you. I was um
just curious the $150,000
in one-time funds. Are those from
what are how did we get those funds?
>> Mr. Chair, through you. U so we had
funding that was allocated for different
projects. we were able to save money uh
by getting bids that were lower than so
this is a balance and so we brought that
the funds that were available to make
this purchase.
>> Okay. and a follow-up question.
Initially, um, my understanding was that
the this entire project was going to be
donated or done through donations, and I
did have a member of the public, um,
approach me and and talk about that
there are lots of other things, uh, to
honor veterans that we've done in our
community. In fact, I have a little list
here of a request from Saturday's
Council on Coffee that um people would
like to [clears throat] see like
honoring the Navy and such. But in the
past, we've and Mr. Galvati I know is
here. We've had to raise money for the
little statue uh the bronze across the
street that um council former Councilman
Johnson um raised money for. I'm just
wondering
and you said they're going to raise
money to
replace the back fill to backfill
whatever they can out of the $125,000,
but the other $150,000 onetime funds um
will will just donate for this project.
Does it set a precedent for other
projects, I guess, is my question.
>> Mr. Chair, through you um
if possibly it does. uh I I would back
up and just kind of walk the council
through how all of this started. I was
It's been a long night. It's hot and
stuffy in here and so I was trying to
not go into a lot of utilize a lot of
words here. But um in 2024, the Veterans
Remembrance Group approached the mayor
with the thought of if they were to
acquire a permanent wall, would the
council support that acquisition and
dedicate an area for it? Uh the mayor I
believe sent the council an email asking
for that support and I believe we
received that. Um prior to that request
the city had rented the Vietnam memorial
while the traveling wall and we had
placed it in Lions Park on the west side
of the pathway and it it that area lent
itself well. It was it met um
accessibility um requirements and it
provided a good safe space for the wall.
Following that request, another group,
Leadership Cheyenne, approached us with
the notion that they would like to do a
tribute for fallen first responders and
a war on terror somewhere in town. They
hadn't [clears throat] decided on a
location, but that was the the the
request that they had. So, we were
looking at uh what areas in town might
be suitable for that. Not long after
that, we were uh contacted by the
Compass of Honor group. They also wanted
to do a tribute to recognize all eight
branches of the military and do a flag
display. Their request was to do it at
Civic Commons. Civic Commons is built as
a retention pond, right? So, if we have
big rainstorms, it could hold water. So,
I didn't think that was a very prudent
move. But hearing multiple civic groups
have a similar idea, we said, "Hey, why
don't we all sit down and instead of
spreading these out around town, we'll
find a location that they that could
accommodate all of them." So, um, Sam
Payne and I, we started evaluating
different areas in town and the area in
Lions Park rose to the top. Okay. Um,
many reasons. One, it's an irrigated
bluegrass area. We constantly talk about
conservation and and trying to create
more water-wise landscapes. By
incorporating all of these projects into
one area, we could reduce some of the
irrigation from the bluegrass. It would
still we'll still have a landscape out
there when this is all done, but it
helps us accomplish that goal. That area
is not heavily utilized. Sam and I have
both been here for over 30 years. We see
the use in the area. It is utilized
sometimes. I'm not saying never, but not
highly. the area where we put the pickle
ball courts, right? That wasn't highly
utilized either, but we put the pickle
ball courts there. When we did, some
people did not like that. They liked the
native grass, but it now most of the
folks think, hey, that's a good area. It
can still expand. And this area for
Freedom Point has the lends itself to
future expansion as well. for tributes
like to World War II, to the
Spanishamean War. There there there's
room to grow for other conflicts that
that need to be recognized
from that point. We did uh so we did a
conceptual plan. We held an introduction
of this for the community for free. We
had an the army band played a free
concert at the civic center and we
introduced these concepts to the
community to the council and we actually
had one of our congressional delegates
come in um and attended that event. Uh
Matt Murphy launched the Freedom Point
information page on the city website in
April on April 25th of 2025 producing
information about the project, how to
donate, pictures and of the renderings
were available. Um the Tribune Eagle ran
an article on April 25th. Wyoming News
Now ran an article on April 28th. Cave
Gab did an article on May 5th of 2025.
Wyoming News Now did another article in
May 14th of 2026. The veterans groups
held public information uh tables at
Super Day 2025 and and at Fridays on the
Plaza 2025. multiple opportunities to
get this information out and to collect
feedback from the community so that
people could be excited to figure out
learn how they could support it or
sponsor and to hear different feedback
if somebody had a different idea. Uh
we're willing to hear that. But I would
say that Lions Park in the area that we
chose lends itself to to do this tribute
uh to honor all of our veterans, to
honor our our first responders. Um, so
police are going to be recognized, fire
recognized, all of our military. Um,
that's what you see taking place on the
east side of the path right now. We're
talking about purchasing the Vietnam
Memorial Wall for the west side of the
path. So I've heard people say the that
we're doing this, but we already started
on the project. Well, they're kind of
two separate things, but it ties
together in the for the entirety of the
project.
Um, one of the challenges we have I hear
at the council and I know as a
department director is how do you get
information out to everyone so that no
one can say they weren't aware? And I
just rattled off the multiple times that
we've had public events to give this
information. I don't know what else we
can do. I have banners that have been
out at the park since October
highlighting this is the future home of
here's a QR code so that you can reach
out and talk to us. I've had people
call, some people have talked to me
about different options or different
ideas, but the majority of the
community, especially our veteran
community, are ecstatic about the the
location. And so, I hope I've answered
all your questions.
>> Just one follow-up question from
President Crave. Do you can you tell us
how much has been collected to date and
how do people go about donating if they
would still are you still willing to
take donations and how do people go
about doing that?
>> Absolutely. So again, if you go to the
city's website and you go to the Freedom
Point uh link, you can you could uh
donate there and get information. The
Veterans Remembrance Group, ALF is here
behind me, uh they've raised over
$75,000 toward the Vietnam wall already.
Leadership Cheyenne raised over $66,000
for the war on terror monument that was
placed at Lance Park last week. The
Compass of Honor group has raised over
47,000 and the Wyoming Law Enforcement
Memorial Group has raised over 80,000
toward their monument.
Thank you, director. Any further
questions for director Sanchez?
Thank you, sir. Welcome.
Please turn that on so the green light
comes on on on the dis the microphone.
There you go.
>> Got a big mouth. [laughter]
>> Please identify yourself for us.
>> Uh Gordon Al Parks.
>> I'm not the elf that owns the bar. I'm
the other white meat.
Um, me and my wife started this a little
over two years ago.
Um, I know none of you guys here are
veterans and that's cool, but there's
58,479
names that's going to be on that Vietnam
wall. We owe them that. We have a place
in Cheyana to memorialize them, our
fallen police, our firefighters.
Any anybody that man and woman that's
ever served this country.
Um, I beat these streets for months and
and couple years to raise what I could.
I had a lot of corporations say, "We're
going to do this, do that." And they
didn't. Anybody in politics knows if you
can get 20% of the people, then you're
doing good.
[snorts] We need this park.
This park will also be beneficial to our
city. The I can promise you this will
bring people from the surrounding states
to the Dakotas. They will plan a weekend
to come visit this Vietnam wall and the
rest of this memorial park. It ain't
just about the wall. They'll come here.
This is the third largest Vietnam wall
replica in our country.
Nothing bigger this side of Missouri.
nothing. People will come because they
can't just get up and go to DC to see
the the Vietnam War. They can't just get
up and go to Missouri to see that
Vietnam wall.
They might only be here for a day, but
they're going to need gas to get back
home. They're going to want food while
they're downtown eating. They're going
to want to walk our shops and see the
beauty of the city. Even if they're here
for one day, that's going to bring
revenue into the city. I don't want to
use my veterans for revenue. I'm just
making a fact. This will help the city.
Also,
um I'm well known in this city, me and
my wife, for what we do for veterans.
And every veteran that I know in this
city
is ecstatic over this park.
Um it's going to be a beautiful thing.
It ain't sure ain't going to be no
eyesore. And to the few Karens, I got no
other way to say that to be nicely that
want to bring up this that or the other,
you know, do they have anybody on that
wall? I got four of my friends that I
used to play stickball with, they're on
that wall.
And when I go to
when I go to DC every year to Arlington
and the Vietnam War in DC, which I'll be
going in August every year, me and my
wife goes and place 49 flowers in
Arlington for people all over this city
that asked us to do that.
That's how much this monument will mean.
Please, I beg of you for every veteran
in this city and every 58,479
men and women on that wall, please pass
this. We need this. I promise each and
every one of you sitting here. I will
still work to raise money.
Um, anything I raise here out goes back
to the city, you know. So, that money
will eventually come back to
um I don't know all this stuff, Jason.
And I I don't know all this stuff. I'm
an old plumber, but the money will come
back. Our governor has pretty much told
me he's at 200,000, but he's only
personally got the 100,000 so far. So
unless it's in his hand, you know, and
that's with any of us, please vote this.
Please, for every veteran in this city
and the state, and not just our city,
this is our state. Um, it's it's going
to be a beautiful thing. Thank you for
your time.
>> Thank you very much.
Uh, Dr. Aldrich,
>> President Crave, through you. I just
want to say that as a daughter of a
Vietnam veteran, thank you.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Please
start this.
[laughter]
>> Please. Is he still with us? Ma'am,
your flag sent to us from all over this
country. No longer flying in honor. We
start to keep this flag in service. My
wife and I have given out over 14,000 of
them. And please accept this on behalf
of your father.
give this to him and let him know ma'am
that we appreciate the freedoms he has
given us in this country. We will not
forget him.
>> Thank you and welcome.
>> Thank you ma'am.
>> Thank you very much sir.
>> Any further discussion
>> Mr. President
public discussion?
>> Oh I'm sorry.
>> Oh I'm I'm sorry. Go ahead Sophia.
>> Hello. Good evening. Um Sophia Maize and
tonight I'm speaking to you all as a W
one resident. Um and uh I want I don't
know how I can compete with that. Um
last speaker uh but I would like to show
my support for this project and uh this
contract. I was a part of the leadership
Cheyenne class that um started the
global war on terror memorial that was
installed last week on Tuesday. Um I
personally have not had time to go out
there, but I plan on going out there
hopefully this weekend to see to see how
how it looks. Um, but I do I do want to
talk about how we came to this this
project. You know, as uh director
Sanchez had talked about, we had wanted
to find a way to memorialize and to pay
tribute to those who serve our country
and our community. Um, we had several
military men within our class. We had
Sheriff Kak and a few others um that
were had been in service and this was at
the top of the list. Um, as we decided
to figure out or as we decided where and
what we would do, um, this opportunity
came to us and it was a partnership that
was most advantageous in terms of how
much we could raise for this project.
But partnering with the city could make
it expand to um, what we wanted to see
as a class, but also for other community
groups um, throughout the area. Um
coming to the Army Field Band
presentation and and um performance on
April 22nd last year was really amazing
to see. Um I passed out a lot of tickets
myself. They were free. Um and a lot of
my co-workers and their families came um
both with veterans as parents,
grandparents, but also those who had
served and whose children are now
serving. Um and it was just a really
beautiful event and a lot of positive
feedback from that as well.
this um the location at Lions Park is um
I believe is the best location in this
community. Uh the tourist and act active
nature of this park including the
amenities like Botanic Gardens uh Kuanas
community area and directly across from
Frontier Park um lends itself to this
type of of amenity. It does remind me,
and I don't know if this will weigh you
for or against it, but it reminds me a
little bit of Central Park where you
have a lot of that natural space, a lot
of the green space, but amenities
throughout, and that's what keeps people
going back. And um it is one of those
just kind of all-around um well-rounded
experiences.
um Freedom Point and it starting with
the Vietnam wall is not only an asset to
the community and um you know tourism
and representing those who we've lost,
but it's also a way that we can show our
community pride as a military community.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Further discussion um in the
room. Yes, sir. Welcome.
>> Uh good evening. I'm Tyler Nef. uh
Cheyenne resident and I also serve with
the Wyoming Army National Guard uh first
sergeant for cowboy aviation. Um so the
Vietnam Memorial uh I think is great for
our community to have. I think this
whole Freedom Point is amazing to have
right at Lions Park. I know that drill
weekend comes you have JFRC the 115th.
If you guys are familiar with the
National Guard footprint, it is right
outside of gate 5. Um, a lot of the PT
we do on drill weekend where we bring in
all our younger soldiers, we take them
to Lions Park, we run that little loop
with them. Um, having something like
Freedom Point there to stop and have the
education piece of the history. Um, and
really reflect on why they're serving.
Uh, as a first sergeant, I couldn't ask
for more. just something to uh really
instill service into these young guys
that come in that you know sometimes
they just join for college that's great
but if you can you know you have them
for four years if you can instill that
service with them um they stick it out
for 20 years and they they become crazy
uh great members of society so um the
location Lions Park I really think it'd
be a missed opportunity to move it
anywhere else in the city Right outside
of gate five, you're going to have FE
Warren. All the airmen are going to be
coming out um right next to Cheyenne
Frontier Days. So, the tourism you have
during that going right there to see
that that beautiful thing you're putting
up. So, um I'm a strong advocate for
keeping it and definitely for getting
that uh Vietnam memorial placed in. So,
I just wanted to uh stay late tonight
and uh voice my opinion and show you
guys that there is a lot of support for
this and uh I hope you guys pass it. So,
thank you.
>> Thank you very much. We appreciate that.
Further discussion. Further discussion.
Seeing none, we'll close public comment
and we'll bring it up for a motion.
>> Mr. President, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to emphatically
improve approve in the amount not to
exceed 275,000
and I so move.
>> Second.
>> We have a second by Councilman White.
Discussion. Uh, Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. President. Through
you. Um, just a bit of background. I
live two blocks from this uh Lions Park
uh from actually the memorial. Um and um
at the committee meeting, finance
committee meeting last week, uh we
didn't have anybody come talk to us who
was actually representing the veterans
community. Um and um and I I thought
that was a significant missing piece and
and I ended up voting no in committee.
Um, but I promised that I would go talk
to
uh some friends of mine who were
veterans and I'm the proud son of a US
Army career officer who graduated from
West Point in 1939.
Um, and um, so I did that, talked to a
number of them and then uh, Mr. Parks
came tonight and um, he's a very
persuasive man. Uh and I also appreciate
Sophia and uh thank you sir for for your
remarks. Um so you may see me on TV sort
of raising some questions but you can
ignore that because I intend to vote yes
uh on this. So thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you Councilman Wolf.
Further discussion.
>> Councilman Esel. No
>> I'm sorry. Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you Mr. President. Thank you
for the comments voting finance
committee vote I again but again I want
to see other monuments SpanishAmerican
war because again as I said a lot of our
youth don't know the saying remember the
main or world war I as well too they
don't know the trench warfare and also
world war II unfortunately you are s not
know about D-Day or euima so let's make
sure that in the future we expand it to
the other conflicts as well thank you
>> thank you councilman Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I'm very
excited as a 66y year member of the
American Legion Auxiliary to support
this tonight.
>> Thank you, Dr. uh Councilman Escoel.
>> Yeah, Mr. President, at the finance
committee, I had asked how many other
cities had something similar to what
we're getting and uh as said uh the
biggest one west of the Mississippi. So,
uh, I was astonished to hear that just
now. Uh, and, uh, I'm sure the tourism
aspect of it, uh, we'll see the rewards
of that. And, uh, my cousin,
uh, Ernest Claude Bland, I think he was
one of the very first Cheyenne residents
that, uh, was a victim of the Vietnam
War.
>> Thank you. Further discussion.
Discussion. Seeing none. All in favor
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
U. Recommendation is to approve. Next
item, please.
>> Next item.
>> I'm sorry. Go ahead.
>> Next items number 35A on page eight.
Reappoints of Deputy Sheriff Timothy
Johnson, Lieutenant Joel Hickerson,
Kathy Emmens, Jeffrey O'Halerin, and
Mike Bates to the Laram County Community
Juvenile Services Joint Powers Board,
Anthony Ortiz to the Tourism Promotion
Joint Powers Board, Andy Mickelson,
Richard Valley, Michael Rucker, and JC
Manalo to the Transit Advisory Board,
Katie Ames to the Urban Renewal
Authority Board, and Jasper James, JJ
Chen to the Cheyenne, Laramie County
Economic Development Joint Powers Board.
Could I have a motion?
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Uh moved by Dr. Aldry, second by
Councilman White. All in favor signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
>> They're approved. Next item, please.
>> 35B. Appointments of Michael Sanchez to
the Laram County Community Juvenile
Services Joint Powers Board. Bria
Hammock and Barbara Sandic to the
Downtown Development Authority. And
Josie Mallaloy to the Tourism Promotion
Joint Powers Board.
>> Could I have a motion?
>> So move.
>> Second. Moved by Dr. Aldridge, second by
Councilman White. All in favor signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. Recommendation is approved. Uh,
next item,
>> voucher report.
>> Anyone want to speak about the vouchers?
Either in the audience or on the dis.
>> Vouchers. All right. Next item, please.
>> Revenue report.
>> Anyone want to talk about revenue?
I'm just glad we have some. Next item,
please. announcement that a Kolkata
benefiting Cheyenne area charities will
be held on Saturday, July 25th, 2026 at
5:30 p.m. in the cowboy beastro located
beside the rodeo committee cabin at
Frontier Park Cheyenne Wyoming in
conjunction with the 2026 Cheyenne
Frontier Days Rodeo. 10% of proceeds go
to bonafide charities. Announcement of a
public hearing to be held July 13, 2026
at 6 o'clock PM in city council chambers
21101 O'Neal Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming,
and via electronic conference meeting
for a bar and grill liquor license
application filed with the city clerk's
office for Cheyenne Railard LLC doing
business as the Railard Cheyenne 115
West 15th Street, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
Announcement of a public hearing to be
held July 13, 2026 at 6 o'clock PM in
city council chambers 21101 O'Neal
Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming and via
electronic conference meeting to
determine whether compliance of
annexation conditions required by
Wyoming statute 15-1-42
exist for about 34.46 acres of land
located west of Roundtop Road and south
of HappyJack Road. Other business,
>> is there anyone? Yes, sir. Would like to
talk to us under other business?
Welcome.
Mr. President, thank you.
And I and I won't be long. Um
do have handouts if you could pass them
down. Um the first thing I wanted to
address was uh
through you probably to the
who handles alley grading in the uh in
the in the area. Um, so I'm looking at
uh I think it was initially my initial
request via the the the web was on 28
May. Uh I hadn't heard anything or seen
anything. They hadn't come down to and
this is grading two alleys. Oh, and I'm
sorry. Uh Jim Ridgeway, 3615 Moore
Avenue. Yes, sir. Uh to grade two alleys
uh from Pioneer to Capitol between third
and fourth. I did an email uh with a
followup on 9th June,
9 June and uh Miss Flores from the
department verified that there there was
a request in
few weeks behind blading operations due
to other projects and they she was going
to remind them of the work and they they
still haven't been out. So, I was just
trying to find out, you know, how far
they are backed up, what the other
projects were.
>> All right. Do we still have anyone here
from um
public works? Uh Miss Ash, the chief of
staff is going to try to answer it for
you, sir.
>> Welcome.
>> Um chair throughu. Unfortunately, um our
public works director um got called away
tonight. Um, however, I would be happy
to take your phone number. I'll be
meeting with her tomorrow morning. Um,
and we'll certainly follow up with her
and then follow up with you. So, if
you'd like to meet me outside, I can get
your phone number.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Uh, the next item I wanted to find or
talk about uh referenced uh, Mr.
President through you to a police
department representative.
>> All right. Uh, and this was regards uh,
say reporting an abandoned vehicle. Uh,
what I was told was that if you report
an abandoned vehicle in your
neighborhood that that vehicle is
checked the same day, though it may not
be tagged until a Cso officer is on
duty. So, I don't know if there's
anybody from the department that could
verify that.
>> Uh, chief or captain.
We have the head guy here for you,
>> Chief. Welcome.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Mark
Francisco, Shy Chief of Police. Um, I I
think there's probably some
misunderstanding in what you were told.
We have currently have one cso to cover
the entire city. So, um, that has caused
us some delays with tagging those those
things, but the cso is generally the one
that responds to it first and and then
tags it. um if they can't, you know,
remedy the situation on the spot, then
they'll go ahead and tag it. So, what
happens is when those get called in,
they get added to a list and uh or one
cso gets to them as quickly as they can.
>> Uh Mr. President, through you to the
chief again. the the the question I have
is if if it's an abandoned vehicle,
um isn't there a delay that that vehicle
could be involved in a in a crime or
some other situation? You're talking
about a week before the plate or the VIN
is ran.
Maybe it doesn't happen a lot. Maybe
it's never happened, but that's a
question that I, you know, it given to
an officer.
>> Yeah, I would say that'd be a very rare
occasion. I can't think of one where an
abandoned vehicle was involved in a
crime. They're generally just in
disrepair and abandoned.
>> And then do you know how many Mr.
President through you, how many
abandoned vehicles were we're looking at
how far the backlog is?
>> We we currently other than our our
manpower issue of responding to them
don't have a backlog that the tow lot
was expanded some time ago. So we don't
have to wait for space in in that uh
particularly. So, um, they're generally
tagged. Five days later, they're towed.
>> Okay. And that,
>> Mr. President, through you, there's no
way that, uh, an officer, the the
regular officers
could take on those calls, whether
through overtime or some other reason or
other method. Chief, you know, if you
want to stop by the police department,
we can talk about our scheduling issues
if you want, not bore everybody
[clears throat] else with them. But uh
um we prioritize what we do. We have a
person that does that. We get to it as
quickly as we can. It would be u
probably a misuse of uh a a full police
officer to do things like that. There
there are other things that are expected
to do.
>> Mr. Dway, I will say that we just
approved the hiring of a third U
position. Uh there was an opening for
the second and effective July one that
we did approve the hiring of a third. So
it's
we're aware of it. We're trying to
address it.
>> Okay.
>> So we do have that going if we can hire
people.
>> Okay. The other the other item I wanted
to talk about is uh and this and I'm
through with the the the department the
police department is there if there is a
permit required
when a uh a subject takes down a a tree.
We're not talking about the property
owner, but a contractor takes down a
tree.
Is there a permit that has to be applied
for?
>> Um
maybe Mr. Sanchez can help us. Um, I'm
not aware of one, but I'm certainly not
an expert. Uh,
>> Mr. Chair, Jason Sanchez, Community
Reckoning Events. I don't believe they
have to pull a permit, but they do have
to be a licensed contractor.
>> Okay. No permit, but a licensed
contractor
>> in and part of that handout is I'm going
to and I don't know the process to to
make that a requirement for a uh a
contractor to get a permit. Um, if you
look at the photos that I've enclosed,
this is uh this has been going on since
Friday of this contractor taking down a
tree
uh
address at 216 West 3rd Avenue. Uh the
contractor I had uh interactions with uh
the police department on trespassing.
I had interactions with animal control
reference a rottwaller that was running
loose on my property and generally in
the neighborhood for 20 minutes. Um I
don't think he's licensed.
I don't think a a licensed contractor
trespasses on people's property or
damages property.
Uh I don't think a a licensed contractor
would bring an animal where it's just
running loose in the neighborhood.
Uh, I don't know if there's anything the
city can do. I had interactions with the
person on three different times. Uh,
telling him to remove his vehicle from
my property. Uh, remove the stansions of
a of a lift off of my property and then
animal control to get his dog under
control because there was a time for
probably 30 minutes that I stayed inside
because a Rottwaller is a big dog.
So, and I don't know if there's uh if
there's an issue where uh the process
for that it doesn't have to be an
expensive fee, but when they come in to
get a permit, at least you know that
they're going to be a licensed
contractor and that they're going to
follow, I guess, the the rules and
regulations of the city.
And then I have any questions for me on
this?
>> Director Sanchez.
>> Mr. Chair Jason Sanchez. If I could get
a copy of that, I'll have our city
forester look into it first.
>> I have one also if you need one here.
>> Okay. All right, Mr. Rididgeway, we
appreciate you bringing these concerns
and we'll address them.
>> And then uh one other comment on the the
Vietnam Memorial. I do think it's a good
idea, but I do think that uh Leighton,
Utah has a has a fairly large size
replica of the memorial uh in their
city.
All right, just to comment on it.
Thanks. Thank you very much. Anyone else
for other business? Uh Jennifer, you
have someone online.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller.
Mr. Mr. Miller,
>> me.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir. We can now.
>> Okay. Um, I've been trying to figure out
uh just what to try to cram in here to
other business, but um kind of having a
difficult time there. Um
for the permanent administrative record,
Charles Miller. I'm utilizing the other
business portion of this docket to
summarize the chronological collapse of
municipal integrity that occurred from
the beginning of tonight's agenda to the
end.
Um,
let's see here. There there's
um
the tonight's proceedings contain
documented violations that will form the
basis of a petition for review under
Wyoming statute 16-3-114C.
Tonight, this council attempted to strip
my standing to comment on public land
use legislation, selectively enforced
time limits against my testimony while
allowing other speakers to return to the
microphone multiple times, ignored my
raised hand in the online queue while
granting in room speakers a second turn
on the same motion, and had its city
attorney dismissed formal constructive
notices entered into the administrative
record as legally meaningless. That last
act is the most consequential. The Tanga
doctrine applied in Wyoming through
statute 16-3-114C
requires that quasi judicial decisions
be supported by substantial evidence in
the record and that findings logically
connect to that evidence. When the
city's own legal council predeclares
citizen entered evidence to be worthless
before the vote is called, the tribunal
has confessed that it was not weighing
the evidence at all. That confession,
combined with the applicant's own
admission tonight that the studies
required to inform this decision do not
yet exist and that no detailed design
has been advanced means this council
cannot demonstrate the substantial
evidentiary foundation that Wyoming law
requires to sustain these land use
decisions on appeal. [clears throat]
Every cut microphone is an exhibit.
Every bypassed hand is an exhibit and
every unsupported finding is an exhibit.
The administrative record is now closed
and it is closed against you guys. I
yield my time.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. Anyone else?
Anyone else in the room under other
business?
Seeing none, how about on the dis other
business? Anyone?
Anyone, Mr. President? Um, Councilman
Escoel. So, I believe this is the last
committee meeting of the governing body
we'll have before the July 1st 5:30
ribbon cutting at the Belvore.
>> I believe that's correct.
>> So, just wanted to remind everybody that
uh at that ribbon cutting, we'll be
dedicating
a monument to former
uh Councilman Scott Royel
and
Hopefully you all can be there for that.
>> Thank you for reminding us. Uh Dr.
Aldrich,
>> uh President Crav, I just wanted to
remind everyone that this um upcoming
Saturday will be uh Super Day and that
uh Councilman Wolf and I will be manning
a booth at Super Day for the city
council. So hopefully people stop by and
see us.
>> Thank you.
>> And Jeff as well.
>> Anyone else?
I would take a motion to adjurnn.
>> So move.
>> Second.
>> All in favor?
>> I.
>> Thank you all so much. Appreciate your
>> being here. sleep.